[
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Dulari Devi from Bihar was awarded with Padma shri, she is associated with",
        "answer": "Madhubani Art",
        "choices": [
            "Madhubani Art",
            "Sikki Craft",
            "Mithila Art",
            "Patna Kalam"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "ICC Women Under-19 Cricket World Cup 2025 was held in ",
        "answer": "Malaysia",
        "choices": [
            "Malaysia",
            "India",
            "Australia",
            "Afghanistan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which country won ICC Women Under-19 Circket World Cup 2025",
        "answer": "India",
        "choices": [
            "India",
            "South Africa",
            "Australia",
            "Pakistan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which Indian state became first to enact Uniform Civil Code",
        "answer": "Uttrakhand",
        "choices": [
            "Uttrakhand",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Rajasthan",
            "Maharashtra"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Deepseek is related with",
        "answer": "Artifical Intelligence",
        "choices": [
            "Artifical Intelligence",
            "Quantum Computing",
            "Space Technology",
            "Defense Technology"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Aero India 2025 was organised in which city",
        "answer": "Bengaluru",
        "choices": [
            "Bengaluru",
            "Mumbai",
            "Delhi",
            "Chennai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Rekha Gupta newly elected Chief Minister of Delhi has won from which assembly seat",
        "answer": "Shalimar Bagh",
        "choices": [
            "Shalimar Bagh",
            "New Delhi",
            "Kalkaji",
            "Moti Nagar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In which state Jaitapur Nuclear Power Project (JNPP) is proposed to be built",
        "answer": "Maharastra",
        "choices": [
            "Maharastra",
            "Karnataka",
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Gujarat"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "AI Action Summit 2025 was held in which country",
        "answer": "France",
        "choices": [
            "France",
            "USA",
            "India",
            "UK"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which country would host next AI Action Summit",
        "answer": "India",
        "choices": [
            "India",
            "France",
            "USA",
            "UK"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who was the host for ICC Champions Trophy 2025",
        "answer": "Pakistan",
        "choices": [
            "Pakistan",
            "India",
            "Australia",
            "New Zealand"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In Guillian Barre's Syndrome (GBS), immune system attacks it's own",
        "answer": "Nerve Cells",
        "choices": [
            "Nerve Cells",
            "Muscle Cells",
            "Brain Cells",
            "Blood Cells"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Quantum Computer Chip developed by Microsoft",
        "answer": "Majorana 1",
        "choices": [
            "Majorana 1",
            "Willow",
            "Lucy",
            "Maxwell"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Quantum Computer Chip developed by Google",
        "answer": "Willow",
        "choices": [
            "Willow",
            "Majorana1",
            "Lucy",
            "Maxwell"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Panchayat Devolution Index prepared by IIPA considers how many dimensons",
        "answer": 6,
        "choices": [
            6,
            5,
            7,
            4
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which state tops the Panchayat Devolution Index this year",
        "answer": "Karnataka",
        "choices": [
            "Karnataka",
            "Bihar",
            "Kerala",
            "Tamil Nadu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "A folk dance of Assam Tea Tribe and Adivasi Communities of Assam",
        "answer": "Jhumoir / Jhumur",
        "choices": [
            "Jhumoir / Jhumur",
            "Bihu",
            "Bhortal",
            "Bardo Chham"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name of new space telescope being developed by NASA for mapping universe",
        "answer": "SPHEREx",
        "choices": [
            "SPHEREx",
            "James Webb Space Telescope",
            "Wide Field Infrared Survey Explorer",
            "Euclid"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "SPHEREx is designed to create map of entire sky in how many different colour bands",
        "answer": 102,
        "choices": [
            102,
            101,
            100,
            103
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "SPHEREx will operate in which frequency range of light",
        "answer": "Visible & Infrared",
        "choices": [
            "Visible & Infrared",
            "Visible & Ultraviolet",
            "Ultraviolet & Infrared",
            "Visible & Xray"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The first woman to become the president of European Commission",
        "answer": "Ursula von der Leyen",
        "choices": [
            "Ursula von der Leyen",
            "Teresa Ribera",
            "Henna Virkkunen",
            "Kaja Kallas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the gas which leaked in Bhopal Gas Tragedy",
        "answer": "Methyl Isocynate",
        "choices": [
            "Methyl Isocynate",
            "Ethyl Isocynate",
            "Propyl Isocynate",
            "Butyl Iscoynate"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who is referred as Parrot of India / Tuti-e-Hind",
        "answer": "Amir Khusaro",
        "choices": [
            "Amir Khusaro",
            "Rumi",
            "Kabir",
            "Rahim"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The academy (Oscar) Best picture award went to",
        "answer": "Anora",
        "choices": [
            "Anora",
            "The Brutalist",
            "A Real Pain",
            "Conclave"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where is the largest olive ridely mass nesting site present in the world",
        "answer": "Odisha",
        "choices": [
            "Odisha",
            "Mexico",
            "Costa Rica",
            "Bahamas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Olive ridely is related with which wildlife",
        "answer": "Turtle",
        "choices": [
            "Turtle",
            "Dolphins",
            "Penguins",
            "Eagle"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Total population of Dolphins found in India according to recently relased Dolphin Survey Report",
        "answer": 6327,
        "choices": [
            6327,
            6732,
            6237,
            6732
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Total population of Dolphins found in Bihar according to recently relased Dolphin Survey Report",
        "answer": 2220,
        "choices": [
            2220,
            3330,
            1110,
            4440
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Flex Fuel is a mixture of ",
        "answer": "Petrol & Ethanol",
        "choices": [
            "Petrol & Ethanol",
            "Petrol & Diesel",
            "Ethanol & Diesel",
            "Petrol & Methanol"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where is Vantara, the wildlife rescue, re-habilitation and conservation centre located",
        "answer": "Jamnagar",
        "choices": [
            "Jamnagar",
            "Gandhinagar",
            "Dholavira",
            "Ahmedabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the latest NASA mission to study corona of the Sun",
        "answer": "PUNCH",
        "choices": [
            "PUNCH",
            "Aditya L1",
            "Proba-3",
            "Helios"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Cryogenic temperature generally starts below",
        "answer": "minus 150 deg C",
        "choices": [
            "minus 150 deg C",
            "minus 273 deg C",
            "minus 123 deg C",
            "minus 100 deg C"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The fuel and oxidiser combination used in Cryogenic Engines are",
        "answer": "Liquid Hydrogen (LH2) & Liquid Oxygen (LOX)",
        "choices": [
            "Liquid Hydrogen (LH2) & Liquid Oxygen (LOX)",
            "Refined Kerosene (RP-1) & Liquid Oxygen (LOX)",
            "Refined Kerosene (RP-1) & Liquid Hydrogen (LH2)",
            "Liquid Hydrogen (LH2) & Liquid Nitrogen (LN2)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The fuel and oxidiser combination used in Semi-Cryogenic Engines are",
        "answer": "Refined Kerosene (RP-1) & Liquid Oxygen (LOX)",
        "choices": [
            "Refined Kerosene (RP-1) & Liquid Oxygen (LOX)",
            "Liquid Hydrogen (LH2) & Liquid Oxygen (LOX)",
            "Refined Kerosene (RP-1) & Liquid Hydrogen (LH2)",
            "Liquid Hydrogen (LH2) & Liquid Nitrogen (LN2)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "T-Cell used in CAR T-Cell Therapy is a type of which blood cell",
        "answer": "WBC",
        "choices": [
            "WBC",
            "RBC",
            "Platelets",
            "Plasma"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What does CAR stands for in CAR T-Cell therapy",
        "answer": "Chimeric Antigen Receptors",
        "choices": [
            "Chimeric Antigen Receptors",
            "Chronic Allergic Reaction",
            "Chimeric Allergic Receptors",
            "Chronic Antigen Reactor"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "First women president of International Olympics Committee",
        "answer": "Kirsty Conventry",
        "choices": [
            "Kirsty Conventry",
            "PT Usha",
            "Serena Williams",
            "Nadia Comaneci"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was the theme for this year Bihar Foundation Day",
        "answer": "Unnat Bihar Viksit Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Unnat Bihar Viksit Bihar",
            "Yuva Shakti Bihar ki Pragati",
            "Jal Jeevan Hariyali",
            "Nasha Mukt Bihar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which city hosted SepakTakraw World Cup 2025",
        "answer": "Patna",
        "choices": [
            "Patna",
            "Hyderabad",
            "Delhi",
            "Chennai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which country topped the medal tally in Sepaktaraw World Cup 2025 hosted in Patna, Bihar",
        "answer": "Thailand",
        "choices": [
            "Thailand",
            "India",
            "Myanmar",
            "Indonesia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was India stand in medal tally in Sepaktaraw World Cup 2025",
        "answer": "4th",
        "choices": [
            "4th",
            "3rd",
            "2nd",
            "1st"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where is the headquarter of International Sepaktaraw Federation (ISTAF) located?",
        "answer": "Bangkok. Thailand",
        "choices": [
            "Bangkok. Thailand",
            "Patna, Bihar",
            "Bali, Indonesia",
            "Kathmandu, Nepal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "BioE3 policy envisioned by Government of India stands for",
        "answer": "Biotechnology for Economy, Environment & Employment",
        "choices": [
            "Biotechnology for Economy, Environment & Employment",
            "Biotechnology for Economy, Environment & Energy",
            "Biotechnology for Electricity, Environment & Energy",
            "Biotechnology for Electricity, Employment & Energy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Mechi River is tributary of ",
        "answer": "Mahananda",
        "choices": [
            "Mahananda",
            "Kosi",
            "Son",
            "Ganga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which Nuclear Fuel is most abundant in India",
        "answer": "Thorium",
        "choices": [
            "Thorium",
            "Uranium",
            "Plutonium",
            "Neptunium"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who formulated Three-Stage Indian Nuclear Power Programme",
        "answer": "Dr. Homi Bhabha",
        "choices": [
            "Dr. Homi Bhabha",
            "Dr. APJ Abdul Kalam",
            "Vikram Sarabhai",
            "C. V. Raman"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Three-Stage Indian Nuclear Power Programme is designed to utilise which natural resource of India",
        "answer": "Thorium",
        "choices": [
            "Thorium",
            "Uranium",
            "Plutonium",
            "Neptunium"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was the name of disaster and relief operation made by Indian Army for Earthquake hit Myanmar in 2025",
        "answer": "Operation Brahma",
        "choices": [
            "Operation Brahma",
            "Operation Buddha",
            "Operation Veer",
            "Operation Abhimanyu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where was the 6th BIMSTEC Summit organised",
        "answer": "Thailand",
        "choices": [
            "Thailand",
            "Myanmar",
            "India",
            "Bangladesh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which country has the current chairmanship of BIMSTEC",
        "answer": "Thailand",
        "choices": [
            "Thailand",
            "Myanmar",
            "India",
            "Bangladesh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "How many member countries are there in BIMSTEC",
        "answer": "Seven",
        "choices": [
            "Seven",
            "Six",
            "Eight",
            "Five"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where is the permament secretariat of BIMSTEC located",
        "answer": "Dhaka",
        "choices": [
            "Dhaka",
            "Delhi",
            "Bangkok",
            "Kathmandu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The Waqf Ammendement Bill 2025 seeks to ammend which Act",
        "answer": "Waqf Act 1995",
        "choices": [
            "Waqf Act 1995",
            "Waqf Act 1905",
            "Waqf Act 2005",
            "Waqf Act 1885"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "India's first vertical Lift Sea Bridge",
        "answer": "Pamban Bridge",
        "choices": [
            "Pamban Bridge",
            "Chenab Bridge",
            "Atal Setu",
            "Sudarshan Setu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was theme of 76th Republic Day",
        "answer": "Swarnim Bharat: Virasat aur Vikas",
        "choices": [
            "Swarnim Bharat: Virasat aur Vikas",
            "Unnat Bharat Viksit Bharat",
            "Atmanirbhar Bharat",
            "Bharat: Loktantra ki Matruka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who received Padma Vibhushan this year from Bihar",
        "answer": "Sharda Sinha",
        "choices": [
            "Sharda Sinha",
            "Sushil Kumar Modi",
            "Kishore Kunal",
            "Nirmala Devi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who received Padma Bhushan this year from Bihar",
        "answer": "Sushil Kumar Modi",
        "choices": [
            "Sushil Kumar Modi",
            "Sharda Sinha",
            "Kishore Kunal",
            "Nirmala Devi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the political leader popularly known as Jan Nayak",
        "answer": "Karpuri Thakur",
        "choices": [
            "Karpuri Thakur",
            "Jay Prakash Narayan",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Satyendra Prasad Sinha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In which district Bihar's State Wushu Championship 2025 was held",
        "answer": "Muzaffarpur",
        "choices": [
            "Muzaffarpur",
            "Patna",
            "Nalanda",
            "Gaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where was Buddhisht Festival 2025 organised",
        "answer": "Gaya",
        "choices": [
            "Gaya",
            "Patna",
            "Nalanda",
            "Muzaffarpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where was 38th edition of National Games India 2025 organised",
        "answer": "Uttrakhand",
        "choices": [
            "Uttrakhand",
            "Delhi",
            "Bihar",
            "Uttar Pradesh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was the motto of the 38th National Games?",
        "answer": "Sankalp Se Shikhar Tak",
        "choices": [
            "Sankalp Se Shikhar Tak",
            "Unity in Sports",
            "Strive and Achieve",
            "Play for Glory"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The mascot of the 38th National Games, Mauli, is inspired by which bird?",
        "answer": "Himalayan Monal",
        "choices": [
            "Himalayan Monal",
            "Peacock",
            "Parrot",
            "Eagle"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was position of Bihar in 38th National Games India 2025",
        "answer": "29th",
        "choices": [
            "29th",
            "30th",
            "28th",
            "27th"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "After how many years Bihar won Gold in 38th National Games India",
        "answer": "25 years",
        "choices": [
            "25 years",
            "24 years",
            "23 years",
            "26 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In which sport did Bihar win Gold in 38th National Games India 2025",
        "answer": "Triple Women Lawn Ball",
        "choices": [
            "Triple Women Lawn Ball",
            "Swimming",
            "Shooting",
            "Athletics"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "How many medals did Bihar win in 38th National Games India 2025",
        "answer": 12,
        "choices": [
            12,
            11,
            10,
            13
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "World record in Javelin throw in Diamond League 2025 is set by",
        "answer": "Julian Weber",
        "choices": [
            "Julian Weber",
            "Neeraj Chopra",
            "Arshad Nadeem",
            "Jan Zelenzy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "When is National Panchayti Raj day celebrated",
        "answer": "24th April",
        "choices": [
            "24th April",
            "22nd March",
            "24th March",
            "22nd April"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In which city this year Panchayati Raj Day celebration event organised",
        "answer": "Patna",
        "choices": [
            "Patna",
            "Bengaluru",
            "Ahmedabad",
            "Mumbai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the panchayat in Bihar that got Rank3 in Climate Action Special Panchayat Award",
        "answer": "Motipur. Samastipur",
        "choices": [
            "Motipur. Samastipur",
            "Mohanpur, Darbhanga",
            "Maner. Patna",
            "Mairwa, Siwan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According to Household Consumption Expenditure Survey 2023-24, which state has highest monthly per capita consumption expenditure",
        "answer": "Sikkim",
        "choices": [
            "Sikkim",
            "Chhattisgarh",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Gujarat"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According to Household Consumption Expenditure Survey 2023-24, which state has lowest monthly per capita consumption expenditure",
        "answer": "Chhattisgarh",
        "choices": [
            "Chhattisgarh",
            "Sikkim",
            "Bihar",
            "Jharkhand"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According to Household Consumption Expenditure Survey 2023-24, which Union Territory has highest monthly per capita consumption expenditure",
        "answer": "Chandigarh",
        "choices": [
            "Chandigarh",
            "Jammu & Kashmir",
            "Lakshadweep",
            "New Delhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According to Household Consumption Expenditure Survey 2023-24, how much is the estimated rural monthly per capita consumption expenditure of the country in rupees",
        "answer": 4122,
        "choices": [
            4122,
            6996,
            4927,
            13425
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According to Household Consumption Expenditure Survey 2023-24, how much is the estimated urban monthly per capita consumption expenditure of the country in rupees",
        "answer": 6996,
        "choices": [
            6996,
            4122,
            4927,
            13425
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According to Household Consumption Expenditure Survey 2023-24, how much is the Urban Non-Food expenditure compared to total MPCE",
        "answer": "60 pecent",
        "choices": [
            "60 pecent",
            "40 percent",
            "30 percent",
            "70 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According to Household Consumption Expenditure Survey 2023-24, how much is the Rural Non-Food expenditure compared to total MPCE",
        "answer": "53 percent",
        "choices": [
            "53 percent",
            "40 percent",
            "30 percent",
            "60 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the duration of National Critical Mineral Mission annouced in Budget 2024-25",
        "answer": "7 years",
        "choices": [
            "7 years",
            "6 years",
            "8 years",
            "5 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the launch site used by ISRO recently for its 100th launch.",
        "answer": "Sriharikota",
        "choices": [
            "Sriharikota",
            "Bengaluru",
            "Thoothukudi",
            "Thumba"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where is headquarter of ISRO located",
        "answer": "Bengaluru",
        "choices": [
            "Bengaluru",
            "Sriharikota",
            "Thoothukudi",
            "Thumba"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According Payment Systems Report published by Reserve Bank of India, which country tops in global remittances",
        "answer": "India",
        "choices": [
            "India",
            "USA",
            "China",
            "UK"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According Payment Systems Report published by Reserve Bank of India, which payment mode is most preferred in the country",
        "answer": "UPI",
        "choices": [
            "UPI",
            "Netbanking",
            "Cash",
            "Cards"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According Payment Systems Report published by Reserve Bank of India, which remittance corridor is the most effective",
        "answer": "Malaysia-India",
        "choices": [
            "Malaysia-India",
            "UAE-India",
            "Kuwait-India",
            "Qatar-India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the multilateral international initiative recently joined by RBI to enable instant cross-border retail payments",
        "answer": "Project Nexus",
        "choices": [
            "Project Nexus",
            "Project UPI",
            "Project Rupee",
            "Project PayNow"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According to Fiscal Health Index 2025 published by Niti Ayog, which state is the top performer",
        "answer": "Odisha",
        "choices": [
            "Odisha",
            "Bihar",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Gujarat"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According to Fiscal Health Index 2025 published by Niti Ayog, which state is the poorest performer",
        "answer": "Punjab",
        "choices": [
            "Punjab",
            "Bihar",
            "Kerala",
            "West Bengal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According to Fiscal Health Index 2025 published by Niti Ayog, what is the rank of Bihar",
        "answer": "13th",
        "choices": [
            "13th",
            "12th",
            "11th",
            "14th"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "From which state evidences of Iron Furnaces has been found which pushes the date of onset of Iron Age in India to 3345 BCE",
        "answer": "Tamil Nadu",
        "choices": [
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Bihar",
            "Andhra Pradesh",
            "Maharashtra"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "How much is the country's target power generation capacity from non-fossil fuels by 2030",
        "answer": "500 GW",
        "choices": [
            "500 GW",
            "1500 GW",
            "1000 GW",
            "100 GW"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In India which renewable source of Energy is being used most for power generation",
        "answer": "Solar",
        "choices": [
            "Solar",
            "Wind",
            "Hydroelectric",
            "Nuclear"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "As of October 2024, how much does renewable energy-based electricity accounts for, compared to  country's total installed capacity",
        "answer": "46.3 percent",
        "choices": [
            "46.3 percent",
            "34.6 percent",
            "63.4 percent",
            "36.4 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which country has recently withdrawal from Paris Agreement",
        "answer": "USA",
        "choices": [
            "USA",
            "Canada",
            "UK",
            "India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the agreed limit on global increase in temperature according to the Paris Agreement",
        "answer": "1.5 degree celcius",
        "choices": [
            "1.5 degree celcius",
            "1.0 degree celcius",
            "5.0 degree celcius",
            "3.0 degree celcius"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Recently India entered the elite group of nations capable of executing space docking operations, what was the name of the mission carried by ISRO",
        "answer": "SpaDex Mission",
        "choices": [
            "SpaDex Mission",
            "SpaDock Mission",
            "SatDex Mission",
            "SatDock Mission"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the river over which world's highest rail bridge is constructed",
        "answer": "Chenab River",
        "choices": [
            "Chenab River",
            "Ganga River",
            "Kosi River",
            "Godavari River"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the height of Chenab Rail Bridge from river bed",
        "answer": "359 m",
        "choices": [
            "359 m",
            "539 m",
            "395 m",
            "593 m"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In which district of Jammu & Kashmir, Chenab Rail Bridge - the world's highest rail bridge is located",
        "answer": "Reasi",
        "choices": [
            "Reasi",
            "Baramulla",
            "Jammu",
            "Srinagar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the current President of South Korea",
        "answer": "Lee Jae-myung",
        "choices": [
            "Lee Jae-myung",
            "Kim Moon-Soo",
            "Lee Jun-Seok",
            "Yoon Suk-Yeol"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Ukraine drone strike on Russian airbases was part of ",
        "answer": "Operation Spider's Web",
        "choices": [
            "Operation Spider's Web",
            "Operation Sindoor",
            "Operation Night Owl",
            "Operation Elephant"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which Team won IPL 2025 season",
        "answer": "RCB",
        "choices": [
            "RCB",
            "GT",
            "PBKS",
            "MI"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where was IPL 2025 Final played",
        "answer": "Narendra Modi Stadium, Ahmedabad",
        "choices": [
            "Narendra Modi Stadium, Ahmedabad",
            "Sawai Mansingh Stadium, Jaipur",
            "Arun Jaitley Stadium, Delhi",
            "Wankhede Stadium, Mumbai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who kept the Orange Cap in IPL 2025",
        "answer": "Sai Sudarshan",
        "choices": [
            "Sai Sudarshan",
            "Virat Kohli",
            "Shreyas Iyer",
            "Shubham Gill"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who kept the Purple Cap in IPL 2025",
        "answer": "Prasidh Krishna",
        "choices": [
            "Prasidh Krishna",
            "Jasprit Bumrah",
            "Varun Chakarvarthy",
            "Bhubhneshwar Kumar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the military campaign launched by India after terroist attack in Phalgam",
        "answer": "Operation Sindoor",
        "choices": [
            "Operation Sindoor",
            "Operation Spider's Web",
            "Operation Elephant",
            "Operation Smiling Buddha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the current Prime Minister of Canada",
        "answer": "Mark Joseph Carney",
        "choices": [
            "Mark Joseph Carney",
            "Justin Trudeau",
            "Stephen Harper",
            "Paul Martin"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where is ICRISAT Centre of Excellence for South-South Cooperation in Agriculture (ISSCA) located",
        "answer": "Hyderabad",
        "choices": [
            "Hyderabad",
            "Delhi",
            "Bengaluru",
            "Chennai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where is Mount Etna located, which showed recent volcanic activity",
        "answer": "Italy",
        "choices": [
            "Italy",
            "Hawaii",
            "Japan",
            "South America"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name Europe's largest active volcano",
        "answer": "Mount Etna",
        "choices": [
            "Mount Etna",
            "Mount Helena",
            "Mount Pico",
            "Mount Elbrus"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who among following is NOT part of Selection Committee created for selecting Chief Election Commissioner and other two Election Commissioners",
        "answer": "Chief Justice of India",
        "choices": [
            "Chief Justice of India",
            "Prime Minister of India",
            "Union Minister",
            "Leader of Opposition"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In which year Genome India project was launched",
        "answer": 2020,
        "choices": [
            2020,
            2025,
            2010,
            2015
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Genome sequencing of how many individuals has been completed recently under Genome India project",
        "answer": 10000,
        "choices": [
            10000,
            1000,
            100000,
            100
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which city topped Global Power City Index 2024",
        "answer": "London",
        "choices": [
            "London",
            "New York",
            "Dubai",
            "Mumbai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the only indian city that has featured in the Global Power City Index 2024",
        "answer": "Mumbai",
        "choices": [
            "Mumbai",
            "New Delhi",
            "Bengaluru",
            "Hyderabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the newly appointed chairman of Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO)",
        "answer": "V Narayan",
        "choices": [
            "V Narayan",
            "S Somanath",
            "K Sivan",
            "A S Kiran Kumar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "28th Conference of Speakers and Presiding Officers of Parliaments of Commonwealth Countries (CSPOC) scheduled to be held in",
        "answer": "India",
        "choices": [
            "India",
            "UK",
            "Australia",
            "Canada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the ISRO's mission to stduy sun corona",
        "answer": "Aditya-L1",
        "choices": [
            "Aditya-L1",
            "Gaganyaan",
            "NISAR",
            "Artemis"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the combined mission by ISRO and NASA for earth radio imaging, using dual frequency band",
        "answer": "NISAR",
        "choices": [
            "NISAR",
            "Artemis",
            "MAIA",
            "TSIS-2"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Trade Promotion Council of India successfully organised the mega 8th edition of Indusfood 2025 on January 8-10, 2025 at",
        "answer": "Greater Noida",
        "choices": [
            "Greater Noida",
            "New Delhi",
            "Bengaluru",
            "Gurugram"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "8th edition of Indusfood 2025 was inaugurated by",
        "answer": "Chirag Paswan",
        "choices": [
            "Chirag Paswan",
            "Piyush Goyal",
            "Shivraj Singh Chouhan",
            "Jagat Prakash Nadda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which country has the chairmanship of BRICS for year 2025",
        "answer": "Brazil",
        "choices": [
            "Brazil",
            "India",
            "Russia",
            "China"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the new member country to join BRICS in 2025",
        "answer": "Indonesia",
        "choices": [
            "Indonesia",
            "Saudi Arabia",
            "Egypt",
            "Iran"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the portal developed by Central Bureau of Investigation (CBI) India having access to INTERPOL databases",
        "answer": "Bharatpol",
        "choices": [
            "Bharatpol",
            "Indiapol",
            "India International Police Database",
            "India-Interpol Database"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In which year Production-Linked Incetive (PLI) scheme was launched in India",
        "answer": 2020,
        "choices": [
            2020,
            2010,
            2015,
            2025
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "How many sectors are covered under Production-Linked Incetive (PLI) scheme in India",
        "answer": "14 sectors",
        "choices": [
            "14 sectors",
            "15 sectors",
            "11 sectors",
            "10 sectors"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the position of India in list of largest operational metro network in the world",
        "answer": "third largest",
        "choices": [
            "third largest",
            "first largest",
            "second largest",
            "fourth largest"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where was 18th Pravasi Bhartiya Divas 2025 organised ",
        "answer": "Bhubneshwar, Odisha",
        "choices": [
            "Bhubneshwar, Odisha",
            "Indore, Madhya Pradesh",
            "Patna, Bihar",
            "Ahmedabad, Gujarat"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the resolution of newly developed Bharat Forecast system by Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology, Pune",
        "answer": "6km x 6km",
        "choices": [
            "6km x 6km",
            "12km x 12km",
            "10km x 10km",
            "8km x 8km"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who is known as the father of Cooperatives in India",
        "answer": "Tribhuvandas Kishibhai Patel",
        "choices": [
            "Tribhuvandas Kishibhai Patel",
            "Vallabhbhai Patel",
            "Verghese Kurien",
            "Dara Nusserwanji Khurody"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where is India's first Cooperative University - Tribhuvan Shahkari Univerity established",
        "answer": "Anand, Gujarat",
        "choices": [
            "Anand, Gujarat",
            "Kheda, Gujarat",
            "Mumbai, Maharashtra",
            "Surat, Gujarat"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where was Ahilyabai Holkar born",
        "answer": "Chondi, Maharashtra",
        "choices": [
            "Chondi, Maharashtra",
            "Indore, Madhya Pradesh",
            "Mumbai, Maharashtra",
            "Raigarh, Chhattisgarh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who rebuilt Kashi Vishwanath Temple in Varanasi and Vishnupad Temple in Gaya, Bihar",
        "answer": "Rani Ahilyabai Holkar",
        "choices": [
            "Rani Ahilyabai Holkar",
            "Rani Chennamma",
            "Rani Lakshmibai",
            "Rani Durgavati"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "When was Ahilyabai holkar born",
        "answer": "31 May 1725",
        "choices": [
            "31 May 1725",
            "31 May 1825",
            "31 July 1825",
            "31 July 1725"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the Indian Astraunaut to be part of Axiom Mission 4 - a commercial human spaceflight mission to the Ineternational Space station",
        "answer": "Shubhanshu Shukla",
        "choices": [
            "Shubhanshu Shukla",
            "Rakesh Sharma",
            "Ravish Malhotra",
            "Prashanth Balakrishnan Nair"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the first Indian citizen to enter space",
        "answer": "Rakesh Sharma",
        "choices": [
            "Rakesh Sharma",
            "Shubhanshu Shukla",
            "Ravish Malhotra",
            "Prashanth Balakrishnan Nair"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name ISRO Human spaceflight mission",
        "answer": "Gaganyaan",
        "choices": [
            "Gaganyaan",
            "Aditya L1",
            "Axiom-4",
            "Chandrayaan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "When was Namami Gange - a flagship union government programme to rejuvenate Ganga and its tributaries launched",
        "answer": 2014,
        "choices": [
            2014,
            2025,
            2024,
            2015
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In which year was Indus Water Treaty signed between India and Pakistan",
        "answer": 1960,
        "choices": [
            1960,
            1950,
            1947,
            1999
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The joint military exercise (Army) between India and Nepal is called",
        "answer": "Surya Kiran",
        "choices": [
            "Surya Kiran",
            "Nomadic Elephant",
            "Garuda",
            "Indra"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The joint military exercise (Army) between India and Mongolia is called",
        "answer": "Nomadic Elephant",
        "choices": [
            "Nomadic Elephant",
            "Surya Kiran",
            "Garuda",
            "Indra"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The joint military exercise (Airforce) between India and France is called",
        "answer": "Garuda",
        "choices": [
            "Garuda",
            "Nomadic Elephant",
            "Surya Kiran",
            "Indra"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Rcently launched, Stumped - is the autobiography of",
        "answer": "Syed Kirmani",
        "choices": [
            "Syed Kirmani",
            "Ravi Shastri",
            "Sunil Gavaskar",
            "Anil Kumble"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the autography of Sachin Tendulkar",
        "answer": "Playing it my way",
        "choices": [
            "Playing it my way",
            "Star Gazing",
            "Stumped",
            "Wide Angle"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "PM Modi has recently laid foundation of India's first Green Hydrogen Hub in",
        "answer": "Vishakhapatnam, Andhra Pradesh",
        "choices": [
            "Vishakhapatnam, Andhra Pradesh",
            "Surat, Gujarat",
            "Patna, Bihar",
            "Mumbai, Maharashtra"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According to UN - World Economic Situation and Prospects Report 2025, what is the expected economy growth of India",
        "answer": "6.9 percent",
        "choices": [
            "6.9 percent",
            "9.6 percent",
            "2.6 percent",
            "3.4 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where is Sepahijala Wildlife Sanctuary located",
        "answer": "Tripura",
        "choices": [
            "Tripura",
            "Nagaland",
            "Manipur",
            "Meghalaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where is International Kite Festival celebrated in 2025",
        "answer": "Ahemedabad, Gujarat",
        "choices": [
            "Ahemedabad, Gujarat",
            "Mumbai, Maharashtra",
            "Kolkata, West Bengal",
            "Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which Indian Cricket player has been inducted to ICC Hall of Fame in year 2025",
        "answer": "Mahender Singh Dhoni",
        "choices": [
            "Mahender Singh Dhoni",
            "Virendra Shewag",
            "Virat Kohli",
            "Rohit Sharma"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "First gene-edited animal in India is",
        "answer": "Sheep",
        "choices": [
            "Sheep",
            "Rat",
            "Pig",
            "Monkey"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the technology used in gene editing",
        "answer": "CRISPR-CAS9",
        "choices": [
            "CRISPR-CAS9",
            "CHIP-SEQ",
            "DNA-Split",
            "Genome-X"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the micro-organism known for their survival ability in space",
        "answer": "Tardigrades - Water Bears",
        "choices": [
            "Tardigrades - Water Bears",
            "Sea Horse",
            "Octopus",
            "Coral"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name India's first deep-water Sea Port built to handle Ultra Large Container Vessels (ULCVs)",
        "answer": "Vizhinjam International Seaport",
        "choices": [
            "Vizhinjam International Seaport",
            "Haldia Dock Complex",
            "Chennai Port",
            "Visakhapatnam Port"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the world's largest container ship that recenlty docked on India's newly built Vizhimjam International Seaport",
        "answer": "MSC IRINA",
        "choices": [
            "MSC IRINA",
            "OOCL Spain",
            "Ever Alot",
            "HMM Oslo"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Inequality in consumption in a population is measured by ",
        "answer": "Gini Coefficient",
        "choices": [
            "Gini Coefficient",
            "Ruban Coefficient",
            "Pop Coefficient",
            "Equality Coefficient"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the revised International Poverty Line for Low income countries set by the world bank in 2025",
        "answer": "3 dollars per day",
        "choices": [
            "3 dollars per day",
            "2.5 dollars per day",
            "2 dollars per day",
            "3.5 dollars per day"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "How much is the poverty rate in India according to revised International Poverty Line",
        "answer": "5.25 percent",
        "choices": [
            "5.25 percent",
            "3 percent",
            "2.35 percent",
            "2.55 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the proposed date of completion of next census in India",
        "answer": "March 1, 2027",
        "choices": [
            "March 1, 2027",
            "March 1, 2025",
            "March 1, 2026",
            "March 1, 2028"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Future Minerals Forum 2025 is organised in",
        "answer": "Riyadh, Saudi Arabia",
        "choices": [
            "Riyadh, Saudi Arabia",
            "Dubai, UAE",
            "Doha, Qatar",
            "Cairo, Egypt"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "India is not part of ",
        "answer": "ASEAN",
        "choices": [
            "ASEAN",
            "SAARC",
            "BIMSTEC",
            "BRICS"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the chief guest on India's Republic Day 2025 event",
        "answer": "Prabowo Subianto, Indonesia",
        "choices": [
            "Prabowo Subianto, Indonesia",
            "Emmanuel Macron, France",
            "Adel Fatteh-al Sisi, Egypt",
            "Joe Biden, USA"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "When was Jal Jeevan Mission - Har Ghar Jal was launched",
        "answer": "15th August 2019",
        "choices": [
            "15th August 2019",
            "15th August 2020",
            "15th August 2024",
            "15th August 2021"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "85th All India Presiding Officers’ Conference (AIPOC) was held in",
        "answer": "Patna, Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Patna, Bihar",
            "New Delhi",
            "Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh",
            "Indore, Madhya Pradesh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "How many Indian cities have been recently accredited as Wetland Cities according to Ramsar Convention",
        "answer": "Two - Inodre & Udaipur",
        "choices": [
            "Two - Inodre & Udaipur",
            "Two - Darbhanga & Jaipur",
            "One - Darbhanga",
            "One - Udaipur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which country won ICC World Test Championship 2025",
        "answer": "South Africa",
        "choices": [
            "South Africa",
            "India",
            "Australia",
            "England"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "South African team recently won it's maiden ICC world Test Championship under captainship of",
        "answer": "Temba Bavuma",
        "choices": [
            "Temba Bavuma",
            "Aiden Markaram",
            "AB de Villiers",
            "Kagiso Rabada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who was awarded as Player of the Match in ICC World Test Championship Final",
        "answer": "Aiden Markaram",
        "choices": [
            "Aiden Markaram",
            "Temba Bavuma",
            "AB de Villiers",
            "Kagiso Rabada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Pataudi Trophy is related to which sport",
        "answer": "Cricket",
        "choices": [
            "Cricket",
            "Tennis",
            "Badminton",
            "Javelin"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Recently England Cricket Board renamed bilateral test series between India and England to be Tendulkar-Andreson Trophy, what was it called earlier?",
        "answer": "Pataudi Trophy",
        "choices": [
            "Pataudi Trophy",
            "Anthony de Mello Trophy",
            "Richards-Botham trophy",
            "Wisden Trophy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the first female ADC to the President of India",
        "answer": "Yashasvi Solanki",
        "choices": [
            "Yashasvi Solanki",
            "Sofiya Qureshi",
            "Vyomika Singh",
            "Shaliza Dhami"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Census of India is conducted under which ministry",
        "answer": "Ministry of Home Affairs",
        "choices": [
            "Ministry of Home Affairs",
            "Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation",
            "Ministry of Law and Justice",
            "Ministry of Information and Broadcasting"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Bill to allow Assisted dying for terminally ill adults was recently passed in lower house of which country",
        "answer": "United Kingdom",
        "choices": [
            "United Kingdom",
            "United States of America",
            "India",
            "France"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which of the following country is not a signatory of Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty?",
        "answer": "India",
        "choices": [
            "India",
            "USA",
            "UK",
            "France"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which of the following country is a signatory of Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty?",
        "answer": "Iran",
        "choices": [
            "Iran",
            "Isreal",
            "Pakistan",
            "India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "When was Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty signed?",
        "answer": "1st July 1968",
        "choices": [
            "1st July 1968",
            "5th March 1970",
            "5th July 1968",
            "1st July 1970"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "How many alphanumeric digits is used in DIGIPIN",
        "answer": 10,
        "choices": [
            10,
            9,
            6,
            11
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the size of geographical division made for DIGIPIN",
        "answer": "4m x 4m",
        "choices": [
            "4m x 4m",
            "6m x 6m",
            "9m x 9m",
            "12m x 12m"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the rescue operation conducted by Government of India to bring back Indian nationals from war struck Iran?",
        "answer": "Operation Sindhu",
        "choices": [
            "Operation Sindhu",
            "Operation Kagar",
            "Operation Sindoor",
            "Operation Brahma"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the military operation conducted by Indian security forces against Naxalite insurgents in the border areas between Chhattisgarh and Telangana",
        "answer": "Operation Kagar",
        "choices": [
            "Operation Kagar",
            "Operation Sindhu",
            "Operation Sindoor",
            "Operation Brahma"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was the theme of this year International Yoga Day celebration?",
        "answer": "Yoga for One Earth, One Health",
        "choices": [
            "Yoga for One Earth, One Health",
            "Yoga for self and society",
            "Youga for Vashudhaiva Kutumbakama",
            "Yoga for well being"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "First state to roll out e-voting system for municipal and urban body polls in India",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Kerala"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Strait of Hormuz connects",
        "answer": "Persian Gulf & Gulf of Oman",
        "choices": [
            "Persian Gulf & Gulf of Oman",
            "Persian Gulf & Gulf of Aden",
            "Red Sea and Gulf of Aden",
            "Red Sea and Gulf of Oman"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where is the proposed CIP-South Asia Regional Centre (CSARC) Potato research centre coming up",
        "answer": "Agra, Uttar Pradesh",
        "choices": [
            "Agra, Uttar Pradesh",
            "Patna, Bihar",
            "Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh",
            "Amritsar, Punjab"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The proposed CIP-South Asia Regional Centre will focus research and development of",
        "answer": "Potato & Sweet Potato",
        "choices": [
            "Potato & Sweet Potato",
            "Wheat",
            "Rice",
            "Sugarcane"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the revised total coastline of India",
        "answer": "11098.81 km",
        "choices": [
            "11098.81 km",
            "7516 km",
            "9069.52 km",
            "10042.61 km"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which state of India has longest coastline",
        "answer": "Gujarat",
        "choices": [
            "Gujarat",
            "Andhra Pradesh",
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Maharashtra"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the primary use of GLP-1 (Glucagon-Like Peptide-1) drug?",
        "answer": "Treatment of Diabetes and obesity",
        "choices": [
            "Treatment of Diabetes and obesity",
            "Treatment of Cancer",
            "Treatment of Tuberculosis",
            "Treatment of AIDS"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In which constitutional amendment the term socialist and secular were inserted into the preamble?",
        "answer": "42nd Amendment",
        "choices": [
            "42nd Amendment",
            "44th Amendment",
            "52nd Amendment",
            "62nd Amendment"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "When was emergency declared in India?",
        "answer": "25th June 1975",
        "choices": [
            "25th June 1975",
            "25th June 1980",
            "25th June 1965",
            "25th June 1995"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who has the authority to proclaim an emergency under Article 352?",
        "answer": "President of India",
        "choices": [
            "President of India",
            "Prime Minister of India",
            "Chief Justice of India",
            "Parliament of India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who was president of India when emergency was declared in 1975?",
        "answer": "Fakhruddin Ali Ahmed",
        "choices": [
            "Fakhruddin Ali Ahmed",
            "Shankar Dayal Sharma",
            "Zakir Hussain",
            "V. V. Giri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Under which Article of the Indian Constitution can a National Emergency be proclaimed?",
        "answer": "Article 352",
        "choices": [
            "Article 352",
            "Article 360",
            "Article 370",
            "Article 356"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which constitutional amendment replaced the term “internal disturbance” with “armed rebellion” in Article 352?",
        "answer": "44th Amendment",
        "choices": [
            "44th Amendment",
            "42nd Amendment",
            "52nd Amendment",
            "62nd Amendment"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "For how many months India was placed under state of Emergency by Indira's Government?",
        "answer": "21 months",
        "choices": [
            "21 months",
            "20 months",
            "18 months",
            "24 months"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who is the 14th and current Dalai Lama?",
        "answer": "Tenzin Gyatso",
        "choices": [
            "Tenzin Gyatso",
            "Gedun Drupa",
            "Thubten Gyatso",
            "Trinley Gyatso"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the position of current Dalai Lama - Tenzin Gyatso",
        "answer": "14th",
        "choices": [
            "14th",
            "13th",
            "15th",
            "11th"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The 14th Dalai Lama, Tenzin Gyatso, fled to India in which year?",
        "answer": 1959,
        "choices": [
            1959,
            1962,
            1960,
            1958
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In which mountain range Lake Mansarovar is located?",
        "answer": "Kailash",
        "choices": [
            "Kailash",
            "Himadri",
            "Pir Panjal",
            "Zaskar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Fourth of july is related to",
        "answer": "American Independence day",
        "choices": [
            "American Independence day",
            "American Republic Day",
            "Birth of Jesus Christ",
            "Christian Halloween"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "On which date 13 American colonies declared independence from Britain?",
        "answer": "4th July 1776",
        "choices": [
            "4th July 1776",
            "4th July 1786",
            "1st July 1786",
            "6th July 1776"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "How many American colonies signed the declaration of independence from Britain on 4th July 1776?",
        "answer": "Thirteen",
        "choices": [
            "Thirteen",
            "Eleven",
            "Twelve",
            "Ten"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the last Indian warship purchased from the foreign country recently?",
        "answer": "INS Tamal",
        "choices": [
            "INS Tamal",
            "INS Talwar",
            "INS Trishul",
            "INS Tarkash"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who is the Prime Minister of Trinidad & Tobago?",
        "answer": "Kemala Persad",
        "choices": [
            "Kemala Persad",
            "Christine Kangaloo",
            "Jagdeo Singh",
            "Wade Mark"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where is the capital of Trinidad & Tobago?",
        "answer": "Port of Spain",
        "choices": [
            "Port of Spain",
            "Accra",
            "Buenos Aires",
            "Brasilia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where is the capital of Ghana?",
        "answer": "Accra",
        "choices": [
            "Accra",
            "Port of Spain",
            "Buenos Aires",
            "Brasilia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the condition of End-of-Life Vehicles",
        "answer": "Petrol vehicles over 15 years and Diesel vehicles over 10 years",
        "choices": [
            "Petrol vehicles over 15 years and Diesel vehicles over 10 years",
            "Petrol vehicles over 10 years and Diesel vehicles over 15 years",
            "Petrol vehicles over 15 years and Diesel vehicles over 20 years",
            "Petrol vehicles over 20 years and Diesel vehicles over 15 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "On bank of which river Keezhadi Civilisation was based upon?",
        "answer": "Vaigai",
        "choices": [
            "Vaigai",
            "Indus",
            "Godavari",
            "Krishna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "How many countries are member of BRICS as of 2025?",
        "answer": "Ten",
        "choices": [
            "Ten",
            "Five",
            "Six",
            "Eight"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the Indain state which overtook TB Death Free initiative in 2022 showing promiment reduction in death rate of TB patients?",
        "answer": "Tamil Nadu",
        "choices": [
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Bihar",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Kerala"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the first woman director of Railway Protection Force in India?",
        "answer": "Sonali Mishra",
        "choices": [
            "Sonali Mishra",
            "Kiran Bedi",
            "Kanchan Chaudhary Bhattacharya",
            "Meera Borwankar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which technology underlies cryptocurrencies like Bitcoins and Stablecoins?",
        "answer": "Blockchain",
        "choices": [
            "Blockchain",
            "Cloud Computing",
            "Artificial Intelligence",
            "Quantum Computing"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What are Stablecoins",
        "answer": "Cryptocurrencies backed by an asset",
        "choices": [
            "Cryptocurrencies backed by an asset",
            "Cyrptocurrencies not linked to any fiat money",
            "Cryptocurrencies independent of market",
            "Cryptocurrencies issued by private entity"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which type of asset can back a fiat-collateralised Stablecoin?",
        "answer": "Indian Rupee",
        "choices": [
            "Indian Rupee",
            "Cryptocurrency",
            "Oil",
            "Gold"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "How many days does Shubhanshu Shukla spent in space during Axiom4 mission?",
        "answer": "20 days",
        "choices": [
            "20 days",
            "15 days",
            "18 days",
            "16 days"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "How much is the contribution from Non-Fossil Fuel sources in country's total installed electric capacity?",
        "answer": "50.1 percent",
        "choices": [
            "50.1 percent",
            "49.9 percent",
            "37.8 percent",
            "30.4 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "How many UNESCO World Heritage sites are there in India as per July 2025?",
        "answer": 44,
        "choices": [
            44,
            45,
            43,
            40
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the latest addition in UNESCO World Heritage sites in India in July 2025?",
        "answer": "Military Landscape of Maratha Empire",
        "choices": [
            "Military Landscape of Maratha Empire",
            "Moidams – Mound-Burial System of the Ahom Dynasty",
            "Sacred Ensembles of the Hoysalas",
            "Dholavira: A Harappan City"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "According to Article 145(3) what is the minimum number of judges required to interprete the Constitution or hear any reference?",
        "answer": "Five",
        "choices": [
            "Five",
            "Four",
            "Ten",
            "Seven"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the maximum one-time incentive for first-time employees under the ELI scheme?",
        "answer": "15,000 rupees",
        "choices": [
            "15,000 rupees",
            "50,000 rupees",
            "20,000 rupees",
            "25,000 rupees"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which of the following countries is not part of E3 grouping?",
        "answer": "Switzerland",
        "choices": [
            "Switzerland",
            "Germany",
            "United Kingdom",
            "France"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Under which Article of the Indian Constitution can a Supreme Court judge be removed from office?",
        "answer": "Article 124(4)",
        "choices": [
            "Article 124(4)",
            "Article 142",
            "Article 370",
            "Article 356"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What are the grounds for initiating impeachment proceedings against a Supreme Court or High Court judge in India?",
        "answer": "Proved misbehaviour or incapacity",
        "choices": [
            "Proved misbehaviour or incapacity",
            "Financial irregularities",
            "Treason",
            "Breach of privilege"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the minimum number of Lok Sabha members required to sign a motion for the removal of a judge?",
        "answer": 100,
        "choices": [
            100,
            50,
            150,
            200
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the minimum number of Rajya Shabha members required to sign a motion for the removal of a judge?",
        "answer": 50,
        "choices": [
            50,
            100,
            150,
            200
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "For a judge’s removal motion to pass in Parliament, what is the required majority in both Houses?",
        "answer": "Majority of total membership and two-third of members present and voting",
        "choices": [
            "Majority of total membership and two-third of members present and voting",
            "simple majority",
            "two-third of total membership",
            "three-fourth of total membership"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which Act regulates the detailed procedure for the investigation and removal of judges in India?",
        "answer": "Judges (Inquiry) Act, 1968",
        "choices": [
            "Judges (Inquiry) Act, 1968",
            "Judicial Review Act, 1970",
            "Indian Penal Code",
            "Representation of the People act"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The term of office of vice-president of India is mentioned under which article?",
        "answer": "Article 67",
        "choices": [
            "Article 67",
            "Article 124",
            "Article 56",
            "Article 65"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The title Gangaikonda Chola was acquired by which ruler?",
        "answer": "Rajendra Chola I",
        "choices": [
            "Rajendra Chola I",
            "Rajaraja Chola I",
            "Aditya Chola",
            "Kulothunga Chola I"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The Aadi Thiruvathirai Festival celebrates the birth anniversary of which great Chola emperor?",
        "answer": "Rajendra Chola I",
        "choices": [
            "Rajendra Chola I",
            "Rajaraja Chola I",
            "Karikala Chola",
            "Kulothunga Chola I"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the capital established by Rajendra Chola I?",
        "answer": "Gangaikonda Cholapuram",
        "choices": [
            "Gangaikonda Cholapuram",
            "Thanjavur",
            "Uraiyur",
            "Kaveripoompattinam"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the Pala king who was defeated by Rajendra Chola I?",
        "answer": "Mahipala I",
        "choices": [
            "Mahipala I",
            "Devapala",
            "Rajyapala",
            "Gopala I"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the first state in India to introduce an e-voting system for urban local body elections",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Kerala",
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Karnataka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who has won the Sahitya Akademi Yuva Puraskar 2025 for Maithili language",
        "answer": "Neha Jha Mani for Benaras Aa Hum",
        "choices": [
            "Neha Jha Mani for Benaras Aa Hum",
            "Sushil Shukla for Ek Batey Bara",
            "Advait Kottary for Siddhartha",
            "Parvati Tirkey for Phir Ugna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who has won the Sahitya Akademi Bal Puraskar 2025 for Maithili language",
        "answer": "Munni Kamat for Chukka",
        "choices": [
            "Munni Kamat for Chukka",
            "Neha Jha Mani for Benaras Aa Hum",
            "Advait Kottary for Siddhartha",
            "Parvati Tirkey for Phir Ugna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In which city has Chief Minister of Bihar recently inaugurated Bikram Lock Canal Bank solar power project",
        "answer": "Patna",
        "choices": [
            "Patna",
            "Muzaffarpur",
            "Darbhanga",
            "Jamui"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What does NISAR stand for?",
        "answer": "NASA-ISRO Synthetic Aperture Radar",
        "choices": [
            "NASA-ISRO Synthetic Aperture Radar",
            "National Integrated Sattellite for Atmospheric Research",
            "New Indian Satellite for Advanced Remote Sensing",
            "National Indian Space Agency Radar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which launch vehicle was used to carry the NISAR satellite into orbit?",
        "answer": "GSLV-F16",
        "choices": [
            "GSLV-F16",
            "Falcon 9",
            "Araine 5",
            "PSLV-C50"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "NISAR employs a dual-frequency Synthtic Aperture Radar (SAR) system. Which two radar bands does it utilize?",
        "answer": "L-band and S-band",
        "choices": [
            "L-band and S-band",
            "Ku-band and Ka-band",
            "P-band and V-band",
            "X-band and C-band"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Among the two bands that NISAR utilises which one is provided by NASA?",
        "answer": "L-Band",
        "choices": [
            "L-Band",
            "S-Band",
            "X-Band",
            "C-Band"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Among the two bands that NISAR utilises which one is provided by ISRO?",
        "answer": "S-Band",
        "choices": [
            "S-Band",
            "L-Band",
            "X-Band",
            "C-Band"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the approximate revisit cycle of the NISAR satellite, meaning how often it scans nearly all of Earth's land and ice surfaces?",
        "answer": "Every 12 days",
        "choices": [
            "Every 12 days",
            "Every 6 months",
            "Once a year",
            "Every 24 hours"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which article of Constitution of India empowers the Election Commission to undertake the Special Intensive Revision (SIR) of electoral rolls in states like Bihar?",
        "answer": "Article 324",
        "choices": [
            "Article 324",
            "Article 423",
            "Article 234",
            "Article 342"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was the magnitude of the recent earthquake that struck off Russia's eastern Kamchatka Peninsula?",
        "answer": 8.8,
        "choices": [
            8.8,
            9.5,
            9.1,
            8.2
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The recent earthquake that struck off Russia's eastern Kamchatka Peninsula is part of which seismic active region?",
        "answer": "Circum-Pacific Belt or Ring of Fire",
        "choices": [
            "Circum-Pacific Belt or Ring of Fire",
            "Alpide Belt",
            "Mid-Atlantic Ridge",
            "San Andreas Fault Zone"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Shibu Soren was popularly known by which of the following nicknames?",
        "answer": "Dishom Guru",
        "choices": [
            "Dishom Guru",
            "Loknayak",
            "Netaji",
            "Janayak"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who among the following is one of the founders of the Jharkhand Mukti Morcha?",
        "answer": "Shibu Shoren",
        "choices": [
            "Shibu Shoren",
            "Hemant Soren",
            "Jaipal Singh Munda",
            "Rajendra Prasad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "On which date was Jharkhand officially formed as a separate state?",
        "answer": "15th November 2000",
        "choices": [
            "15th November 2000",
            "15th August 1999",
            "26th January 2001",
            "2nd October 2000"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Legislative Assemby of which state or UT in India has become completely solar-powered recently",
        "answer": "Delhi",
        "choices": [
            "Delhi",
            "Bihar",
            "Gujarat",
            "Lakshadweep"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which indigenous surface-to-air missile system was effective in a layered defense grid during Operation Sindoor?",
        "answer": "Akash",
        "choices": [
            "Akash",
            "BrahMos",
            "Prithvi",
            "Agni"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the latest release model of chatGPT",
        "answer": "GPT-5",
        "choices": [
            "GPT-5",
            "GPT-4",
            "chatGPT Agent",
            "GPT-4o"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "M.S. Swaminathan is best known for his contribution to which field?",
        "answer": "Green Revolution in India",
        "choices": [
            "Green Revolution in India",
            "Information Technology",
            "Space Science",
            "Indian Freedom Struggle"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who is known as the ‘Father of the Green Revolution in India’?",
        "answer": "M S Swaminathan",
        "choices": [
            "M S Swaminathan",
            "Norman Borlaug",
            "Verghese Kurien",
            "C Subramaniam"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which National Sports Policy does NSP 2025 replace?",
        "answer": 2001,
        "choices": [
            2001,
            2010,
            2015,
            1992
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where was Asia Rugby Under-20 Sevens Championship hosted?",
        "answer": "Rajgir, Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Rajgir, Bihar",
            "Mumbai, Maharashtra",
            "Delhi",
            "Bhubaneswar, Odisha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What percentage of seats does the Women’s Reservation Bill propose to reserve for women in Parliament and State Assemblies?",
        "answer": "33 percent",
        "choices": [
            "33 percent",
            "50 percent",
            "25 percent",
            "45 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which of the following books by George Orwell is a satirical allegory of the Russian Revolution and the rise of Stalinism?",
        "answer": "Animal Farm",
        "choices": [
            "Animal Farm",
            "Nineteen Eighty-Four",
            "Homage to Catalonia",
            "Down and Out in Paris and London"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "George Orwell was the pen name of which British writer?",
        "answer": "Eric Arthur Blair",
        "choices": [
            "Eric Arthur Blair",
            "Thomas Hardy",
            "Rudyard Kipling",
            "W H Auden"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the birthplace of George Orwell?",
        "answer": "Motihari, Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Motihari, Bihar",
            "London, UK",
            "Patna, Bihar",
            "Kolkata, West Bengal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Padma Shree awardee Baua Devi is associated with which art form?",
        "answer": "Mithila Painting",
        "choices": [
            "Mithila Painting",
            "Sikki Craft",
            "Patna Kalam",
            "Manjusha Art"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the author of the book Street Vendor to Bureaucrat recently released by Governor of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Manoj Kumar Rai",
        "choices": [
            "Manoj Kumar Rai",
            "Arif Mohammed Khan",
            "Amitava Kumar",
            "Siddhartha Chaudhury"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which of the following is the most recent product from Bihar to have received a Geographical Indication (GI) tag?",
        "answer": "Gaya Pattharkatti Stone Craft",
        "choices": [
            "Gaya Pattharkatti Stone Craft",
            "Madhubani Paintings",
            "Katarni Rice",
            "Shahi Litchi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The Government of Bihar launched the Bihari Yoddha Samman scheme to encourage citizens to report",
        "answer": "Illegal Sand Mining",
        "choices": [
            "Illegal Sand Mining",
            "Tax Evasion",
            "Child Labour",
            "Human Trafficking"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who launched the Bihari Yoddha Samman scheme in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Mines & Geology Department, Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Mines & Geology Department, Bihar",
            "Bihar Police Department",
            "Panchayati Raj Department",
            "Forest & Environment Department"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Along which river and in which district is the planned incubation centre for gharials and turtles being established?",
        "answer": "Gandak River, Bettiah (West Champaran)",
        "choices": [
            "Gandak River, Bettiah (West Champaran)",
            "Ganga River, Bhagalpur",
            "Kosi River, Darbhanga",
            "Sone River, Rohtas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What makes the Gandak River significant for gharial conservation in India?",
        "answer": "It is the second most successful gharial breeding site after Chambal",
        "choices": [
            "It is the second most successful gharial breeding site after Chambal",
            "It has the largest dolphin population in India",
            "It's the only river with gharials in India",
            "It has no history of illegal sand mining"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which organisation from outside India is collaborating with the Bihar government on Incubation Centre-cum-Nature Interpretation Centre' dedicated to gharials and freshwater turtles?",
        "answer": "Los Angeles Zoo",
        "choices": [
            "Los Angeles Zoo",
            "World Wildlife Fund (WWF)",
            "Smithsonian Institution",
            "London Zoo"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In July 2025, a statue of Maharishi Valmiki was unveiled in which European country as a symbol of Indo-cultural ties?",
        "answer": "Italy",
        "choices": [
            "Italy",
            "France",
            "Germany",
            "United Kingdom"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Maharishi Valmiki is regarded as",
        "answer": "The Adi Kavi (first poet) of Sanskrit literature",
        "choices": [
            "The Adi Kavi (first poet) of Sanskrit literature",
            "The first philosopher of India",
            "The composer of Mahabharata",
            "The first astronomer of India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Bihar won Gold at the ET Government Digitech Awards 2025 for which of the following initiatives?",
        "answer": "Bihar Krishi App and Smart Prepaid Metering",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar Krishi App and Smart Prepaid Metering",
            "Bihar Krishi App and e-Challan Portal",
            "Smart City App and Digital Bihar Portal",
            "e-Mandi App and Solar Power Initiative"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was the official theme of India’s 79th Independence Day celebrations?",
        "answer": "Naya Bharat",
        "choices": [
            "Naya Bharat",
            "Vikstit Bharat",
            "Aatmanirbhar Bharat",
            "Yuva Bharat"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The Gazetteer-cum-Atlas of Water Bodies of Bihar was launched in which year?",
        "answer": 2025,
        "choices": [
            2025,
            2024,
            2023,
            2022
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The preparation of the Water Atlas supports which major Bihar government mission?",
        "answer": "Jal-Jeevan-Hariyali Abhiyan",
        "choices": [
            "Jal-Jeevan-Hariyali Abhiyan",
            "Har Ghar Jal Mission",
            "Ganga Action Plan",
            "Mission Amrit Sarovar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The 29th Conference of the Parties (COP29) to the UNFCCC was held in which country?",
        "answer": "Azerbaijan",
        "choices": [
            "Azerbaijan",
            "India",
            "Brazil",
            "UAE"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was the major finance commitment adopted at COP29, also called the “Baku Finance Goal”?",
        "answer": "USD 300 billion per year by 2035",
        "choices": [
            "USD 300 billion per year by 2035",
            "USD 100 billion per year till 2030",
            "USD 500 billion per year by 2030",
            "USD 1 trillion per year by 2035"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The “Baku to Belém Roadmap” announced at COP29 aims to scale up climate finance to what level by 2035?",
        "answer": "USD 1.3 trillion per year",
        "choices": [
            "USD 1.3 trillion per year",
            "USD 500 billion per year",
            "USD 700 billion per year",
            "USD 2 trillion per year"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The 29th UN Climate Change Conference (COP29) in 2024 was hosted in which city?",
        "answer": "Baku, Azerbaijan",
        "choices": [
            "Baku, Azerbaijan",
            "Balem, Brazil",
            "Dubai, UAE",
            "New Delhi, India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was the official theme of COP29 held in Baku, Azerbaijan, in 2024?",
        "answer": "Investing in a Livable Planet for All",
        "choices": [
            "Investing in a Livable Planet for All",
            "Strengthening Ambitions and Ensuring Action",
            "Climate and Peace for Sustainable Growth",
            "Nature, People, and Equity"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The world’s first wooden satellite developed by Japan in 2024 is called:",
        "answer": "LignoSat",
        "choices": [
            "LignoSat",
            "HikariSat",
            "KiboSat",
            "SakuraSat"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which country launched the wooden satellite LignoSat in November 2024?",
        "answer": "Japan",
        "choices": [
            "Japan",
            "India",
            "USA",
            "Russia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The MATES scheme is a bilateral mobility arrangement between:",
        "answer": "India & Australia",
        "choices": [
            "India & Australia",
            "India & USA",
            "India & Russia",
            "India and UK"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the maximum duration Indian professionals can live and work in Australia under the MATES scheme?",
        "answer": "2 years",
        "choices": [
            "2 years",
            "3 years",
            "4 years",
            "5 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was the rank of India in the Climate Change Performance Index (CCPI) 2025?",
        "answer": "Tenth",
        "choices": [
            "Tenth",
            "First",
            "Seventh",
            "Fourth"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which country topped the CCPI 2025 ranking?",
        "answer": "Denmark",
        "choices": [
            "Denmark",
            "Netherlands",
            "United Kingdom",
            "India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who won the Miss Universe 2024 title?",
        "answer": "Victoria Kjær Theilvig (Denmark)",
        "choices": [
            "Victoria Kjær Theilvig (Denmark)",
            "Chidimma Adetshina (Nigeria)",
            "Rhea Singha (India)",
            "María Fernanda Beltrán (Mexico)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The Miss Universe 2024 pageant was held in",
        "answer": "Arena CDMX, Mexico City",
        "choices": [
            "Arena CDMX, Mexico City",
            "Bangkok, Thailand",
            "Impact Arena, Thailand",
            "Las Vegas, USA"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "India’s representative in Miss Universe 2024 was",
        "answer": "Rhea Singha",
        "choices": [
            "Rhea Singha",
            "Sini Shetty",
            "Harnaaz Sandhu",
            "Adline Castelino"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which country will host the upcoming Miss Universe 2025?",
        "answer": "Thailand",
        "choices": [
            "Thailand",
            "Mexico",
            "USA",
            "Philippines"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which university was ranked #1 globally in the QS World University Rankings 2025?",
        "answer": "Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)",
        "choices": [
            "Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)",
            "Harvard University",
            "University of Cambridge",
            "University of Oxford"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which Indian university ranked highest in QS World University Ranking 2025?",
        "answer": "IIT Bombay",
        "choices": [
            "IIT Bombay",
            "IIT Delhi",
            "IIT Madras",
            "IISc Bangalore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the commercial arm of ISRO responsible for marketing satellites and launch services?",
        "answer": "NewSpace India Limited (NSIL)",
        "choices": [
            "NewSpace India Limited (NSIL)",
            "Antrix Corporation",
            "ISRO Enterprises",
            "Indian Space Corporation"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What does NavIC stand for?",
        "answer": "Navigation with Indian Constellation",
        "choices": [
            "Navigation with Indian Constellation",
            "National India Vehicle for Communication",
            "Navigation Indian Circular",
            "National Aerospace and Vehicle Initiative for Communication"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The Gaganyaan mission is intended for",
        "answer": "India’s first human spaceflight",
        "choices": [
            "India’s first human spaceflight",
            "Venus exploration",
            "Lunar exploration",
            "Mars orbit"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which ISRO mission is planned to explore Venus?",
        "answer": "Shukrayaan-1",
        "choices": [
            "Shukrayaan-1",
            "Chandrayaan-3",
            "Astrosat",
            "Mangalyaan-2"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was the theme of the 55th IFFI?",
        "answer": "Young Filmmakers – The Future is Now",
        "choices": [
            "Young Filmmakers – The Future is Now",
            "Global Stories, Local Voices",
            "Cinema for Change",
            "Films for Humanity"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which country was the country of focus at the 55th IFFI?",
        "answer": "Australia",
        "choices": [
            "Australia",
            "Japan",
            "USA",
            "France"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which film won the Golden Peacock Award (Best Film) at the 55th IFFI?",
        "answer": "Toxic (Lithuania)",
        "choices": [
            "Toxic (Lithuania)",
            "The Silent River (India)",
            "The Last Dance (Australia)",
            "Holy Cow (France)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which new award was introduced at the 55th IFFI?",
        "answer": "Best Debut Director of Indian Feature Film",
        "choices": [
            "Best Debut Director of Indian Feature Film",
            "Best Actor in a Debut Film",
            "Best Short Film Award",
            "Lifetime Achievement Award"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who was honored as Personality of the Year at the 55th IFFI?",
        "answer": "Vikrant Massey",
        "choices": [
            "Vikrant Massey",
            "Ranbir Kapoor",
            "Manoj Bajpayee",
            "AR Rahman"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Where was the 2024 G20 Summit held?",
        "answer": "Rio de Janeiro",
        "choices": [
            "Rio de Janeiro",
            "Salvador",
            "Sao paulo",
            "Brasilia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who was the host president of Brazil during the 2024 G20 Summit?",
        "answer": "Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva",
        "choices": [
            "Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva",
            "Jair Bolsonaro",
            "Michel Temer",
            "Fernando Henrique Cardoso"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was the theme of the 2024 G20 Summit in Brazil?",
        "answer": "Building a Just World and a Sustainable Planet",
        "choices": [
            "Building a Just World and a Sustainable Planet",
            "Global Economic Recovery",
            "Climate Action for All",
            "Digital Transformation and Inclusion"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Who was honored with the 34th Vyas Samman in 2024?",
        "answer": "Suryabala",
        "choices": [
            "Suryabala",
            "Pushpa Bharati",
            "Ram Vilas Sharma",
            "Kamal Kishore Goenka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which of the following works earned Suryabala the 34th Vyas Samman?",
        "answer": "Kaun Des Ko Vasi: Venu Ki Diary",
        "choices": [
            "Kaun Des Ko Vasi: Venu Ki Diary",
            "Yaadein, Yaadein!...Aur Yaadein",
            "Pagalkhana",
            "Mahabali"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which country is scheduled to host the 47th ASEAN Summit in October 2025?",
        "answer": "Malaysia",
        "choices": [
            "Malaysia",
            "Thailand",
            "Philippines",
            "Myanmar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What was the theme of the 46th ASEAN Summit held in Kuala Lumpur in May 2025?",
        "answer": "Inclusivity and Sustainability",
        "choices": [
            "Inclusivity and Sustainability",
            "Digital Transformation",
            "Maritime Security",
            "Economic Integration"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the theme of the 47th ASEAN Summit (2025) in Kuala Lumpur?",
        "answer": "ASEAN: Catalyzing Innovation and Sustainability for a Resilient Future",
        "choices": [
            "ASEAN: Catalyzing Innovation and Sustainability for a Resilient Future",
            "ASEAN: Driving Economic Integration and Connectivity",
            "ASEAN: Strengthening Maritime Security and Cooperation",
            "ASEAN: Promoting Cultural Heritage and Tourism"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which country was announced by the World Health Organization (WHO) as the first to have eliminated leprosy as a public health problem?",
        "answer": "Jordan",
        "choices": [
            "Jordan",
            "Brazil",
            "India",
            "Nigeria"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The biennial joint military (ARMY) exercise conducted between the armies of India and Oman is called",
        "answer": "Al-Najah",
        "choices": [
            "Al-Najah",
            "Naseem Al Bahr",
            "Varun",
            "Garuda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The biennial joint military (NAVY) exercise conducted between the armies of India and Oman is called",
        "answer": "Naseem Al Bahr",
        "choices": [
            "Naseem Al Bahr",
            "Al-Najah",
            "Varun",
            "Garuda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which Indian state has introduced the concept of 'co-districts'?",
        "answer": "Assam",
        "choices": [
            "Assam",
            "Bihar",
            "West Bengal",
            "Sikkim"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the official title of the head of a co-district in Assam?",
        "answer": "Additional Deputy Commissioner",
        "choices": [
            "Additional Deputy Commissioner",
            "Deputy Commissioner",
            "Sub-Divisional Officer",
            "District Magistrate"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "What is the monthly stipend provided to interns under Prime Minister's Internship Scheme?",
        "answer": "5000 rupees",
        "choices": [
            "5000 rupees",
            "3000 rupees",
            "15000 rupees",
            "30000 rupees"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The internships under the Pradhan Mantri Internship Scheme are for a duration of how many months?",
        "answer": "12 months",
        "choices": [
            "12 months",
            "15 months",
            "18 months",
            "24 months"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Name the India’s fully indigenous, automated Air Defence Control and Reporting System?",
        "answer": "Akashteer",
        "choices": [
            "Akashteer",
            "Akash",
            "Brahmos",
            "Garuda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Nirmala Devi, this year recepient of Padma Shri is related to",
        "answer": "Sujni Embroidery",
        "choices": [
            "Sujni Embroidery",
            "Madhubani Painting",
            "Folk Songs of Bihar",
            "Civil Service"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The “brain-eating amoeba” that causes Primary Amoebic Meningoencephalitis (PAM) is scientifically known as",
        "answer": "Naegleria fowleri",
        "choices": [
            "Naegleria fowleri",
            "Entamoeba histolytica",
            "Giardia lamblia",
            "Acanthamoeba castellanii"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT true about Naegleria fowleri?",
        "answer": "It usually spreads from person to person",
        "choices": [
            "It usually spreads from person to person",
            "It thrives in warm freshwater bodies like lakes and ponds",
            "It causes a disease called Primary Amoebic Meningoencephalitis",
            "It can survive in chlorinated swimming pools"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "In the Bronco Test, the athlete runs repeated shuttles covering which standard set of distances?",
        "answer": "20m, 40m, 60m",
        "choices": [
            "20m, 40m, 60m",
            "20m, 40m, 80m",
            "10m, 30m, 70m",
            "40m, 60m, 100m"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Recent2025",
        "question": "The total distance covered in one complete Bronco Test circuit is:",
        "answer": "1200 m",
        "choices": [
            "1200 m",
            "1000 m",
            "1500 m",
            "500 m"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which year marks fall of Constantinople",
        "answer": 1453,
        "choices": [
            1453,
            1454,
            1452,
            1455
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who discovered America",
        "answer": "Christopher Columbus",
        "choices": [
            "Christopher Columbus",
            "Vasco Da Gama",
            "Prince Henry The Navigator",
            "Captain Hawkins"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Treaty of Tordesillias was signed between",
        "answer": "Spain & Portugal",
        "choices": [
            "Spain & Portugal",
            "Spain & England",
            "Portugal & England",
            "Greece & Spain"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who discovered all sea route from Europe to India",
        "answer": "Vasco Da Gama",
        "choices": [
            "Vasco Da Gama",
            "Christopher Columbus",
            "Captain Hawkins",
            "Afonso de Albuquerque"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which year was the first regulating act passed to regulate the administration of the East India Company in India",
        "answer": 1773,
        "choices": [
            1773,
            1774,
            1775,
            1772
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which year Pitt's India Act enacted",
        "answer": 1784,
        "choices": [
            1784,
            1783,
            1786,
            1785
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who introduced Permanent Settlement system of revenue collection",
        "answer": "Charles Cornwallis",
        "choices": [
            "Charles Cornwallis",
            "Warren Hastings",
            "Robert Clive",
            "William Pitt"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who introduced the system of Subsidiary Alliance",
        "answer": "Richard Wellesley",
        "choices": [
            "Richard Wellesley",
            "Charles Cornwallis",
            "Warren Hastings",
            "Robert Clive"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the leader of the Ghadar Movement, a revolutionary movement aimed at overthrowing British rule in India?",
        "answer": "Kartar Singh Sarabha",
        "choices": [
            "Kartar Singh Sarabha",
            "Lala Lajpat Rai",
            "Bhagat Singh",
            "Sardar Uddham Singh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The term Girmitiya refers to",
        "answer": "Indian indentured laborers sent to work overseas under contract",
        "choices": [
            "Indian indentured laborers sent to work overseas under contract",
            "British planters in India",
            "Indian traders in Southeast Asia",
            "Foreign slaves in India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The word Girmitiya is derived from",
        "answer": "The English word agreement",
        "choices": [
            "The English word agreement",
            "The Hindi word grihapati",
            "A Sanskrit term meaning worker",
            "A Persian word meaning servant"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The system of indentured labor was introduced primarily after",
        "answer": "The abolition of slavery in the British Empire",
        "choices": [
            "The abolition of slavery in the British Empire",
            "The arrival of the British in India",
            "The end of the Mughal Empire",
            "The Industrial Revolution in Britain"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who laid the foundation of new landed aristocracy in Bengal?",
        "answer": "Murshid Quli Khan",
        "choices": [
            "Murshid Quli Khan",
            "Mir Jafar",
            "Mir Qasim",
            "Shah Alam"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the first Portugese Viceroy in India?",
        "answer": "Almeida",
        "choices": [
            "Almeida",
            "Diaz",
            "Vasco da Gama",
            "Albuquerque"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who used Hooghly as a base for piracy in the Bay of Bengal?",
        "answer": "Portugeese",
        "choices": [
            "Portugeese",
            "Dutch",
            "French",
            "British"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Dutch East India Company established its factory at Patna in which year?",
        "answer": 1632,
        "choices": [
            1632,
            1601,
            1774,
            1651
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Where in India did Britishers set up their first factory in 1613?",
        "answer": "Surat",
        "choices": [
            "Surat",
            "Goa",
            "Hooghly",
            "Amarkot"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the British officials defeated Portugeese at Sowlley?",
        "answer": "Thomas Best",
        "choices": [
            "Thomas Best",
            "William Hawkins",
            "Josiah Child",
            "Thomas Roe"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which one of the following was the immediate cause of First Carnatic War?",
        "answer": "Capture of French ships by British",
        "choices": [
            "Capture of French ships by British",
            "Anglo-French Rivalry",
            "Austrian War of Succession",
            "Issues of Carnatic Succession"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Identify the region from where Europeans got best shora (Saltpetre) and opium",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Gujarat",
            "Bengal",
            "Madras"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "During British rule which region of India was famous for the production of opium?",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Gujarat",
            "Assam",
            "Bengal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Emperor Shah Alam II gave the Diwani of Bengal, Bihar and Orissa to East India Company on",
        "answer": "12th  August 1765",
        "choices": [
            "12th  August 1765",
            "18th  August 1765",
            "29th  August 1765",
            "21st  August 1765"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which treaty was signed after the Battle of Buxar?",
        "answer": "Treaty of Allahabad",
        "choices": [
            "Treaty of Allahabad",
            "Treaty of Sugauli",
            "Treaty of Bassein",
            "Treaty of Salbai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the Commander-in-chief of the English forces during the Buxar war?",
        "answer": "Hector Munro",
        "choices": [
            "Hector Munro",
            "Campbell",
            "Holwell",
            "Neill"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was appointed Deputy Diwan of Murshidabad by Robert Clive after the Allahabad Treaty?",
        "answer": "Muhammad Raza Khan",
        "choices": [
            "Muhammad Raza Khan",
            "Shitab Rai",
            "Rai Durlabh",
            "Syed Ghulam Hussain"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The famous Battle of Wandiwash in 1760 was fought by the British against whom?",
        "answer": "French",
        "choices": [
            "French",
            "Dutch",
            "Mysore",
            "Portugese"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which city of Bihar was made capital in lieu of Murshidabad by Mir Qasim?",
        "answer": "Munger",
        "choices": [
            "Munger",
            "Rajgir",
            "Patna",
            "Darbhanga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Robert Lytton is not associated with which of the following?",
        "answer": "Ilbert Bill",
        "choices": [
            "Ilbert Bill",
            "Strachey Commission",
            "Arms act",
            "Vernacular Press act"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Ranjeet Singh got famous Kohinoor diamond from",
        "answer": "Shah Shuja",
        "choices": [
            "Shah Shuja",
            "Zaman Shah",
            "Dost Mohammad",
            "Sher Ali"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Tipu Sultan set up his capital at",
        "answer": "Srirangapatnam",
        "choices": [
            "Srirangapatnam",
            "Mysore",
            "Bangalore",
            "Coimbatore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Englishmen made the Treaty of Srirangapatnam with",
        "answer": "Tipu Sultan",
        "choices": [
            "Tipu Sultan",
            "Hyder Ali",
            "Dupleix",
            "Nandraj"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the first Governor General of India?",
        "answer": "William Bentinck",
        "choices": [
            "William Bentinck",
            "Warren Hastings",
            "Charles Canning",
            "Robert Lytton"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which year, first Census was introduced in India?",
        "answer": 1872,
        "choices": [
            1872,
            1901,
            1911,
            1921
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who said, A single shelf of a good European library was worth the whole native literature of India and Arabia?",
        "answer": "Thomas Babington Macaulay",
        "choices": [
            "Thomas Babington Macaulay",
            "Dr William Carey",
            "Charles Grant",
            "John Elliot - Minto"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following abolished Dual Government system in Bengal?",
        "answer": "Warren Hastings",
        "choices": [
            "Warren Hastings",
            "Robert Clive",
            "Charles Cornwallis",
            "Richard Wellesley"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The policy of Security Cell or Ring Fence policy is related to",
        "answer": "Warren Hastings",
        "choices": [
            "Warren Hastings",
            "James Andrew - Dalhousie",
            "Charles Cornwallis",
            "Robert Clive"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The dual system of governance in Bengal was enforced by",
        "answer": "Robert Clive",
        "choices": [
            "Robert Clive",
            "Warren Hastings",
            "William Bentinck",
            "George Curzon"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who is considered the Father of Diarchy?",
        "answer": "Lionel Curtis",
        "choices": [
            "Lionel Curtis",
            "Robert Clive",
            "Hector Munro",
            "Thomas Babington Macaulay"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "First Maratha Sardar to accept the subsidiary alliance of Richard Wellesley was",
        "answer": "Peshwa Bajirao II",
        "choices": [
            "Peshwa Bajirao II",
            "Raghuji Bhosle",
            "Daulat Rao Scindia",
            "Bhalaji Rao"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Under whose leadership was the suppresson of Thugs achieved?",
        "answer": "Captain William Henry Sleeman",
        "choices": [
            "Captain William Henry Sleeman",
            "Robert Clive",
            "Hector Munro",
            "Alexander Burnes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following princely states was not annexed by the British",
        "answer": "Gwalior",
        "choices": [
            "Gwalior",
            "Sind",
            "Awadh",
            "Satara"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Sind was conquered and annexed by",
        "answer": "Charles Napier",
        "choices": [
            "Charles Napier",
            "Wellington",
            "Sleeman",
            "Lawrence"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The first railway in India was ladi down during the period of",
        "answer": "Dalhousie",
        "choices": [
            "Dalhousie",
            "George Curzon",
            "Wellesly",
            "Lytton"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Queen Victoria was appointed the Empress of India in",
        "answer": 1876,
        "choices": [
            1876,
            1877,
            1858,
            1885
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Viceroy who followd aggressive policy towards Afghanistan was",
        "answer": "Robert Lytton",
        "choices": [
            "Robert Lytton",
            "Richard Bourke - Mayo",
            "Frederick Hamilton - Dufferin",
            "Charles Canning"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which among the following viceroy's period the title of Rai Bahadur and Khan Bhadur began to confer to Indian?",
        "answer": "Robert Lytton",
        "choices": [
            "Robert Lytton",
            "Richard Bourke - Mayo",
            "Frederick Hamilton - Dufferin",
            "George Robinson Ripon"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In 1902 George Curzon appointed the University Commission including two Indian members.Who were they?",
        "answer": "Syed Hussain Bilgrami & Justice Gururdas Banerjeee",
        "choices": [
            "Syed Hussain Bilgrami & Justice Gururdas Banerjeee",
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak and Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale and Rashbehari Bose",
            "Syed Hussain Bilgrami & Surendranath Banerjee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which year was the Indian Universities Act passed by George Curzon?",
        "answer": 1904,
        "choices": [
            1904,
            1901,
            1906,
            1886
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who established Imperial Cadet Corps?",
        "answer": "Charles Curzon",
        "choices": [
            "Charles Curzon",
            "George Robinson Ripon",
            "John Elliot - Minto",
            "Robert Lytton"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In my belief Congress is to tottering to its fails and one of my great ambitions while in India is to assist it to a peaceful demise. Who wrote it",
        "answer": "Charles Curzon",
        "choices": [
            "Charles Curzon",
            "Frederick Hamilton Dufferin",
            "John Elliot - Minto",
            "Robert Lytton"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Muslims, if contented and satisfied would become the greatest bulwark of British power in India, who wrote it?",
        "answer": "William Wilson Hunter",
        "choices": [
            "William Wilson Hunter",
            "Herbert Risley",
            "Henry Noel Brailsford",
            "Robert Lytton"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the founder of Empire in India?",
        "answer": "Robert Clive",
        "choices": [
            "Robert Clive",
            "John Elliot - Minto",
            "Richard Bourke - Mayo",
            "William Henry Sleeman"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who introduced the system of Mahalwari Settlement in Bengal?",
        "answer": "Holt mackenzie",
        "choices": [
            "Holt mackenzie",
            "Charles Cornwallis",
            "Warren Hastings",
            "William Bentinck"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which compensation tax the Indigo farmers were required to pay, if they desired exemption from Indigo cultivation?",
        "answer": "Tawan",
        "choices": [
            "Tawan",
            "Batta",
            "Jaziya",
            "Nazrana"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Permanent Settlement was made with",
        "answer": "Zamindars",
        "choices": [
            "Zamindars",
            "Muqaddamas",
            "Peasants",
            "Village Communities"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following is correct about permanent settlement introduced in Bihar",
        "answer": "The right of ownership of land was made hereditary and transferable for the Zamindars",
        "choices": [
            "The right of ownership of land was made hereditary and transferable for the Zamindars",
            "The Zamindars were deprived of the ownership of the land",
            "Land Revenue was not fixed",
            "Abolition of Zamindari"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which year the rights of the tenants on land in Bengal and Bihar were given by the Bengal Tenancy Act",
        "answer": 1885,
        "choices": [
            1885,
            1995,
            1875,
            1975
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The system, under which the peasant himself is the owner of the land and is held responsible for the payment of land revenue to the government is known as?",
        "answer": "Ryotwari System",
        "choices": [
            "Ryotwari System",
            "Zamindari System",
            "Mahalwari System",
            "Dahsala System"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Ryotwari system was first implemented in",
        "answer": "Madras",
        "choices": [
            "Madras",
            "Bihar",
            "Bengal",
            "Odisha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When was new Enfield Riffle with greased cartridges introduced in the British Indian Army?",
        "answer": "December, 1856",
        "choices": [
            "December, 1856",
            "November, 1856",
            "January, 1857",
            "February, 1857"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following is not a reason for making the sepoys of the East India Company rebellious?",
        "answer": "Inefficiency of the officers",
        "choices": [
            "Inefficiency of the officers",
            "The efforts of the officers of the company to spread Christianity",
            "The order to the sepoys to travel on ships",
            "The stoppage of Bhatta"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Where from the Revolution of 1857 started first?",
        "answer": "Meerut",
        "choices": [
            "Meerut",
            "Lucknow",
            "Allahabad",
            "Jhansi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "At Delhi, during the Revolt of 1857, the nominal and symbolic leadership belonged to the emperor Bahadur Shah, but the real command lay with a court of soldiers headed by",
        "answer": "Bakht Khan",
        "choices": [
            "Bakht Khan",
            "Nana Saheb",
            "Hazrat Mahal",
            "Laxmibai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The first woman President of the Indian National Congress was",
        "answer": "Annie Besant",
        "choices": [
            "Annie Besant",
            "Sarojini Naidu",
            "Kasturba Gandhi",
            "Aruna Asaf Ali"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The female freedom fighter popularly known as the Grand Old Lady of the Independence Movement was",
        "answer": "Aruna Asaf Ali",
        "choices": [
            "Aruna Asaf Ali",
            "Gulab Kaur",
            "Bishni Devi Shah",
            "Annie Besant"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The revolt of 1857 at Lucknow was led by",
        "answer": "Begum Hazrat Mahal",
        "choices": [
            "Begum Hazrat Mahal",
            "Tatya Tope",
            "Rani Lakshmibai",
            "Nana Saheb"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Where did Satyendra Prasad Sinha resign from the post of Governor in 1921?",
        "answer": "Bihar-Odisha",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar-Odisha",
            "Bengal",
            "Punjab",
            "Madras"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who spearheaded the 1857 Revolt in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Kunwar Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Kunwar Singh",
            "Nana Saheb",
            "Tatya Tope",
            "Maulvi Ahmadullah"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Where did Kunwar Singh join the Rebellion of 1857 against the British?",
        "answer": "Arrah",
        "choices": [
            "Arrah",
            "Patna",
            "Bettiah",
            "Varanasi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who said, Wherever I am, there is Jagadishpur?",
        "answer": "Kunwar Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Kunwar Singh",
            "Amar Singh",
            "Rani Lakshmibai",
            "General Lloyd"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The mutiny of 1857 at Patna was led by a dynamic old person known as",
        "answer": "Kunwar Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Kunwar Singh",
            "Hyder Ali Khan",
            "Judhar Singh",
            "Kusal Singh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The centre of 1857 revolt in Bihar from 15th July 1857 to 20th January 1858 was",
        "answer": "Jagdishpur",
        "choices": [
            "Jagdishpur",
            "Hamirpur",
            "Dheerpur",
            "Rampur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "One of the leaders of the Revolt of 1857 Kunwar Singh was related to which place?",
        "answer": "Jagdishpur",
        "choices": [
            "Jagdishpur",
            "Gwalior",
            "Jhansi",
            "Meerut"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who of the following was the bitterest enemy of the British during the Revolt of 1857?",
        "answer": "Maulavi Ahamadullah Shah",
        "choices": [
            "Maulavi Ahamadullah Shah",
            "Maulavi Imadadullah",
            "Maulana Fazi-i-Haq Khairabadi",
            "Nawab Liaquat Ali"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Revolt of 1857 was witnessed by the poet",
        "answer": "Ghalib",
        "choices": [
            "Ghalib",
            "Zauq",
            "Mir Taqi Mir",
            "Iqbal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following did not rebel against the British East India Company's control over them?",
        "answer": "Nizam of Hyderabad",
        "choices": [
            "Nizam of Hyderabad",
            "Raja of Vijayanagar",
            "Polygar of Tamil Nadu",
            "Dewan Velu Thampi of Travancore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which part of Bihar was unaffected with the revolt of 1857?",
        "answer": "Munger",
        "choices": [
            "Munger",
            "Patna",
            "Muzaffarpur",
            "Arrah"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the Governor-General of India in 1857?",
        "answer": "Charles Canning",
        "choices": [
            "Charles Canning",
            "James Andrew - Dalhousie",
            "Richard Wellesley",
            "John Elliot - Minto"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "What was the main cause of the failure of the revolt of 1857?",
        "answer": "Lack of common strategy and central organisation",
        "choices": [
            "Lack of common strategy and central organisation",
            "Lack of Hindu-Muslim Unity",
            "Its effect was within a limited area",
            "Non-participations of Landlords"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who called the revolt of 1857 a conspiracy?",
        "answer": "Sir James Outram and W Taylor",
        "choices": [
            "Sir James Outram and W Taylor",
            "Sir John K",
            "Sir John Lawrence",
            "T R Homes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When did Queen Victoria declare the taking over of Indian Administration under British Crown?",
        "answer": "1st November 1858",
        "choices": [
            "1st November 1858",
            "31st Decemeber 1857",
            "6th January 1958",
            "17th November 1859"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following commissions is associated with the army reorganisation after the suppression of the Revolt of 1857?",
        "answer": "Peel Commission",
        "choices": [
            "Peel Commission",
            "Public Service Commission",
            "Hunter Commission",
            "Simon Commission"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "After the revolt of 1857, the British recruited the soldiers from the",
        "answer": "Gurkhas, Sikhs and Punjabis in the North",
        "choices": [
            "Gurkhas, Sikhs and Punjabis in the North",
            "Brahmins of UP & Bihar",
            "Bengalis and Orria's from the East",
            "Madras presidency and Marathas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The uprising of 1857 was described as the First Indian War of Independence by",
        "answer": "V D Savarkar",
        "choices": [
            "V D Savarkar",
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
            "R C Mazumdar",
            "Dadabhai Naoroji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Tana Bhagat Movement, a nonviolent movement against British rule, originated among the tribal communities of which Indian State?",
        "answer": "Jharkhand",
        "choices": [
            "Jharkhand",
            "Kerala",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Madras"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Indigo rebellion was about",
        "answer": "the peasant not wanting to grow indigo but being forced to grow at a price that was unacceptable",
        "choices": [
            "the peasant not wanting to grow indigo but being forced to grow at a price that was unacceptable",
            "the peasant not wanting to grow indigo but being forced",
            "the peasant wanting to grow indigo but being forced not to",
            "a protest movement that carried an indigo coloured flag"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who is the author of Neel Darpan a book written on the miserable condition of Indigo farmers?",
        "answer": "Dinbandhu Mitra",
        "choices": [
            "Dinbandhu Mitra",
            "Bankim Chandra Chatterji",
            "Acharya Kripalani",
            "Rabindranath Tagore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which month of 1918 was the Champaran Agrarian Act passed against the European Indigo planters?",
        "answer": "March, 1918",
        "choices": [
            "March, 1918",
            "January, 1918",
            "December, 1918",
            "September, 1918"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the bitter critic of Sir Syed Ahmed Khan?",
        "answer": "Jamaluddin Afghani",
        "choices": [
            "Jamaluddin Afghani",
            "C F Andrews",
            "Maulvi Zakaullah",
            "Shibli Nomani"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "What was the purpose of Barhiyataal resistence in Munger?",
        "answer": "Demand of Bakast land restoration",
        "choices": [
            "Demand of Bakast land restoration",
            "Muslim peasants may not be exploited",
            "Abolishment of Zamindari custom",
            "Beginning of class struggle"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Kuka Movement was organised by",
        "answer": "Guru Ram Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Guru Ram Singh",
            "Guru Nanak",
            "Guru Gobind Singh",
            "Guru Ram Das"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who founded the Pagal Panth",
        "answer": "Karam Shah",
        "choices": [
            "Karam Shah",
            "Bulleh Shah",
            "Yaduvendra Singh",
            "Swami Shajananada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who were the Faraizis?",
        "answer": "Followers of Haji Shariatullah",
        "choices": [
            "Followers of Haji Shariatullah",
            "Followers of Dadu",
            "Followers of the Arya Samaj",
            "Followers of the Muslim League"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who began the Faraizi movement?",
        "answer": "Haji Shariatullah",
        "choices": [
            "Haji Shariatullah",
            "Syed Ahmed",
            "Salimullah",
            "Muhammad Ali Jinnah"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Taiyuni Movement began in opposition of the Faraizi Movement at Dhaka in 1893 was started by",
        "answer": "Maulana Karamat Ali of Jaunpur",
        "choices": [
            "Maulana Karamat Ali of Jaunpur",
            "Syed Amir Ali of Calcutta",
            "Sir Syed Ahmed of Aligarh",
            "Hasn Imam of Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who founded Ramosi Krishak Jatha in Maharashtra?",
        "answer": "Vasudeo Balwant Phadke",
        "choices": [
            "Vasudeo Balwant Phadke",
            "Justice Ranade",
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
            "Jyotiba Phule"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The correct geographical location for the Ramosi Uprising was",
        "answer": "Western Ghats",
        "choices": [
            "Western Ghats",
            "Western India",
            "Eastern India",
            "Eastern Ghats"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Name the tribe that rebelled against the Britishers because human sacrifice system was banned",
        "answer": "Khond",
        "choices": [
            "Khond",
            "Kuki",
            "Oraon",
            "Nackda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Kol Mutiny of 1831 under Buddho Bhagat took place in which of the following regions?",
        "answer": "Singhbum",
        "choices": [
            "Singhbum",
            "Kutch",
            "Western Ghats",
            "Satara"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Waghera Uprising happened in",
        "answer": "Baroda",
        "choices": [
            "Baroda",
            "Surat",
            "Poona",
            "Calicut"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who were the leaders of Santhal Revolt?",
        "answer": "Sidhu and Kanhu",
        "choices": [
            "Sidhu and Kanhu",
            "Jara Bhagat and Balaram Bhagat",
            "Gaurakshni Bhagat and Keshav Chandra Roy",
            "Shambhumath Pal and Korra Mallaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which among the following year Santhal Revolt occurred?",
        "answer": "1855-56 CE",
        "choices": [
            "1855-56 CE",
            "1831-32 CE",
            "1844-46 CE",
            "1851-52 CE"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which British Commander was defeated by the Santhals in 1855?",
        "answer": "Major Burroguh",
        "choices": [
            "Major Burroguh",
            "Captain nek Feville",
            "Lt. Bastain",
            "Colonel White"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Mundas raised revolt in",
        "answer": 1899,
        "choices": [
            1899,
            1888,
            1857,
            1875
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Birsa Munda was considered by his followers as the incarnation of ",
        "answer": "Dharti Abba",
        "choices": [
            "Dharti Abba",
            "Sing Bonga",
            "Mago Manki",
            "Bir Sing"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Ulgulan Revolt was related to",
        "answer": "Birsa Munda",
        "choices": [
            "Birsa Munda",
            "Kachha Nagh",
            "Santhal",
            "Kol"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the leader of Munda rebellion of 1899-1900 CE?",
        "answer": "Birsa Munda",
        "choices": [
            "Birsa Munda",
            "Budha Bhagat",
            "Siddhu",
            "Tilak Manjhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Birsa Munda was in favour of",
        "answer": "Munda Raj",
        "choices": [
            "Munda Raj",
            "British Raj",
            "Raj of Dikus",
            "Sepration of Jharkhand"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which was the working area of Birsa Munda?",
        "answer": "Ranchi",
        "choices": [
            "Ranchi",
            "Champaran",
            "Alipur",
            "Balia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which territory did tribals rebel against the British?",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Punjab",
            "Sindh",
            "Kathiwar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Hoz revolt took place during",
        "answer": "1820-21",
        "choices": [
            "1820-21",
            "1620-21",
            "1720-21",
            "1920-21"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Moplah Rebellion of 1921 broke out in",
        "answer": "Kerala",
        "choices": [
            "Kerala",
            "Assam",
            "Punjab",
            "Bengal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which year did Charles Wood send his despatch on General Education in India?",
        "answer": 1854,
        "choices": [
            1854,
            1857,
            1848,
            1850
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which year Mohammedan Anglo-Oriental College at Aligarh was established?",
        "answer": 1877,
        "choices": [
            1877,
            1870,
            1880,
            1890
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When was the National Council of Education established?",
        "answer": "15th August 1906",
        "choices": [
            "15th August 1906",
            "15th August 1903",
            "15th August 1904",
            "15th August 1905"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When did the British Government appoint Sadler University Commission for reforms in education?",
        "answer": 1917,
        "choices": [
            1917,
            1919,
            1921,
            1896
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following Indians qualified the Indian Civil Service Exam for the first time in 1863?",
        "answer": "Satyendranath Thakur",
        "choices": [
            "Satyendranath Thakur",
            "Rabindranath Thakur",
            "Debendranath Thakur",
            "Surendranath Thakur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In 1890, the first woman graduate of Calcutta University, who addressed the Congress session was",
        "answer": "Kadambini Ganguly",
        "choices": [
            "Kadambini Ganguly",
            "Sarojini Naidu",
            "Annie Besant",
            "Indira Gandhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The spiritual side of nationalism was voiced by",
        "answer": "Swami Vivekananda",
        "choices": [
            "Swami Vivekananda",
            "Raja Ram Mohun Roy",
            "Swami Shraddhanand",
            "Swami Shajananada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who founded the newspaper - The Hindu in 1878, which became influential in shaping public opinion during the Indian national movement?",
        "answer": "G Subramania Iyer",
        "choices": [
            "G Subramania Iyer",
            "Viraraghavachariar",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Sahajananda Saraswati"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following repealed the Vernacular Press Act of 1878?",
        "answer": "George Robinson - Ripon",
        "choices": [
            "George Robinson - Ripon",
            "Robert Lytton",
            "Charles Curzon",
            "John Elliot - Minto"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who in America started to issue newspaper The Free Hindustan?",
        "answer": "Tarak Nath Das",
        "choices": [
            "Tarak Nath Das",
            "Ram Nath Puri",
            "G D Kumar",
            "Lala Hardayal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who founded the Amrit Bazar Patrika?",
        "answer": "Shishir Kumar Ghose",
        "choices": [
            "Shishir Kumar Ghose",
            "Harish Chandra Mukherjee",
            "S N Banerjee",
            "Girish Chandra Ghose"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following papers was essentially the mouthpiece of the policies of liberals?",
        "answer": "Leader",
        "choices": [
            "Leader",
            "New India",
            "Young India",
            "Free Press Journal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which journal was not associated with revolutionary activities?",
        "answer": "Young India",
        "choices": [
            "Young India",
            "Yugantar",
            "Sandhya",
            "Gadar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following newspaper used to be published from Patna?",
        "answer": "The Indian Nation",
        "choices": [
            "The Indian Nation",
            "Punjab Kesari",
            "Prabhakar",
            "Dawn"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Name the editor of nationalist newspaper - Kesari",
        "answer": "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "choices": [
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
            "G Subramania Iyer",
            "Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Name the editor of nationalist newspaper - Bengalee",
        "answer": "Surendranath Banerjee",
        "choices": [
            "Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Ganga Prasad Verma",
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Name the editor of nationalist newspaper - Hindustani",
        "answer": "Ganga Prasad Verma",
        "choices": [
            "Ganga Prasad Verma",
            "Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Name the editor of nationalist newspaper - Sudharak",
        "answer": "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
        "choices": [
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
            "Ganga Prasad Verma",
            "G Subramania Iyer",
            "Surendranath Banerjee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Name the editor of nationalist newspaper - The Mahratta",
        "answer": "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "choices": [
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
            "G Subramania Iyer",
            "Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Ganga Prasad Verma"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following was not a nationalist newspaper",
        "answer": "The Times of India",
        "choices": [
            "The Times of India",
            "Bengalee",
            "The Mahratta",
            "The Hindu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The nationalist daily newpaper - Then Indian Nation started its publication in",
        "answer": 1931,
        "choices": [
            1931,
            1930,
            1940,
            1947
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which category of population was least attracted to Religious reform movements of the nineteenth century?",
        "answer": "Poor Ordinariness Class",
        "choices": [
            "Poor Ordinariness Class",
            "Intellectuals",
            "Urban Upper Castes",
            "Liberal Princes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the father of the Indian Renaissance movement?",
        "answer": "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
        "choices": [
            "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
            "Dayanand Saraswati",
            "Shraddhanand"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following was the founder of Atmiya Sabha?",
        "answer": "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
        "choices": [
            "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
            "Swami Dayanand Saraswati",
            "Swami Vivekanand",
            "Aurobindo Ghosh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Brahmo Samaj was founded in the year of",
        "answer": 1828,
        "choices": [
            1828,
            1827,
            1829,
            1843
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The best representative of Neo-Hindustan in the second half of the 19th century was",
        "answer": "Swami Vivekananda",
        "choices": [
            "Swami Vivekananda",
            "Ramkrishna Paramhans",
            "Bankim Chandra Chatterji",
            "Raja Ram Mohan Roy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following participated in the parliament of Religions held at Chicago in 1893?",
        "answer": "Swami Vivekananda",
        "choices": [
            "Swami Vivekananda",
            "Swami Dayanand Saraswati",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Raja Ram Mohan Roy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Swami Vivekananda established Ramakrishna Mission in the year",
        "answer": 1897,
        "choices": [
            1897,
            1891,
            1861,
            1893
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was Sharadamani",
        "answer": "wife of Ramakrishna Paramhansa",
        "choices": [
            "wife of Ramakrishna Paramhansa",
            "Wife of Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
            "Mother of Vivekananda",
            "Daughter of Keshab Chandra Sen"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Dayanand Saraswati founded",
        "answer": "Arya Samaj",
        "choices": [
            "Arya Samaj",
            "Brahmo Samaj",
            "Prathana Samaj",
            "Bhaujan Samaj"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who established the Arya Samaj",
        "answer": "Swami Dayanand Saraswati",
        "choices": [
            "Swami Dayanand Saraswati",
            "Swami Vivekanand",
            "Joytirao Phule",
            "Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following gave the slogan - India for the Indians?",
        "answer": "Swami Dayanand Saraswati",
        "choices": [
            "Swami Dayanand Saraswati",
            "Swami Vivekanand",
            "H N Kunzru",
            "Ishwar Chandra Vidyasagar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Satyarth Prakash was written by",
        "answer": "Swami Dayanand Saraswati",
        "choices": [
            "Swami Dayanand Saraswati",
            "Swami Vivekanand",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Swami Vivekanand"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the founder of Prarthana Samaj",
        "answer": "Atmaram Pandurang",
        "choices": [
            "Atmaram Pandurang",
            "Jyotirao Phule",
            "Gopal Hari Deshmukh",
            "Mahatma Gandhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In 1873 who founded Satya Shodhak Samaj?",
        "answer": "Jyotirao Phule",
        "choices": [
            "Jyotirao Phule",
            "Atmaram Pandurang",
            "Gopal Hari Deshmukh",
            "Naoroji Furdunji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who established Rehnumai Mazdayasan Sabha",
        "answer": "Naoroji Furdunji",
        "choices": [
            "Naoroji Furdunji",
            "Jyotirao Phule",
            "Atmaram Pandurang",
            "Gopal Hari Deshmukh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which social reformer was called Lokhitwadi?",
        "answer": "Gopal Hari Deshmukh",
        "choices": [
            "Gopal Hari Deshmukh",
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
            "Jayaprakash Narayan",
            "Karpuri Thakur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who declared Sati illegal?",
        "answer": "William Bentinck",
        "choices": [
            "William Bentinck",
            "Warren Hastings",
            "Charles Curzon",
            "Charles Cornwallis"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When was the Prohibition of Sati Act passed in India?",
        "answer": 1829,
        "choices": [
            1829,
            1830,
            1831,
            1836
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following inscriptions mentions the instance of widow burining (Sati)?",
        "answer": "Eran Pillar Inscription of Bhanugupta",
        "choices": [
            "Eran Pillar Inscription of Bhanugupta",
            "Eran Pillar Inscription of Budhagupta",
            "Eran Stone Inscription of Samudragupta",
            "Eran Boar Inscription of Toramana"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who founded the Theosophical Society?",
        "answer": "Helena Petrovna Blavatsky",
        "choices": [
            "Helena Petrovna Blavatsky",
            "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Swami Vivekanand"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who demanded the right to enter temples that caused a terrible riot in Tirunelveli in 1899?",
        "answer": "Nadars",
        "choices": [
            "Nadars",
            "Okalinga",
            "Mahar",
            "Pali"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the founder of the Indian Association in 1876?",
        "answer": "Surendranath Banerjee",
        "choices": [
            "Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Chittaranjan Das",
            "Arvind Ghosh",
            "Dadabhai Naoroji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The most important of the pre-Congress Nationalist Organisation was the",
        "answer": "Indian Association of Calcutta",
        "choices": [
            "Indian Association of Calcutta",
            "Young Bengal Association",
            "East India Association",
            "Bengal British India Society"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which year Surendra Nath Banerjee was eliminated from Indian Civil Services?",
        "answer": 1874,
        "choices": [
            1874,
            1892,
            1885,
            1877
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which year Surendra Nath Banerjee founded the Indian Association in Kolkata",
        "answer": 1876,
        "choices": [
            1876,
            1870,
            1885,
            1884
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the first Indian to resist the political reforms?",
        "answer": "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
        "choices": [
            "Raja Ram Mohan Roy",
            "Dadabhai Naoroji",
            "Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Madras Mahajan Sabha was established in the year",
        "answer": 1884,
        "choices": [
            1884,
            1874,
            1881,
            1882
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Madras Mahajan Sabha was established by",
        "answer": "M. Veeraraghavachariar",
        "choices": [
            "M. Veeraraghavachariar",
            "Mahadev Govind Ranade",
            "Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Womesh Chunder Bonerjee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Poona Sarvajanik Sabha was founded in",
        "answer": 1870,
        "choices": [
            1870,
            1874,
            1881,
            1882
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Poona Sarvajanik Sabha was founded by",
        "answer": "Mahadev Govind Ranade",
        "choices": [
            "Mahadev Govind Ranade",
            "M. Veeraraghavachariar",
            "Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Womesh Chunder Bonerjee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Bombay Presidency Association was founded in",
        "answer": 1885,
        "choices": [
            1885,
            1870,
            1884,
            1876
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following was not a founder of Bombay Presidency Association",
        "answer": "Womesh Chunder Bonerjee",
        "choices": [
            "Womesh Chunder Bonerjee",
            "Pherozeshah Mehta",
            "Kashinath Trimbak Telang",
            "Badruddin Tayabji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Indian National Congress was founded by",
        "answer": "Allan Octavian Hume",
        "choices": [
            "Allan Octavian Hume",
            "Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Womesh Chunder Bonerjee",
            "Annie Besant"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The founder of the Indian National Congress was a",
        "answer": "Civil Servant",
        "choices": [
            "Civil Servant",
            "Scientist",
            "Social Worker",
            "Commander"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When was the Indian National Congress set up?",
        "answer": 1885,
        "choices": [
            1885,
            1884,
            1886,
            1887
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "How many representatives took part in the first session of the Indian National Congress?",
        "answer": "72 delegates",
        "choices": [
            "72 delegates",
            "62 delegates",
            "82 delegates",
            "52 delegates"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The first conference of Indian National Congress was held at",
        "answer": "Mumbai",
        "choices": [
            "Mumbai",
            "Pune",
            "Kolkata",
            "Lahore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the first muslim President of the Indian National Congress?",
        "answer": "Badruddin Tyabji",
        "choices": [
            "Badruddin Tyabji",
            "Zakir Hussain",
            "Hakim Ajmal Khan",
            "R A Kidwani"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The precursor of Indian National Congress was",
        "answer": "Indian National Union",
        "choices": [
            "Indian National Union",
            "British Indian Association",
            "Indian Association",
            "Indian League"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "How many muslim delegates participated in the Second Convention of the Indian National Congress?",
        "answer": 33,
        "choices": [
            33,
            41,
            30,
            2
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The second session of the Indian National Congress was presided over by",
        "answer": "Dadabhai Naoroji",
        "choices": [
            "Dadabhai Naoroji",
            "Ganesh Agarkar",
            "Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Pherozeshah Mehta"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the second muslim President of the Indian National Congress?",
        "answer": "Rahimtulla Mahomed Sayani",
        "choices": [
            "Rahimtulla Mahomed Sayani",
            "Zakir Hussain",
            "Badruddin Tyabji",
            "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the first woman President of the Indian National Congress?",
        "answer": "Annie Besant",
        "choices": [
            "Annie Besant",
            "Sarojini Naidu",
            "Kadambini Ganguly",
            "Kasturba Gandhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the first Indian woman President of the Indian National Congress?",
        "answer": "Sarojini Naidu",
        "choices": [
            "Sarojini Naidu",
            "Annie Besant",
            "Kadambini Ganguly",
            "Sucheta Kriplani"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "At which place was the 27th session of the Indian National Congress held?",
        "answer": "Bankipur",
        "choices": [
            "Bankipur",
            "Ramgarh",
            "Gaya",
            "Bhagalpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "At which of the following sessions of the Indian National Congress did the Champaran trouble come up for discussion?",
        "answer": "Lucknow, 1916",
        "choices": [
            "Lucknow, 1916",
            "Calcutta, 1911",
            "Bankipur, 1912",
            "Ramgarh, 1940"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who said - Sawaraj is my birthright and I shall have it?",
        "answer": "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "choices": [
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
            "Bipan Chandra Pal",
            "Aurobindo Ghosh",
            "Subhash Chandra Bose"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who said - The basic cause of problems facing Bharat is the neglect of its national identity?",
        "answer": "Deen Dayal Upadhyay",
        "choices": [
            "Deen Dayal Upadhyay",
            "Keshav Baliram Hedgewar",
            "Madhav Sadashiv Golwalkar",
            "Karpoori Thakur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Lucknow Pact took place in which year",
        "answer": 1916,
        "choices": [
            1916,
            1915,
            1917,
            1912
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Remember once again, now that this flag is unfurled, it must not be lowered as long as a single Indian, man, woman or child lives in India, who said this?",
        "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru in Lahore",
        "choices": [
            "Jawaharlal Nehru in Lahore",
            "Gandhi in Gujarat",
            "Surendranath Banerjee in Bengal",
            "Subhash Chandra Bose in Singapore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who said that Congress Movement was neither inspired by the people, nor devised or planned by them?",
        "answer": "Lala Lajpat Rai",
        "choices": [
            "Lala Lajpat Rai",
            "Syed Ahmed",
            "Frederick Hamilton - Dufferin",
            "George Curzon"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the President of the Patna Session of Indian National Congress held in 1912?",
        "answer": "Raghunath Narsinha Mudholkar",
        "choices": [
            "Raghunath Narsinha Mudholkar",
            "Madan Mohan Malviya",
            "Chittaranjan Das",
            "Ambica Charan Mazumdar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the President of the Gaya Session of Indian National Congress held in 1922?",
        "answer": "Chittaranjan Das",
        "choices": [
            "Chittaranjan Das",
            "Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Raghunath Narsinha Mudholkar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which tribe of Bihar attended Gaya Session of Congress?",
        "answer": "Oraon",
        "choices": [
            "Oraon",
            "Santhal",
            "Sannyasi",
            "Munda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Shubhas Chandra Bose became the President of the Indian National Congress in Tripuri Session by defeating",
        "answer": "Pattabhi Sitaramayya",
        "choices": [
            "Pattabhi Sitaramayya",
            "Rash Behari Bose",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Rajendra Prasad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which Raja rendered a very valuable assistance to the Indian Natioanal Congress for holding is Fourth Session at Allahabad in 1888?",
        "answer": "Raja of Darbhanga",
        "choices": [
            "Raja of Darbhanga",
            "Raja of Benaras",
            "Raja of Jagdishpur",
            "Raja of Bhinga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Sardar Udham Singh killed whom?",
        "answer": "Micheal O'Dwyar",
        "choices": [
            "Micheal O'Dwyar",
            "Reginald Dyer",
            "Curzon Wyllie",
            "Saunders"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The protest method of moderate leaders of the Congress was?",
        "answer": "Constitutional Agitation",
        "choices": [
            "Constitutional Agitation",
            "Non-Cooperation",
            "Passive Resistance",
            "Civil Disobedience"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Most of the moderate leader hailed from",
        "answer": "Urban Areas",
        "choices": [
            "Urban Areas",
            "Rural Areas",
            "Both Rural & Urban Areas",
            "Punjab"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which one of the following was not an extremist?",
        "answer": "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
        "choices": [
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
            "Udham Singh",
            "Madan Lal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who established the Servants of India Society?",
        "answer": "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
        "choices": [
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
            "Lala Lajpat Rai",
            "Bipin Chandra Pal",
            "Bhagat Singh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Indian National Movement came to be dominated by the extremists after",
        "answer": 1906,
        "choices": [
            1906,
            1909,
            1914,
            1919
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which one of the following leaders belonged to the Extremist wing of the Congress?",
        "answer": "Aurobindo Ghosh",
        "choices": [
            "Aurobindo Ghosh",
            "Dadabhai Naoroji",
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
            "Surendranath Banerjee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following was not known as a moderate in the National Movement?",
        "answer": "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
        "choices": [
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
            "Dadabhai Naoroji",
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
            "Mahadev Govind Ranade"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who is popularly known as Sher-e-Punjab?",
        "answer": "Lala Lajpat Rai",
        "choices": [
            "Lala Lajpat Rai",
            "Bhagat Singh",
            "Rajguru",
            "Udham Singh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In 1908, Bal Gangadhar Tilak was imprisoned for",
        "answer": "6 years",
        "choices": [
            "6 years",
            "5 years",
            "7 years",
            "8 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who said about Bengal partition, The partition announcement fell like a bomb shell?",
        "answer": "Surendranath Banerjee",
        "choices": [
            "Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
            "Bipin Chandra Pal",
            "Chittaranjan Das"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Bal Gangadhar Tilak came to be known as Lokmanya Tilak when",
        "answer": "The Government accused him in the Rand Murder case",
        "choices": [
            "The Government accused him in the Rand Murder case",
            "He started the Shivaji and Ganpati festivals",
            "He started a popular newspaper",
            "He became a popular teacher"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who founded Abhinav Bharat Society in 1906 in London?",
        "answer": "Vinayak Damodar Savarkar",
        "choices": [
            "Vinayak Damodar Savarkar",
            "Shyamji Krishna Verma",
            "Sohan Singh",
            "Pandurang Mahadev Bapat"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who established a branch of Anushilan Samiti at Patna in 1913?",
        "answer": "Sachindra Nath Sanyal",
        "choices": [
            "Sachindra Nath Sanyal",
            "Rewati Nag",
            "Yadunath Sarkar",
            "Mazharul Haque"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Anushilan Samiti was",
        "answer": "a revolutionary organisation",
        "choices": [
            "a revolutionary organisation",
            "dedicated to the upliftment of women",
            "promoting widow remarriage",
            "interested in labour welfare"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the founder of Swadesh Bandhav Samiti?",
        "answer": "Ashwini Kumar Dutta",
        "choices": [
            "Ashwini Kumar Dutta",
            "Prafulla Chaki",
            "Vinayak Damodar Savarkar",
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When did the attempt of murder of Kingsford was made at Muzaffarpur, Bihar?",
        "answer": 1908,
        "choices": [
            1908,
            1909,
            1907,
            1911
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following was hanged on the charge of Muzaffarpur Bomb Case?",
        "answer": "Khudiram Bose",
        "choices": [
            "Khudiram Bose",
            "Prafulla Chaki",
            "Batukeshwar Dutt",
            "Rajendra Lahiri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which place Khudiram Bose tried to kill Kingsford?",
        "answer": "Muzaffarpur",
        "choices": [
            "Muzaffarpur",
            "Gaya",
            "Darbhanga",
            "Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was given life punishment for the murder of Colonel Wyllie?",
        "answer": "Madan Lal Dhingra",
        "choices": [
            "Madan Lal Dhingra",
            "Udham Singh",
            "Bhagat Singh",
            "Manmathanath"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Non-Cooperation Movement was suspended in",
        "answer": 1922,
        "choices": [
            1922,
            1921,
            1923,
            1924
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which year Hindustan Republican Association was set up",
        "answer": 1924,
        "choices": [
            1924,
            1920,
            1928,
            1930
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who penned the following lines? Sarfaroshi ki tamanna ab hamare dil me hai dekhna hai zor kitna baju-e-qatil me hai.",
        "answer": "Bismil Azimabadi",
        "choices": [
            "Bismil Azimabadi",
            "Rajguru",
            "Bhagat Singh",
            "Azad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which revolutionaries were hanged in the Kakori Train Robbery Case?",
        "answer": "Ram Prasad Bismil and Ashfaqulla",
        "choices": [
            "Ram Prasad Bismil and Ashfaqulla",
            "Vinayak Damodar Savarkar and Vasudev Chapekar",
            "Prafulla Chandra Chaki and Khudiram Bose",
            "Surya Sen and Udham Singh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following was not associated with the Kakori train robbery case?",
        "answer": "Sukhdev",
        "choices": [
            "Sukhdev",
            "Ram Prasad Bismil",
            "Ashfaqulla Khan",
            "Roshan Singh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "How old was Bhagat Singh when he threw a bomb in the assembly in protest against the government?",
        "answer": "a little more than 21 years",
        "choices": [
            "a little more than 21 years",
            "21 years",
            "25 years",
            "a little more than 25 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "One of the founder leaders of Hindustan Socialist Republican Army was",
        "answer": "Bhagat Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Bhagat Singh",
            "Bhimrao Ambedkar",
            "Subhash Chandra Bose",
            "Jai Prakash Narayan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who gave the Inquilab Zindabad slogan?",
        "answer": "Bhagat Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Bhagat Singh",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Iqbal",
            "Subhash Chandra Bose"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Bhagat Singh, Rajguru and Sukhdev were executed on",
        "answer": "23rd March 1931",
        "choices": [
            "23rd March 1931",
            "23rd March 1932",
            "23rd March 1933",
            "23rd March 1934"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Chittagong Armoury raid had been planned by",
        "answer": "Surya Sen",
        "choices": [
            "Surya Sen",
            "Chandan Dutta",
            "Jatin Das",
            "Vidhan Ghosh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who propounded the doctrine of Passive Resistance",
        "answer": "Aurobindo Ghosh",
        "choices": [
            "Aurobindo Ghosh",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Bipin Chandra Pal",
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "What was the slogan of the Bolsheviks during the 1917 Revolution?",
        "answer": "Peace, Land, Bread",
        "choices": [
            "Peace, Land, Bread",
            "Workers of the world, Unite",
            "Liberty, Equality, Fraternity",
            "Freedom and Justice"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the founder of the India House in London?",
        "answer": "Shyamji Krishnavarma",
        "choices": [
            "Shyamji Krishnavarma",
            "Rash Behari Bose",
            "Ramchandra",
            "Taraknath Das"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Ghadar Party was established in the year?",
        "answer": 1913,
        "choices": [
            1913,
            1907,
            1917,
            1920
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Where was the Ghadar Party established?",
        "answer": "United States of America",
        "choices": [
            "United States of America",
            "Germany",
            "France",
            "England"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "What was the cause of outbreak of Ghadar Revolution",
        "answer": "Beginning of first World War",
        "choices": [
            "Beginning of first World War",
            "Arresting of Lala Hardayal",
            "Kamagatamaru incident",
            "Hanging of Kartar Singh Sarabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Interim government under the leadership of Raja Mahendra Pratap Singh was founded in Kabul with the support of Germany during",
        "answer": "First World War",
        "choices": [
            "First World War",
            "Second World War",
            "Ghadar Movement",
            "Swadeshi Movement"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who is regarded as the Mother of Indian Revolution?",
        "answer": "Bhikaiji Rustom Cama",
        "choices": [
            "Bhikaiji Rustom Cama",
            "Annie Besant",
            "Sarojini Naidu",
            "Rama Bai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Where did Madam Cama unfurl India's tricolour flag of freedom?",
        "answer": "Stuttgart, Germany",
        "choices": [
            "Stuttgart, Germany",
            "Paris, France",
            "London, England",
            "Geneva, Switzerland"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who called for a Total Revolution at Gandhi Maidan, Patna?",
        "answer": "Jayaprakash Narayan",
        "choices": [
            "Jayaprakash Narayan",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Raj Kumar Shukla",
            "Karpoori Thakur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Swadeshi and Boycott were adopted as the methods of struggle for the first time during the",
        "answer": "Partition of Bengal",
        "choices": [
            "Partition of Bengal",
            "Home Rule Movement",
            "Visit of Simon Commission ",
            "Arrival of Mahatma Gandhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which place was the organisation named Golden League formed to work for boycott and the Swadeshi Movement?",
        "answer": "Deoghar",
        "choices": [
            "Deoghar",
            "Muzaffarpur",
            "Patna",
            "Ranchi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The declaration of Partition of Bengal was done on",
        "answer": "19th July 1905",
        "choices": [
            "19th July 1905",
            "16th October 1905",
            "15th August 1905",
            "7th August 1905"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which movement started after the Partition of Bengal?",
        "answer": "Swadeshi Movement",
        "choices": [
            "Swadeshi Movement",
            "Civil Disobedience",
            "Quit India Movement",
            "Non-Cooperation Movement"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Name the viceroy of Indian concerned with Bengal partition",
        "answer": "Charles Curzon",
        "choices": [
            "Charles Curzon",
            "John Elliot - Minto",
            "Robert Lytton",
            "Charles Hardinge"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Bengal was partitioned in 1905, but due to opposition it was annulled in",
        "answer": 1911,
        "choices": [
            1911,
            1906,
            1916,
            1909
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following classes was mainly unaffected of Swadeshi Movement of 1905?",
        "answer": "Farmers & Muslims",
        "choices": [
            "Farmers & Muslims",
            "Women",
            "Intellectuals",
            "Women & Farmers"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following leaders presided over Congress Session at Calcutta in 1906?",
        "answer": "Dadabhai Naoroji",
        "choices": [
            "Dadabhai Naoroji",
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
            "Aurobindo Ghosh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "At the Calcutta Session of the Indian National Congress held in 1906, the Flag of Swaraj for India was unfurled by",
        "answer": "Dadabhai Naoroji",
        "choices": [
            "Dadabhai Naoroji",
            "Allan Octavian Hume",
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "First Indian elected to the British House of Commons was Dadabhai Naoroji who contested on the ticket of ",
        "answer": "Liberal Party",
        "choices": [
            "Liberal Party",
            "Labour Party",
            "Conservative Party",
            "Communist Party"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was not among the founders of All India Muslim League?",
        "answer": "Muhammad Ali Jinnah",
        "choices": [
            "Muhammad Ali Jinnah",
            "Nawab Salimullah",
            "Nawab Moshin-ul-Mulk",
            "Agha Khan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Muslim deputation met Minto in 1906 at Shimla and pleaded for",
        "answer": "Separate electorate for Muslims",
        "choices": [
            "Separate electorate for Muslims",
            "a composite electorate",
            "higher representation to the Hindus",
            "Special representation to Muslim by nomination"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who propounded the two-nation theory prior to the Pakistan Resolution of the Muslim League?",
        "answer": "Syed Ahmad Khan",
        "choices": [
            "Syed Ahmad Khan",
            "Muhammad Iqbal",
            "Liaquat Ali Khan",
            "Muhammad Ali Jinnah"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Whom did Rajendra Prasad considered as the father of Pakistan?",
        "answer": "Gilbert Elliot - Minto",
        "choices": [
            "Gilbert Elliot - Minto",
            "Muhammad Ali Jinnah",
            "Louis Mountbatten",
            "Liaquat Ali Khan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Bihar became a separate state during the British rule in the year?",
        "answer": 1912,
        "choices": [
            1912,
            1905,
            1936,
            1946
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who earned the title of Recruiting Sergeant of the British for this support to the government during First World War?",
        "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "choices": [
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Motilal Nehru",
            "Madan Mohan Malviya",
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following did not contribute to Home Rule League?",
        "answer": "T S Alcott",
        "choices": [
            "T S Alcott",
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
            "Annie Besant",
            "S Subramaniam Iyer"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which conference could the Home-Rule supporters demonstrate their political power successfully?",
        "answer": "Lucknow Conference of Congress in 1916",
        "choices": [
            "Lucknow Conference of Congress in 1916",
            "All India Trade Union Conference held at Bombay in 1920",
            "First Uttar Pradesh Association held in 1918",
            "Joint AITUC and NTU sabha at Nagpur in 1938"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Home Rule Movement was symbol of starting a new phase of freedom movement in India because",
        "answer": "it put a perfect project for the self-Government before the nation",
        "choices": [
            "it put a perfect project for the self-Government before the nation",
            "Leadership of the movement came in the hands of Gandhiji",
            "Hindus and Muslims started to struggle jointly",
            "It established co-ordination between extremists and moderates"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which of the following colleges, Gandhiji studied?",
        "answer": "Samaldas College, Bhavnagar",
        "choices": [
            "Samaldas College, Bhavnagar",
            "Dharmendrasinji College, Rajkot",
            "Gujarat College, Ahmedabad",
            "Bahauddin College, Junagadh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "To sort out whose legal problem was Mahatma Gandhi invited in South Africa in 1893?",
        "answer": "Dada Abdullah of Gujarat",
        "choices": [
            "Dada Abdullah of Gujarat",
            "Sheikh Abdullah of Kashmir",
            "Titu Mir of Bengal",
            "Imdad Imam of Bihar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following was Gandhiji's first Satyagraha Movement in India in which he used Civil Disobedience?",
        "answer": "Champaran",
        "choices": [
            "Champaran",
            "Kheda",
            "Ahmedabad",
            "Rowlatt"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In response to the mass agitation of the Champaran Movement, the British Government took which step to address the issue?",
        "answer": "Instituted the Champaran Agrarian Committee",
        "choices": [
            "Instituted the Champaran Agrarian Committee",
            "Appointed Mahatma Gandhi as the Governor of Champaran",
            "Enforced strict curfew and imposed Martial Law in the region",
            "Declared Champaran as an independent State"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The cook from Bihar who saved Mahatma Gandhi's life from a murder attempt by food poisoning in 1917 was",
        "answer": "Batak Mian",
        "choices": [
            "Batak Mian",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Raj Kumar Shukla",
            "Erwin"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which of the following movements did Mahatma Gandhi make the first use of the hunger strike as a weapon?",
        "answer": "Ahmedabad Strike",
        "choices": [
            "Ahmedabad Strike",
            "Non-Cooperation Movement",
            "Bardoli Satyagraha",
            "Rowlatt Satyagraha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which of the following Satyagraha movements, did Gandhiji not participate directly?",
        "answer": "Vaikom Satyagraha",
        "choices": [
            "Vaikom Satyagraha",
            "Rajkot Satyagraha",
            "Khera Satyagraha",
            "Non-Cooperation Movement"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following capitalists served as an AICC treasurer for many years and went to Jail in 1930?",
        "answer": "Jamnalal Bajaj",
        "choices": [
            "Jamnalal Bajaj",
            "G D Birla",
            "J R D Tata",
            "Balchand Hirachand"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Gandhi's close English compatriot during the Freedom movement was",
        "answer": "Charles Freer Andrews",
        "choices": [
            "Charles Freer Andrews",
            "Thomas Moore",
            "Allan Octavian Hume",
            "William Wavell"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the political guru of Mahatma Gandhi?",
        "answer": "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
        "choices": [
            "Gopal Krishna Gokhale",
            "Dadabhai Naoroji",
            "Mahadev Govind Ranade",
            "Surendranath Banerjee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who participated in Satyagraha started by Gandhiji at Ahmedabad in 1917-18?",
        "answer": "Industrial Workers",
        "choices": [
            "Industrial Workers",
            "Cultivators Class",
            "Public",
            "Middle Class"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who drew Gandhiji's attention to the plight of Indigo peasants in Champaran?",
        "answer": "Raj Kumar Shukla",
        "choices": [
            "Raj Kumar Shukla",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Anugrah Narayan Sinha",
            "Acharya Kriplani"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "How much part of the land was kept in trust for the cultivation of indigo in Bihar under Tinkathiya system?",
        "answer": "3 of 20 Kattha",
        "choices": [
            "3 of 20 Kattha",
            "1 of 10 Kattha",
            "1 of 3 Kattha",
            "3 of 25 Kattha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "At which place of Bihar, Gandhiji started Satyagraha movement for the first time in India?",
        "answer": "Champaran",
        "choices": [
            "Champaran",
            "Madhubani",
            "Gaya",
            "Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The person not connected with Champarana Movement was",
        "answer": "Jai Prakash Narayan",
        "choices": [
            "Jai Prakash Narayan",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Anugrah Narayan Sinha",
            "Jivatram Bhagwandas Kriplani"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which Farmer's Movement did Mahatma Gandhi participate first of all?",
        "answer": "Champaran",
        "choices": [
            "Champaran",
            "Kheda",
            "Bardoli",
            "Baroda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the National Leader of Champaran Indigo movement?",
        "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "choices": [
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Birsa Munda",
            "Baba Ramchandra",
            "Ram Singh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Nai-Dhobi Band was a form of Social boycott in 1919 which",
        "answer": "was started by the farmers of Pratapgarh district",
        "choices": [
            "was started by the farmers of Pratapgarh district",
            "was a movement started by saints for the emancipation of the people lower classes",
            "was a step against contractors of lower castes by landlords",
            "was a movement against contractors by lower castes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Sarabandi Campaign of 1922 was led by",
        "answer": "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
        "choices": [
            "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
            "Chittaranjan Das",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Lala Lajpat Rai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Swami Sahajananda was related to which of the following?",
        "answer": "Peasant Movement in Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Peasant Movement in Bihar",
            "Tribal Movement in Bihar",
            "Labour Movement in Bihar",
            "Caste Movement in Bihar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "What was the aim of Eka Movement in Oudh?",
        "answer": "To protect rights of peasants agianst landlord oppression",
        "choices": [
            "To protect rights of peasants agianst landlord oppression",
            "To stop to give rent to the Government",
            "To protect the rights of landlords ",
            "End of Satyagraha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Eka Movement was launched in the rural areas of which region?",
        "answer": "Awadh",
        "choices": [
            "Awadh",
            "Bihar",
            "Punjab",
            "Bengal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Swami Sahajanand Saraswati published a journal named",
        "answer": "Hunkar",
        "choices": [
            "Hunkar",
            "Jankranti",
            "Krishak Samachar",
            "Vidrohi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Akhil Bhartiya Kisan Congress also known as All India Kisan Sabha was founded in ",
        "answer": 1936,
        "choices": [
            1936,
            1939,
            1942,
            1945
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was elected the first president of All India Kisan Sabha at Lucknow in 1936?",
        "answer": "Swami Sahajanand Saraswati",
        "choices": [
            "Swami Sahajanand Saraswati",
            "N G Ranga",
            "E M S Namboodripad",
            "Acharya Narendra Dev"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Where was the first All India Kisan Maha Sabha formed?",
        "answer": "Lucknow",
        "choices": [
            "Lucknow",
            "Allahabad",
            "Kolkata",
            "Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Tebhaga Movement was started in 1946 from Bengal under leadership of",
        "answer": "Kisan Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "Kisan Sabha",
            "Muslim League",
            "Indian National Congress",
            "Trade Union"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Congress took a critical stand over the Montford Reforms in 1918, which led to break up with the old moderate remnants (Sapru, Jayakar, Chintamani) who formed the ",
        "answer": "Indian National Liberal Federation",
        "choices": [
            "Indian National Liberal Federation",
            "Servants of India Society",
            "Swaraj Party",
            "Janta Dal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the first President of All India Trade Union Congress?",
        "answer": "Lala Lajpat Rai",
        "choices": [
            "Lala Lajpat Rai",
            "B T Ranade",
            "Satya Bhakta",
            "N M Joshi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When was All India Trade Union Congress established in Bombay?",
        "answer": 1920,
        "choices": [
            1920,
            1925,
            1929,
            1935
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the first Indian to be the member of Communist International?",
        "answer": "Manabendra Nath Roy",
        "choices": [
            "Manabendra Nath Roy",
            "Muzaffar Ahmad",
            "S A Dange",
            "Lala Lajpat Rai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The revolutionary phase of the trade union movement in India was",
        "answer": "1926-39",
        "choices": [
            "1926-39",
            "1939-45",
            "1918-26",
            "1914-18"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When was the Rowlatt Act passed?",
        "answer": 1919,
        "choices": [
            1919,
            1909,
            1930,
            1942
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following Acts enabled the British Government to suspend the right of Habeas Corpus?",
        "answer": "The Rowlatt Act, 1919",
        "choices": [
            "The Rowlatt Act, 1919",
            "The Indian Councils Act, 1909",
            "The Indian Councils Act, 1919",
            "The Government of India Act, 1935"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Jallianwala Bagh Massacre happened in the context of which Gandhian Satyagraha?",
        "answer": "Rowlatt Satyagraha",
        "choices": [
            "Rowlatt Satyagraha",
            "Swadeshi Satyagraha",
            "Bardoli Satyagraha",
            "Individual Satyagraha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Indian National Congress opposed the Rowlatt Act because it aimed",
        "answer": "to limit the individual liberty",
        "choices": [
            "to limit the individual liberty",
            "to ban Indian National Congress",
            "to enlarge the communal delegations",
            "to imprision national leaders charging the traitors to the nation"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The massacre of the crowd at Jallianwala Bagh at Amritsar took place on",
        "answer": "April 13, 1919",
        "choices": [
            "April 13, 1919",
            "May 5, 1918",
            "April 1, 1919",
            "July 29, 1919"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Why did people gather to demonstrate at Jallianwala Bagh?",
        "answer": "to protest against the arrest of Kitchlu and Satyapal",
        "choices": [
            "to protest against the arrest of Kitchlu and Satyapal",
            "To protest against the arrest of Gandhi and Lala Lajpat Rai",
            "to protest against the abritarily of inhuman acts of the Punjab Government",
            "to protest against General Dyer"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Rabindranath Tagore gave up his Knighthood because of ",
        "answer": "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
        "choices": [
            "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
            "Brutual supression of Civil Disobedience Movement",
            "Execution of Bhagat Singh",
            "Chauri Chaura Incident"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who from the following killed Micheal O Dwyer responsible for Jallianwala Bagh Massacre?",
        "answer": "Udham Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Udham Singh",
            "Prithvi Singh Azad",
            "Sardar Kishan Singh",
            "Sohan Singh Josh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Micheal O Dwyer was shot dead on 13th March 1940 in London by",
        "answer": "Udham Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Udham Singh",
            "Madan Lal Dhingra",
            "Veer Damodar Savarkar",
            "M P T Acharya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the Prime Minister of England when Montague-Chlemsford Act was passed in 1919?",
        "answer": "David Llyod George",
        "choices": [
            "David Llyod George",
            "George Hamilton",
            "Samuel Hoare",
            "Salisbury"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Muddiman Committee was appointed to report on the working of the ",
        "answer": "Dyarchy",
        "choices": [
            "Dyarchy",
            "Communal Representation",
            "Fedralism",
            "Rowlatt Act"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which event served as a catalyst for the Khilafat Movement?",
        "answer": "The Treaty of Vesailles",
        "choices": [
            "The Treaty of Vesailles",
            "The Partition of Bengal",
            "The Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
            "Arrival of Mahatma Gandhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Why did Mahatma Gandhi support the Khilfat Movement?",
        "answer": "Gandhiji wanted to win the support of the Indian Muslims against the British",
        "choices": [
            "Gandhiji wanted to win the support of the Indian Muslims against the British",
            "The Khalifa had given shelter to Indian revolutionaries",
            "The Khalifa supported Indian struggle for freedom",
            "The Khalifa was a friend of Gandhiji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who viewed the Khilafat Movement as an opportunity for integrating Hindus and Muslims which will not appear again within coming hundred years?",
        "answer": "Ali Brothers",
        "choices": [
            "Ali Brothers",
            "Abul Kalam Azad",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Khan Abdul Gaffar Khan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which city was the conference of Khilafat Committee in 1920 held that requested Gandhiji to assume the leadership of Non-Cooperation Movement?",
        "answer": "Allahabad",
        "choices": [
            "Allahabad",
            "Lahore",
            "Lucknow",
            "Karachi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Moplah Rebellion in 1921 was an offshoot of",
        "answer": "Khilafat Movement",
        "choices": [
            "Khilafat Movement",
            "Mutiny of 1857",
            "Swadeshi Movement",
            "Non-Cooperation Movement"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Non-Cooperation Movement was started in",
        "answer": 1920,
        "choices": [
            1920,
            1919,
            1918,
            1921
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "A pleader of bihar who left his lucrative practice during non-cooperation movement was",
        "answer": "Rajendra Prasad",
        "choices": [
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Jai Prakash Narayan",
            "Sahjananad Saraswati",
            "Raj Kumar Shukla"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which area was Rahul Sanrityayan active in the Non-Cooperation Movement of 1920?",
        "answer": "Chhapra",
        "choices": [
            "Chhapra",
            "Delhi",
            "Lucknow",
            "Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who led cultivators in Bihar during the Non-Cooperation Movement?",
        "answer": "Swami Vidyanand",
        "choices": [
            "Swami Vidyanand",
            "Raj Kumar Shukla",
            "Shri Krishna Singh",
            "J B Sen"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "After which incident, Mahatma Gandhi halted the Non-Cooperation Movement and called it as his Himalayan Blunder?",
        "answer": "Chauri-Chaura",
        "choices": [
            "Chauri-Chaura",
            "Kakori Case",
            "Jallianwala Bagh Massacre",
            "Muzaffarpur Case"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who organized the  Swadesh Bandhav Samiti during the Indian Freedom Struggle?",
        "answer": "Ashwini Kumar Dutta",
        "choices": [
            "Ashwini Kumar Dutta",
            "Batukeshwar Dutta",
            "Surya Sen",
            "Surendranath Banerjee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which state is Chauri-Chaura where in February 1922 a police station was set on fire?",
        "answer": "Uttar Pradesh",
        "choices": [
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Madhya Pradesh",
            "Rajasthan",
            "Madhya Pradesh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "A Sanyasi who came to that district after a spell as an indentured labourer in Fiji, carrying a copy of Tulsidas Ramayana on his back from which he would recite verses to rural audience. The peasant leader refferred to here is",
        "answer": "Baba Ram Chandra",
        "choices": [
            "Baba Ram Chandra",
            "Jhinguri Singh",
            "Yadunandan Sharma",
            "Sahajananda Saraswati"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Swaraj Party was formed after the failure of the ",
        "answer": "Non-Cooperation Movement",
        "choices": [
            "Non-Cooperation Movement",
            "Quit India Movement",
            "Civil Disobedience Movement",
            "Swadeshi Movement"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who established the Swaraj Party in 1923",
        "answer": "Chittaranjan Das & Motilal Nehru",
        "choices": [
            "Chittaranjan Das & Motilal Nehru",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Vallabhbhai Patel",
            "Bhim Rao Ambedkar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who successfully led the Bardoli Satyagraha?",
        "answer": "Vallabhbhai Patel",
        "choices": [
            "Vallabhbhai Patel",
            "Motilal Nehru",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Jivatram Bhagwandas Kriplani"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following movements was led and successful under the leadership of Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel?",
        "answer": "Satyagraha of Bardoli, Gujarat",
        "choices": [
            "Satyagraha of Bardoli, Gujarat",
            "Satyagraha in support of Khadi peasants, Gujarat",
            "Satyagraha of workers of cotton mills, Ahmedabad",
            "Champaran Satyagraha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who established the Swaraj Dal in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Shri Krishna Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Shri Krishna Singh",
            "Ramlal Shah",
            "Bankim Chandra Chatterji",
            "Sachindra Nath Sanyal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The famous slogan Swaraj should be for common people not only for classes was given by",
        "answer": "Chittaranjan Das",
        "choices": [
            "Chittaranjan Das",
            "Motilal Nehru",
            "Gopi Nath Saha",
            "Chakravarti Rajgopalachari"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Mahatma Gandhi presided over which session of the Inidan National Congress?",
        "answer": 1924,
        "choices": [
            1924,
            1922,
            1930,
            1928
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When did Simon Commission visit India?",
        "answer": 1928,
        "choices": [
            1928,
            1929,
            1927,
            1931
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Nehru Report was drafted by a Committeee headed by",
        "answer": "Motilal Nehru",
        "choices": [
            "Motilal Nehru",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Vallabhbhai Patel",
            "Chittaranjan Das"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The proposal of Purna-Swaraj was passed in Lahore Congress in the year",
        "answer": 1929,
        "choices": [
            1929,
            1919,
            1942,
            1939
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who raised the flag of Independence at the Congress Session of 1929?",
        "answer": "Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "choices": [
            "Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Maulana Muhammad Ali",
            "Vallabhbhai Patel",
            "Subhas Chandra Bose"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which day was declared as Purna Swaraj Day by the Indian National Congress?",
        "answer": "26th January 1930",
        "choices": [
            "26th January 1930",
            "30th January 1948",
            "15th August 1947",
            "31st December 1950"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which Sesssion Indian National Congress passed Completed Independence (Purna Swaraj) resolution?",
        "answer": "1929 Lahore",
        "choices": [
            "1929 Lahore",
            "1929 Nagpur",
            "1924 Belgaum",
            "1931 Karachi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Dandi March was undertaken in",
        "answer": 1930,
        "choices": [
            1930,
            1931,
            1932,
            1929
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following participated in the Salt Satyagraha of Gandhi?",
        "answer": "All of these",
        "choices": [
            "All of these",
            "Sarojini Naidu",
            "Rajkumari Amrit Kaur",
            "Kamla Devi Chattopadhyaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The famous Dandi March led by Mahatma Gandhi during the Civil Disobedience Movement covered a distance of approximately",
        "answer": "241 miles (387 km)",
        "choices": [
            "241 miles (387 km)",
            "200 km",
            "400 km",
            "300 km"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In 1930, Mahatma Gandhi started Civil Disobedience Movement from",
        "answer": "Dandi",
        "choices": [
            "Dandi",
            "Sevagram",
            "Wardha",
            "Sabarmati"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "For how many days did Dandi March last?",
        "answer": "24 days",
        "choices": [
            "24 days",
            "10 days",
            "20 days",
            "30 days"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Agitation against Chaukidari Tax in Begusarai was a part of",
        "answer": "Civil Disobedience Movement",
        "choices": [
            "Civil Disobedience Movement",
            "Non-Cooperation Movement",
            "Quit India Movement",
            "Khilafat Movement"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who led the Salt Satyagraha in Bhagalpur",
        "answer": "Mahadev Lal Sarraf",
        "choices": [
            "Mahadev Lal Sarraf",
            "Shri Krishna Singh",
            "Kumar Mishra",
            "Satyanarayan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the founder of All India Harijan Sangh in 1932?",
        "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "choices": [
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Dr Bhim Rao Ambedkar",
            "Jagjivan Ram",
            "Subhas Chandra Bose"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Prabhavati Devi was the freedom fighter from",
        "answer": "Patna",
        "choices": [
            "Patna",
            "Champaran",
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Shahabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Gandhi-Irwin pact was signed in",
        "answer": 1931,
        "choices": [
            1931,
            1935,
            1942,
            1919
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Second Round Table Conference in London was held in the backdrop of the",
        "answer": "Gandhi-Irwin Pact",
        "choices": [
            "Gandhi-Irwin Pact",
            "Emerson-Gandhi Pact",
            "Hailey-Gandhi Pact",
            "Gandhi-Simon Pact"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who played ann important role in the signing of Gandhi-Irwin Pact?",
        "answer": "Tej Bahadur Sapru",
        "choices": [
            "Tej Bahadur Sapru",
            "Motilal Nehru",
            "Madan Mohan Malviya",
            "Chintamani"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following Indian leaders attended the First Round Table Conference in London?",
        "answer": "Maulana Mohammad Ali",
        "choices": [
            "Maulana Mohammad Ali",
            "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Indian National Congress did not take part in which of the following Round Table Conferences?",
        "answer": "First & Third",
        "choices": [
            "First & Third",
            "First",
            "Second",
            "Third"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Mahatma Gandhi returned to India in December, 1931 empty-handed from",
        "answer": "London",
        "choices": [
            "London",
            "Moscow",
            "Washington",
            "Tokyo"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "On which issue did the Second Round Table Conference fail?",
        "answer": "Communal Delegations",
        "choices": [
            "Communal Delegations",
            "Granting Dominion Status",
            "The date of transfer of ruling power",
            "Postponement of Civil Disobedience Movement"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which Round Table Conference held in 1932?",
        "answer": "Third",
        "choices": [
            "Third",
            "Second",
            "First",
            "Fourth"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who wrote the pamphlet Now or Never?",
        "answer": "Choudhary Rahmat Ali",
        "choices": [
            "Choudhary Rahmat Ali",
            "Muhammad Ali Jinnah",
            "Muhammad Iqbal",
            "Khafi Khan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "A separate electoral group was made by the communal Tribunal of Ramsay MacDonald first time in August, 1932",
        "answer": "for Untouchables",
        "choices": [
            "for Untouchables",
            "for Muslims",
            "for Indian Christians",
            "for Anglo-Indians"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "How many seats were given to depressed classes under Communal Award and Poona Pact?",
        "answer": "71 and 147 repectively",
        "choices": [
            "71 and 147 repectively",
            "74 and 79 respectively",
            "78 and 80 respectively",
            "78 and 69 respectively"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The purpose of Poona Pact was",
        "answer": "to provide representation of untouchables",
        "choices": [
            "to provide representation of untouchables",
            "Hindu-Muslim unity",
            "to priviledge the Kings",
            "Reconsideration of Dyarchy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The first meeting of the Congress Socialist Party was held in",
        "answer": "Patna",
        "choices": [
            "Patna",
            "Nasik",
            "Delhi",
            "Lahore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The first session of the Congress Socialist Party was held in the year",
        "answer": 1934,
        "choices": [
            1934,
            1921,
            1937,
            1939
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Congress Socialist Party was founded in 1934 by",
        "answer": "Jayaprakash Narayan & Acharya Narendra Dev",
        "choices": [
            "Jayaprakash Narayan & Acharya Narendra Dev",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru & Vinoba Bhave",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru & Jay Prakash Narayan",
            "Ashok Mehta & Dr Rajendra Prasad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Jayprakash Narayan was associated with the which party",
        "answer": "Congress Socialist Pary",
        "choices": [
            "Congress Socialist Pary",
            "Communist Party",
            "Kisan Sabha",
            "Congress Party"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who formed the Bihar Socialist Party in 1931",
        "answer": "Phulan Prasad Verma",
        "choices": [
            "Phulan Prasad Verma",
            "Swami Yoginath",
            "Narhari Parikh",
            "Dadabhai Naoroji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who started the Asiatic Society of Bengal in 1784?",
        "answer": "William Jones",
        "choices": [
            "William Jones",
            "Max Muller",
            "Charles William",
            "Charles Hardinge"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who is known as Loknayak",
        "answer": "Jayprakash Narayan",
        "choices": [
            "Jayprakash Narayan",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Subhash Chandra Bose",
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which title was given to Jayaprakash Narayan?",
        "answer": "Lok Nayak",
        "choices": [
            "Lok Nayak",
            "Praja Hitechlu",
            "Rashtra Nayak",
            "Lokmanya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Jay Prakash diwas was celebrated in",
        "answer": "1946 April",
        "choices": [
            "1946 April",
            "1946 January",
            "1946 February",
            "1946 March"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Shri Narsingh Narayan was",
        "answer": "Socialist",
        "choices": [
            "Socialist",
            "Nationalist",
            "Internationalist",
            "Communist"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who became champion of socialism and wanted to overthrow British rule, Princely states, Landlordism and Capitalism in 1933?",
        "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "choices": [
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Bhulabhai Dsai",
            "Sardar Patel"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The provincial Governments were consituted under the act of ",
        "answer": 1935,
        "choices": [
            1935,
            1932,
            1936,
            1947
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which working Committee did the Congress adopt the policy of abolishing land ownership?",
        "answer": "Working Committee, 1937",
        "choices": [
            "Working Committee, 1937",
            "Working Committee, 1942",
            "Working Committee, 1945",
            "Working Committee, 1946"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was elected the President of Indian National Congress in 1938?",
        "answer": "Subhash Chandra Bose",
        "choices": [
            "Subhash Chandra Bose",
            "Abul Kalam Azad",
            "Pattabhi Sitaramaiya",
            "Jivatram Bhagwandas Kriplani"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The purpose of Butler Committee, 1927 was",
        "answer": "improvement of relationship between Indian Provinces and the Crown",
        "choices": [
            "improvement of relationship between Indian Provinces and the Crown",
            "Modernisation of Indian Army",
            "innovative modernisation of Indian Agriculture",
            "Implementation of censor over National Newspaper"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "All India State People's Conference was set up in",
        "answer": 1927,
        "choices": [
            1927,
            1924,
            1926,
            1929
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the British Prime Minister of Britain during the Second World War?",
        "answer": "Winston Churchill",
        "choices": [
            "Winston Churchill",
            "Clement Atlee",
            "Anthony Eden",
            "Herald Wilson"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following led the movement for the separate State Pakistan?",
        "answer": "Muhammad Ali Jinnah",
        "choices": [
            "Muhammad Ali Jinnah",
            "Nawab Salimullah",
            "Aga Khan",
            "Liaquat Ali Khan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The resolution demanding the formation of Pakistan was passed by Muslim league in the year of",
        "answer": 1940,
        "choices": [
            1940,
            1939,
            1941,
            1942
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who started the Individual Satyagraha?",
        "answer": "Vinoba Bhave",
        "choices": [
            "Vinoba Bhave",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Sardar Patel",
            "Shauat Ali"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In 1940, Vinoba Bhave started individual Satyagraha from",
        "answer": "Pavnar, Maharashtra",
        "choices": [
            "Pavnar, Maharashtra",
            "Punnapra-Vayalar, Kerala",
            "Nadiad in Kheda district, Gujarat",
            "Patna, Bihar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the first Satyagrahi of the Individual Satyagraha Movement?",
        "answer": "Vinoba Bhave",
        "choices": [
            "Vinoba Bhave",
            "Chakravarti Rajgopalachari",
            "Subhash Chandra Bose",
            "Sarojini Naidu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the second Satyagrahi of the Individual Satyagraha Movement?",
        "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "choices": [
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Vinoba Bhave",
            "Brahma Dutta",
            "Chakravarti Rajgopalachari"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the third Satyagrahi of the Individual Satyagraha Movement?",
        "answer": "Brahma Dutta",
        "choices": [
            "Brahma Dutta",
            "Vinoba Bhave",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Chakravarti Rajgopalachari"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who decided to oppose the war efforts peacefully by initiating a policy of Individual Civil Disobedience in 1941?",
        "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "choices": [
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Tej Bahadur Sapru",
            "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The word Sarvodaya was primarily used by",
        "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "choices": [
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Vinoba Bhave",
            "Jay Prakash Narayan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who viewed the Cripps proposal as a Post-dated cheque upon a crashing bank?",
        "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "choices": [
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Jivatram Bhagwandas Kriplani",
            "Jay Prakash Narayan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In 1942, in which festival Jai Prakash Narayan escaped from Hazaribgh Jail?",
        "answer": "Deepawali",
        "choices": [
            "Deepawali",
            "Baisakhi",
            "Holi",
            "Dussehra"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "On 6th July, 1942 at the Working Committee of the Congress, Mahatma Gandhi discussed for the first time his Quit India Policy. The President of the Committee was",
        "answer": "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad",
        "choices": [
            "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad",
            "Chakravarti Rajgopalachari",
            "Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Annie Besant"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Quit India movement began on",
        "answer": "9th August 1942",
        "choices": [
            "9th August 1942",
            "15th August 1942",
            "10th August 1942",
            "16th August 1942"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The slogan Do or Die was related with",
        "answer": "Quit India Movement",
        "choices": [
            "Quit India Movement",
            "Dandi March",
            "Khilafat Satyagraha",
            "Non-Cooperation Movement"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When did Baldev Sahai resigned from the post of Advocate General of Bihar?",
        "answer": 1942,
        "choices": [
            1942,
            1943,
            1913,
            1911
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Quit India Movement was led by",
        "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi",
        "choices": [
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Bhim Rao Ambedkar",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Muhammad Ali Jinnah"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "On the outbreak of 1942, the people proclaimed the establishment of a National Government under Siaram Singh at",
        "answer": "Bhagalpur",
        "choices": [
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Patna",
            "Champaran",
            "Begusarai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "All India Azad Dasta at Bakri Ka Tapu was organised during the Quit India Movement by",
        "answer": "Jay Prakash Narayan",
        "choices": [
            "Jay Prakash Narayan",
            "Ram Manohar Lohia",
            "Usha Mehta",
            "Chittu Pandey"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who organised the Azad Dasta?",
        "answer": "Jay Prakash Narayan",
        "choices": [
            "Jay Prakash Narayan",
            "Vinoba Bhave",
            "Jwala Prasad",
            "Chittu Pandey"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "During which movement Azad Dasta was active in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Quit India Movement",
        "choices": [
            "Quit India Movement",
            "Non-Cooperation Movement",
            "Champaran Movment",
            "Civil Disobedience Movement"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Prime Minister of England during the Quit India Movement?",
        "answer": "Winston Churchill",
        "choices": [
            "Winston Churchill",
            "Chamberlain",
            "Clement Atlee",
            "MacDonald"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who launched a secret radio during the Quit India Movement?",
        "answer": "Usha Mehta",
        "choices": [
            "Usha Mehta",
            "Subhadra Kumari Chauhan",
            "Sucheta Kriplani",
            "Annie Besant"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which area was affected widest with the communal riots due to Quit India Movement?",
        "answer": "Bihar & Uttar Pradesh",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar & Uttar Pradesh",
            "Bengal",
            "Gujarat",
            "Bihar & Bengal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Dr Rajendra Prasad was arrested on 9th August 1942 and was sent to",
        "answer": "Bankipur Jail",
        "choices": [
            "Bankipur Jail",
            "Hazaribagh Jail",
            "Camp Jail",
            "Bhagalpur Jail"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "After passing the resolution of Quit India Movement Gandhiji was arrested in",
        "answer": "Aga Khan palace",
        "choices": [
            "Aga Khan palace",
            "Yarawada Jail",
            "Naini Jail",
            "Fort of Ahmednagar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "On 9th August 1942 the two arrested leaders of Hazaribagh were",
        "answer": "Shiv Kumar and Ramanand",
        "choices": [
            "Shiv Kumar and Ramanand",
            "Ramlal and Devilal",
            "Narayan Singh and Sukhlal Singh",
            "Ramnath and Devnath"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "With news of Gandhi and other Congress leaders arrest in 1942, a riot in Bihar took place, leading to a total breakdown in the rail services. The most affected area was",
        "answer": "Munger",
        "choices": [
            "Munger",
            "Gaya",
            "Patna",
            "Shahabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which context did Jay Prakash Narayan get the recognition of national leader?",
        "answer": "Quit India Movement",
        "choices": [
            "Quit India Movement",
            "Establishment of Congress Socialist Party",
            "Bhoodan Movement",
            "Making the member of Congress Executive Committee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following escaped the Hazaribagh Jail during the Quit India Movement?",
        "answer": "Jay Prakash Narayan",
        "choices": [
            "Jay Prakash Narayan",
            "Jagjivan Ram",
            "Sachidanand Sinha",
            "Rafi Ahmed Kidwai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Where was Shri Yogendra Shukla brought on the 7th December 1942",
        "answer": "Patna",
        "choices": [
            "Patna",
            "Ranchi",
            "Munger",
            "Bhagalpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the wife of Mr Jagat Narayan Lal",
        "answer": "Rampyari Devi",
        "choices": [
            "Rampyari Devi",
            "Sundari Devi",
            "Bhagwati Devi",
            "Mangala Devi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who formed the Forward Bloc?",
        "answer": "Subhash Chandra Bose",
        "choices": [
            "Subhash Chandra Bose",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Bhagat Singh",
            "Bhim Rao Ambedkar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which country was the honorific - Netaji - added before the name of Subhash Chandra Bose?",
        "answer": "Germany",
        "choices": [
            "Germany",
            "India",
            "Italy",
            "Japan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who joined Subhas Chandra Bose to found All India Forward Bloc and actively associated with the INA movment?",
        "answer": "Sheel Bhadra Yajee",
        "choices": [
            "Sheel Bhadra Yajee",
            "Jay Prakash Narayan",
            "Baikunth Shukla",
            "Ram Narain Prasad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The result of whose brains is INA and who founded it?",
        "answer": "Mohan Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Mohan Singh",
            "Subhas Chandra Bose",
            "Chandra Shekhar Azad",
            "Bhagat Singh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which year was the Indian National Army founded?",
        "answer": 1942,
        "choices": [
            1942,
            1941,
            1943,
            1940
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Organisation of Azad Hind Fauz was declared on",
        "answer": "21st October 1943",
        "choices": [
            "21st October 1943",
            "26th January 1930",
            "8th August 1942",
            "18th February 1946"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Where was Azad Hind Fauz set up in 1943?",
        "answer": "Malaya",
        "choices": [
            "Malaya",
            "Japan",
            "Singapore",
            "Burma"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following advocates had appeared for the INA trials at Delhi in 1945-46?",
        "answer": "Bhulabhai Desai",
        "choices": [
            "Bhulabhai Desai",
            "Dr Rajendra Prasad",
            "K M Munshi",
            "Sardar Patel"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "At the Congress Working Committee meeting at Allahabad (April-May 1947) who of the following members was able to secure a majority for his plan of a Guerilla War against the Japanese due to India's unequivocal stand against Nazism, Fascism and imperialism?",
        "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "choices": [
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad",
            "Sarojini Naidu",
            "Subhas Chandra Bose"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who proceeded to organise the Provisional Government of Free India outside the country?",
        "answer": "Rash Behari Bose",
        "choices": [
            "Rash Behari Bose",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Raja Mahendra Pratap",
            "Darbhanga Raj"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "With which incident Subhas Chandra Bose compared to Napoleaon's March to Paris on his return from Elba?",
        "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi's Salt March",
        "choices": [
            "Mahatma Gandhi's Salt March",
            "Mahatma Gandhi's participation in Second Round Table Conference",
            "Mahatma Gandhi's Champaran Visit",
            "Mahatma Gandhi's Quit India Movement"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Cabinet Mission was sent to India for which of the following",
        "answer": "to work out a constitutional arrangement for the transfer of power",
        "choices": [
            "to work out a constitutional arrangement for the transfer of power",
            "to establish a national government",
            "to work out the details of Jinnah's demand for Pakistan",
            "All of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following was not a member of the Cabinet Mission sent to India in 1946?",
        "answer": "Ramsay MacDonald",
        "choices": [
            "Ramsay MacDonald",
            "Standfford Cripps",
            "Albert Victor Alexander",
            "Pethick Lawrence"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Cabinet Mission was presided over by",
        "answer": "Pethick Lawrence",
        "choices": [
            "Pethick Lawrence",
            "Standfford Cripps",
            "Albert Victor Alexander",
            "Clement Attlee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Cabinet Mission came to India in",
        "answer": "1946 March",
        "choices": [
            "1946 March",
            "1942 May",
            "1946 February",
            "1942 April"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which Congress President negotiated with both Cripps Mission and Wavell?",
        "answer": "Moulana Abul Kalam Azad",
        "choices": [
            "Moulana Abul Kalam Azad",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Jivatram Bhagwandas Kriplani",
            "Chakravarti Rajgopalachari"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was allotted the Portfolio of the Labour Department in the Interim Government's Cabinet of 1946",
        "answer": "Babu Jagjivan Ram",
        "choices": [
            "Babu Jagjivan Ram",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Anugrah Narayan Sinha",
            "Syed Ali Zaheer"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who presided the first session of the Constituent Assemby formed in 1946",
        "answer": "Sachchidanand Sinha",
        "choices": [
            "Sachchidanand Sinha",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Bhim Rao Ambedkar",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Dr Rajendra Prasad was elected the Chairman of the Constituent Assembly in",
        "answer": "11th December 1946",
        "choices": [
            "11th December 1946",
            "11th November 1946",
            "9th November 1946",
            "9th December 1946"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When was the first meeting of Constituent Assembly held",
        "answer": "9th December 1946",
        "choices": [
            "9th December 1946",
            "11th November 1946",
            "11th December 1946",
            "9th November 1946"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the Finance Minister in the Interim Government?",
        "answer": "Liaquat Ali Khan",
        "choices": [
            "Liaquat Ali Khan",
            "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
            "Muhammad Ali Jinnah",
            "Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which portfolio did Rajendra Prasad hold in the interim government formed in 1946?",
        "answer": "Food & Agriculture",
        "choices": [
            "Food & Agriculture",
            "Finance",
            "Home",
            "Foreign Affairs"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the Congress President at the time of transfer of power in 1947 to India by the British?",
        "answer": "Jivatram Bhagwandas Kriplani",
        "choices": [
            "Jivatram Bhagwandas Kriplani",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the last Governor-General of Independent India",
        "answer": "Chakravarti Rajgopalachari",
        "choices": [
            "Chakravarti Rajgopalachari",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Louis Mountbatten",
            "Charles Canning"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The first Indian to hold office as Governor-General of independent India was",
        "answer": "Chakravarti Rajgopalachari",
        "choices": [
            "Chakravarti Rajgopalachari",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Surinder Nath",
            "Bhim Rao Ambedkar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "On February 20, 1947 Prime Minister Attlee announced the British Government's decision to withdraw from India latest by",
        "answer": "1948 June",
        "choices": [
            "1948 June",
            "1947 August",
            "1948 July",
            "1947 January"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who hailed free India's first Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru as an outstanding leader of courage and vision?",
        "answer": "Louis Mountbatten",
        "choices": [
            "Louis Mountbatten",
            "Moulana Abul Kalam Azad",
            "Sardar Patel",
            "Clement Attlee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which incidents shocked British Prime Minister Clement Attlee, who had to declare that the edifice of the British imperialism had suffered a severe jolt?",
        "answer": "Campaign of the INA and Revolt of the Royal Indian Navy",
        "choices": [
            "Campaign of the INA and Revolt of the Royal Indian Navy",
            "Failure of Cabinet Mission",
            "Revolt of the Royal Indian Navy",
            "Rejection of the Cripps Mission"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Royal Indian Navy Mutiny, also known as the Bombay Mutiny took place in year",
        "answer": 1946,
        "choices": [
            1946,
            1945,
            1947,
            1948
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which of the following Indian National Congress Sessions, the resolutions related to the Fundamental Rights were passed for the first time?",
        "answer": "Karachi 1931",
        "choices": [
            "Karachi 1931",
            "Surat 1907",
            "Gaya 1922",
            "Delhi 1947"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When did the Indian Independence Bill get Royal Assent in England?",
        "answer": "18th July 1947",
        "choices": [
            "18th July 1947",
            "18th June 1947",
            "15th July 1947",
            "15th August 1947"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Under the provision of Regulating Act, a provincial Assembly for Bihar was set up in",
        "answer": 1774,
        "choices": [
            1774,
            1772,
            1776,
            1778
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When did Bihar become a separate province in India?",
        "answer": 1912,
        "choices": [
            1912,
            1774,
            1905,
            1907
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following Acts empowered Charles Cornwallis to overrule the decision of his Council?",
        "answer": "Amending Act of 1786",
        "choices": [
            "Amending Act of 1786",
            "Regulation Act of 1773",
            "Charter Act of 1853",
            "Charter Act of 1813"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When were the rights of the tenants on land in Bengal and Bihar recognised by the Bengal Tenancy Act",
        "answer": 1885,
        "choices": [
            1885,
            1968,
            1881,
            1893
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which Act provisioned competitive exam system for Civil Services?",
        "answer": 1853,
        "choices": [
            1853,
            1833,
            1858,
            1882
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "To control the media in India, Acts were passed in",
        "answer": "1835, 1867, 1878, 1908",
        "choices": [
            "1835, 1867, 1878, 1908",
            "1854, 1864, 1872, 1910",
            "1854, 1872, 1908, 1910",
            "1867, 1908, 1910, 1919"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following Acts introduced separate electorate system in India?",
        "answer": "Indian Councils Act, 1909",
        "choices": [
            "Indian Councils Act, 1909",
            "Regulating Act, 1773",
            "Charter Act of 1853",
            "Pitt's India Act, 1784"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Montagu-Chlemsford Report formed the basis of ",
        "answer": "Government of India Act, 1919",
        "choices": [
            "Government of India Act, 1919",
            "Government of India Act, 1947",
            "Government of India Act, 1935",
            "Indian Councils Act, 1909"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The post of the Indian High Commission was created by which Act?",
        "answer": "Government of India Act, 1919",
        "choices": [
            "Government of India Act, 1919",
            "Government of India Act, 1947",
            "Government of India Act, 1935",
            "Indian Councils Act, 1909"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following became India's unofficial Ambassador to England?",
        "answer": "Dadabhai Naoroji",
        "choices": [
            "Dadabhai Naoroji",
            "Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Swami Vivekanand",
            "Subhas Chandra Bose"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Government of India Act, 1935 abolished",
        "answer": "Provincial Dyarchy",
        "choices": [
            "Provincial Dyarchy",
            "Provincial Autonomy",
            "Federal Structure of India",
            "Responsible Central Government"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who described the Government of India Act, 1935 as a Charter of Slavery?",
        "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru",
        "choices": [
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Subhash Chandra Bose",
            "Maulana Hasrat Mohani"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "About which Act, Jawaharlal Nehru had said, We were provided with a car with all breaks and no engine?",
        "answer": "Government of India Act, 1935",
        "choices": [
            "Government of India Act, 1935",
            "Government of India Act, 1919",
            "Government of India Act, 1947",
            "Indian Councils Act, 1909"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which agreement failed to resolve the border issues between India and China, ultimately leading to the conflict?",
        "answer": "Panchsheel Agreement",
        "choices": [
            "Panchsheel Agreement",
            "Tashkent Agreement",
            "Shimla Agreement",
            "Tibet Agreement"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which Act is not landmark in the development of the Constitution during British Rule?",
        "answer": "Protection of Civil Rights, 1955",
        "choices": [
            "Protection of Civil Rights, 1955",
            "Regulating Act, 1773",
            "Charter Act of 1853",
            "Government of India Act, 1919"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When did Sri Lanka become independent?",
        "answer": 1948,
        "choices": [
            1948,
            1945,
            1947,
            1950
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "During the freedom struggle, a parallel movement launched in the Indian States such as Kashmir, Hyderabad, Travancore etc was",
        "answer": "Praja Mandal Movement",
        "choices": [
            "Praja Mandal Movement",
            "Swaraj Movement",
            "State People's Movement",
            "Provincial Movement"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who started newspaper Motherland in September 1921 to disseminate the Hindu-Muslim unity and Gandhian ideology?",
        "answer": "Maulana Mazharul Haque",
        "choices": [
            "Maulana Mazharul Haque",
            "Anugrah Narayan Sinha",
            "Shambhu Sharan",
            "Shah Mohammad Zubair"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "On which date, Sukhdev, Bhagat Singh and Rajguru were hanged?",
        "answer": "23rd March 1931",
        "choices": [
            "23rd March 1931",
            "12th November 1930",
            "7th September 1931",
            "4th March 1931"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Where was Jhansi ki Rani Laxmibai died?",
        "answer": "Gwalior",
        "choices": [
            "Gwalior",
            "Kanpur",
            "Jhansi",
            "Lucknow"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Subhas Chandra Bose renamed Nicobar Island as",
        "answer": "Swaraj Island",
        "choices": [
            "Swaraj Island",
            "Shaheed Island",
            "Balidan Island",
            "Navodaya Island"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Subhas Chandra Bose renamed Andman Island as",
        "answer": "Shaheed Island",
        "choices": [
            "Shaheed Island",
            "Swaraj Island",
            "Balidan Island",
            "Navodaya Island"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Indian National Congress was founded on the basis of safety valve theory, to protect the British Government from threats. Which leader said that?",
        "answer": "Lala Lajpat Rai",
        "choices": [
            "Lala Lajpat Rai",
            "Chakravarti Rajgopalachari",
            "Bipin Chandra Pal",
            "Dadabhai Naoroji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which of the following event happened first?",
        "answer": "Arrival of the Cripps Mission",
        "choices": [
            "Arrival of the Cripps Mission",
            "Quit India Movement",
            "Arrival of Wavell as the Governor General",
            "Arrival of Cabinet Mission"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Employee State Insuarance Act was passed in",
        "answer": 1948,
        "choices": [
            1948,
            1950,
            1951,
            1949
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Ramchandra Sharma belonged to which village?",
        "answer": "Amhara",
        "choices": [
            "Amhara",
            "Indrapur",
            "Gogri",
            "Pema"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who among the following Indian is known as Gurudev?",
        "answer": "Rabindra Nath Tagore",
        "choices": [
            "Rabindra Nath Tagore",
            "Chakravarti Rajgopalachari",
            "Lala Lajpat Rai",
            "Bhim Rao Ambedkar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who gave the slogan Jai Jawan Jai Kisan",
        "answer": "Lal Bahadur Sashtri",
        "choices": [
            "Lal Bahadur Sashtri",
            "Subhash Chandra Bose",
            "Devi Lal",
            "Morarji Desai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "It will be our blunder if we leave people of Bihar and their Government unsafe before the violence and uncivilised attacks of league leaders. In year 1946 who spoke this?",
        "answer": "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
        "choices": [
            "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Mahatama Gandhi",
            "Rajendra Prasad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who raised the demand of Complete Independence for the first time in 1921",
        "answer": "Moulana Hasrat Mohani",
        "choices": [
            "Moulana Hasrat Mohani",
            "Maulana Muhammad Ali",
            "Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Mahatma Gandhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Banaras Session of August, 1923 of the Hindu Mahasabha was presided over by",
        "answer": "Pandit Madan Mohan Malviya",
        "choices": [
            "Pandit Madan Mohan Malviya",
            "Swami Shraddhanda",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Lala Lajpat Rai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "In which year was Vinayak Damodar Savarkar elected the President of the Hindu Mahasabha?",
        "answer": 1937,
        "choices": [
            1937,
            1935,
            1919,
            1916
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The real name of the Frontier Gandhi is",
        "answer": "Abdul Gaffar Khan",
        "choices": [
            "Abdul Gaffar Khan",
            "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad",
            "Purshottam Das Tandon",
            "Netaji Subhash Chandra Bose"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Ambabai, a woman freedom fighter, belonged to which of the following States of India?",
        "answer": "Karnataka",
        "choices": [
            "Karnataka",
            "Kerala",
            "Andhra Pradesh",
            "Madhya Pradesh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Rajendra Prasad belonged to",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Madhya Pradesh",
            "Punjab"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Jagat Narayan Lal was sent to",
        "answer": "Hazaribagh Jail",
        "choices": [
            "Hazaribagh Jail",
            "Bankipur Jail",
            "Camp Jail",
            "Bhagalpur Jail"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "To establish global peace and cooperation among the people, which of the following concept introduced by the Jawaharlal Nehru?",
        "answer": "Non-Alignment",
        "choices": [
            "Non-Alignment",
            "Panchsheel",
            "Peaceful Coexistence",
            "Akhand Bharat"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Name the Deoband scholar who played a significant role in freedom movement.",
        "answer": "Abul Kalam Azad",
        "choices": [
            "Abul Kalam Azad",
            "Muhammad Ali Jinnah",
            "Badruddin Tyabji",
            "Chirag Ali"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who organised the Khudai Khidmatgar in 1929?",
        "answer": "Khan Abdul Gaffar Khan",
        "choices": [
            "Khan Abdul Gaffar Khan",
            "Ali Brothers",
            "Ansari Brothers",
            "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "When was the Punjab Land Alienation Act passed?",
        "answer": 1900,
        "choices": [
            1900,
            1850,
            1895,
            1905
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Department of State was established under whose headship?",
        "answer": "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
        "choices": [
            "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Mahatama Gandhi",
            "G B Pant"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The objective of Antodaya program is ",
        "answer": "to help the poorest of poor",
        "choices": [
            "to help the poorest of poor",
            "development of minorities",
            "advancement of Dalits",
            "complete eradication of poverty"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who is considered as the creator of Modern Bihar?",
        "answer": "Sachchidanand Sinha",
        "choices": [
            "Sachchidanand Sinha",
            "Kumar Kalika Prasad Sinha",
            "Acharya Narendra Dev",
            "Jai Prakash Narayan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Religious Organisation established by Mother Teresa is called",
        "answer": "Missionaries of Charity",
        "choices": [
            "Missionaries of Charity",
            "Sisters of Charity",
            "Organisation of Love",
            "Charity of all"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which organisation of India has the motto, Dharmo Rakshati Rakshitah?",
        "answer": "Research and Analysis Wing",
        "choices": [
            "Research and Analysis Wing",
            "Indian Army",
            "Indian Supreme Court",
            "Indian Navy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Indian Nationalist leader who delivered lecture on Joseph Mazzini and the Young Italy movement was",
        "answer": "Surendranath Banerjee",
        "choices": [
            "Surendranath Banerjee",
            "Subhash Chandra Bose",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Mahatma Gandhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Welby Commission 1895 was constituted on which of the following matters?",
        "answer": "Indian Expenditure",
        "choices": [
            "Indian Expenditure",
            "Education in India",
            "Land Revenue",
            "Indian Military"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Hitler's autobiography which outlined his political ideology and future plans for Germany, is titled",
        "answer": "Mein Kampf",
        "choices": [
            "Mein Kampf",
            "Das Kapital",
            "Communist Manifesto",
            "Tryst with Truth"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who wrote the book, India Divided?",
        "answer": "Rajendra Prasad",
        "choices": [
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad",
            "Penderel Moon",
            "Ambra Prasad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which one of the following was a journal brought out by Abul Kalam Azad?",
        "answer": "Al-Hilal",
        "choices": [
            "Al-Hilal",
            "Hunkar",
            "Zamindar",
            "The Comrade"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who started the journal Bahishkrit Bharat?",
        "answer": "Babasahed Ambedkar",
        "choices": [
            "Babasahed Ambedkar",
            "Jyotiba Phule",
            "Karsandas Mulji",
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Which one of the following books was written by Tilak?",
        "answer": "Gita Rahasya",
        "choices": [
            "Gita Rahasya",
            "India in Transition",
            "Gokhale-My Political Guru",
            "Discovery of India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the author of the book, Mahatma Gandhi and Bihar: Some Reminiscences?",
        "answer": "Rajendra Prasad",
        "choices": [
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Syed Ali Zaheer",
            "Jivatram Bhagwandas Kriplani",
            "Raj Kumar Shukla"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "What was the name of the first book of Raja Ram Mohan Roy published in 1815?",
        "answer": "Vedanta Grantha",
        "choices": [
            "Vedanta Grantha",
            "Tuhfat-ul-Muwahhidin",
            "Bharathi Vilasa",
            "Shakuntalam"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who was the author of Indian Unrest?",
        "answer": "Valentine Chirol",
        "choices": [
            "Valentine Chirol",
            "Dadabhai Naoroji",
            "Annie Besant",
            "Lala Lajpat Rai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who has written the book Unhappy India?",
        "answer": "Lala Lajpat Rai",
        "choices": [
            "Lala Lajpat Rai",
            "Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
            "Annie Besant",
            "Allan Octavian Hume"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who wrote the book, Poverty and un-British Rule in India?",
        "answer": "Dadabhai Naoroji",
        "choices": [
            "Dadabhai Naoroji",
            "R C Dutta",
            "Bipin Chandra Pal",
            "Lala Lajpat Rai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who had translated the Bengali play, Nil Darpan into English?",
        "answer": "Micheal Madhusudan Dutt",
        "choices": [
            "Micheal Madhusudan Dutt",
            "Dinabandhu Mitra",
            "James Long",
            "Antonio Gramsci"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Who wrote the book, India for Indians?",
        "answer": "Chittaranjan Das",
        "choices": [
            "Chittaranjan Das",
            "M G Ranade",
            "Vinayak Damodar Savarkar",
            "Surendranath Banerjee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The novel Durgesha Nandini is written by",
        "answer": "Bankim Chandra Chatterjee",
        "choices": [
            "Bankim Chandra Chatterjee",
            "Rabindranath Tagore",
            "Taraknath Gangopadhayaya",
            "Swarna Kumari"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The temple of Deogarh near Jhansi and the sculptures in the temples at Garhwa near Allahabad are the important remains of the",
        "answer": "Gupta Art",
        "choices": [
            "Gupta Art",
            "Maurya Art",
            "Rashtrakuta Art",
            "Mughal Art"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "Pietra Dura is related to which of the following?",
        "answer": "Decorating the walls with floral designs made of semi-precious stones",
        "choices": [
            "Decorating the walls with floral designs made of semi-precious stones",
            "building sloping walls in Minars",
            "Use of arch in constuction",
            "use of marble in buildings"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The Brihadisvara Temple in Thanjavur was constructed by which King?",
        "answer": "Rajaraja I",
        "choices": [
            "Rajaraja I",
            "Rajendra I",
            "Rajendra II",
            "Kulottunga I"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryModern",
        "question": "The mighty gateways found at the temples of South India are called",
        "answer": "Gopurams",
        "choices": [
            "Gopurams",
            "Shikhars",
            "Devalayas",
            "Mandaps"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which one of the following periods is also known as Chalcolithic Age?",
        "answer": "Copper Age",
        "choices": [
            "Copper Age",
            "Old Stone Age",
            "New Stone Age",
            "Iron Age"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Indus Civilisation existed in",
        "answer": "Proto-Historic age",
        "choices": [
            "Proto-Historic age",
            "Pre-Historic age",
            "Historic age",
            "Post-Historic age"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The earliest evidence of animal domestication and agriculture in India has come from",
        "answer": "Mehrgarh",
        "choices": [
            "Mehrgarh",
            "Harappa",
            "Lothal",
            "Diamabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The earliest evidence of rice cultivation in Ganga valley comes from",
        "answer": "Lahuradewa",
        "choices": [
            "Lahuradewa",
            "Mehrgarh",
            "Lothal",
            "Diamabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which colour was commonly used in the Harappan Pottery?",
        "answer": "Red-Black",
        "choices": [
            "Red-Black",
            "Yellow",
            "Green",
            "Blue-Grey"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In which of the following Harappan cities, furrows of ploughed fields have been found?",
        "answer": "Kalibangan",
        "choices": [
            "Kalibangan",
            "Dholavira",
            "Mohenjodaro",
            "Lothal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In which of the following Harappan sites, terracotta of plough has been found?",
        "answer": "Banawali",
        "choices": [
            "Banawali",
            "Dholavira",
            "Kalibangan",
            "Lothal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "What is the most significant feature of the Indus Valley Civilisation?",
        "answer": "Use of burnt bricks",
        "choices": [
            "Use of burnt bricks",
            "Fine true arches",
            "Buildings of worship",
            "Art & Architecture"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following animals was not known to the people of Indus Valley Civilisation",
        "answer": "Horse",
        "choices": [
            "Horse",
            "Humped Bull (Zebu)",
            "Deer",
            "Elephant"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is Harappan Port",
        "answer": "Lothal",
        "choices": [
            "Lothal",
            "Diamabad",
            "Nagapattinam",
            "Mahasthangarh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is the largest Harappan site in India",
        "answer": "Rakhigarhi",
        "choices": [
            "Rakhigarhi",
            "Mohenjodaro",
            "Lothal",
            "Kalibangan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is the largest Harappan site",
        "answer": "Mohenjodaro",
        "choices": [
            "Mohenjodaro",
            "Rakhigarhi",
            "Lothal",
            "Kalibangan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is the western most Harappan site",
        "answer": "Sutkagendor",
        "choices": [
            "Sutkagendor",
            "Shortugai",
            "Alamgirpur",
            "Diamabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is the eastern most Harappan site",
        "answer": "Alamgirpur",
        "choices": [
            "Alamgirpur",
            "Shortugai",
            "Suktagendor",
            "Diamabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is the northern most Harappan site",
        "answer": "Shortugai",
        "choices": [
            "Shortugai",
            "Alamgirpur",
            "Suktagendor",
            "Diamabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is the southern most Harappan site",
        "answer": "Diamabad",
        "choices": [
            "Diamabad",
            "Alamgirpur",
            "Suktagendor",
            "Shortugai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following Harappan site is associated with trade in Lapis Lazuli",
        "answer": "Shortugai",
        "choices": [
            "Shortugai",
            "Sutkagendor",
            "Surkotada",
            "Manda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is a Harappan site in Gujarat",
        "answer": "Lothal",
        "choices": [
            "Lothal",
            "Dabarkot",
            "Kalibangan",
            "Rakhigarhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who among the following was not associated with the excavation of Harappa and Mohenjodaro?",
        "answer": "V A Smith",
        "choices": [
            "V A Smith",
            "R D Banerjee",
            "K N Dikshit",
            "M S Vats"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "According to report of IIT Kharagpur study group, continous low rainfall for how many years was the cause of fall of the Indus Valley civilisation?",
        "answer": "900 years",
        "choices": [
            "900 years",
            "600 years",
            "700 years",
            "800 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "When did the use of Iron begin in Indian Subcontinent?",
        "answer": "Around 3000 years ago",
        "choices": [
            "Around 3000 years ago",
            "Around 6000 years ago",
            "Around 9000 years ago",
            "Around 10000 years ago"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which mandala of Rig Veda is completely dedicated to 'Soma'?",
        "answer": "Ninth Mandala",
        "choices": [
            "Ninth Mandala",
            "Seventh Mandala",
            "Eighth Mandala",
            "Tenth Mandala"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Name the ancient site outside India from where inscription containing Rigvedic dieties names has been found",
        "answer": "Boghazkoi",
        "choices": [
            "Boghazkoi",
            "Babylon",
            "Gonur Tepe",
            "Ur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Famous Battle of Ten Kings was fought on the bank of river:",
        "answer": "Parushni",
        "choices": [
            "Parushni",
            "Ganga",
            "Brahmputra",
            "Kaveri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In which Mandala of Rigveda, Battle of Ten Kings is mentioned",
        "answer": "Seventh Mandala",
        "choices": [
            "Seventh Mandala",
            "Eighth Mandala",
            "Tenth Mandala",
            "Ninth Mandala"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In which Mandala of Rigveda, Gayatri Mantra is mentioned",
        "answer": "Third Mandala",
        "choices": [
            "Third Mandala",
            "Eighth Mandala",
            "Seventh Mandala",
            "Ninth Mandala"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In which book Gayatri Mantra is found",
        "answer": "Rig Veda",
        "choices": [
            "Rig Veda",
            "Upanishad",
            "Bhagwatgita",
            "Ramayana"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Gayatri Mantra is dedicated to which diety",
        "answer": "Sun",
        "choices": [
            "Sun",
            "Parvati",
            "Shiva",
            "Indra"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In which phase, the concept of untouchability was put clearly?",
        "answer": "Dharmashastra Phase",
        "choices": [
            "Dharmashastra Phase",
            "Rigvedic Phase",
            "Later Vedic Phase",
            "Later Gupta Phase"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which ancient Indian text, composed during the later Vedic period, contains philosophical hymns and discussions on cosmology and ethics?",
        "answer": "Upanishads",
        "choices": [
            "Upanishads",
            "Rigveda",
            "Yajurveda",
            "Samveda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Where did Mahatma Buddha's Mahaparinirvana take place",
        "answer": "Khushi Nagar",
        "choices": [
            "Khushi Nagar",
            "Lumbini",
            "Kapilvastu",
            "Bodhgaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The ruler of Suvarnabhumi, who founded a Buddhist monastery at Nalanda and requested Devapala through his ambassador to grant, five villages for its maintenance, was",
        "answer": "Balaputradeva",
        "choices": [
            "Balaputradeva",
            "Dharanindra",
            "Sangramadhanjaya",
            "Chudamanivarmana"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "At which place did Mahatma Buddha give his first Dharmachakkhapavathana?",
        "answer": "Sarnath",
        "choices": [
            "Sarnath",
            "Lumbini",
            "Khushi Nagar",
            "Kapilvastu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who got enlightenment in Bodh Gaya?",
        "answer": "Gautam Buddha",
        "choices": [
            "Gautam Buddha",
            "Mahavir Jain",
            "Smandhar Swami",
            "Parshvanath Swami"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Gautam Buddha gave his first sermon at",
        "answer": "Sarnath",
        "choices": [
            "Sarnath",
            "Vaishali",
            "Kaushambi",
            "Pavapuri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following rulers convened the fourth Buddhist Council in Kashmir?",
        "answer": "Kanishka",
        "choices": [
            "Kanishka",
            "Ashoka",
            "Ajatshatru",
            "kalashoka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "A Buddhist Council during the reign of Kanishka was held at",
        "answer": "Kashmir",
        "choices": [
            "Kashmir",
            "Magadha",
            "Pataliputra",
            "Rajgriha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Where was the third Buddhist Council held?",
        "answer": "Pataliputra",
        "choices": [
            "Pataliputra",
            "Sarnath",
            "Taxila",
            "Bodh Gaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The third Buddhist Council was presided over by",
        "answer": "Moggaliputta-Tissa",
        "choices": [
            "Moggaliputta-Tissa",
            "Mahakassapa",
            "Vasumitra",
            "Ashvaghosha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In Indian art, the construction of Stupa, Chaitya and Vihara is related to which of the following?",
        "answer": "Buddhism",
        "choices": [
            "Buddhism",
            "Jainism",
            "Vaishanva sect",
            "Shaiva sect"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Mahabodhi temple has been built at Bodh Gaya where",
        "answer": "Gautam Buddha received enlightenment",
        "choices": [
            "Gautam Buddha received enlightenment",
            "Gautam Buddha was born",
            "Gautam Buddha gave his first sermon",
            "Gautam Buddha passed away"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The present Bodhi Vriksha in Bodh Gaya belongs to which generation of family",
        "answer": "Fifth",
        "choices": [
            "Fifth",
            "Fourth",
            "Third",
            "Sixth"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "After the Mahaparinirvana of Lord Buddha, the first Buddhist council was held at",
        "answer": "Rajgriha (Rajgir)",
        "choices": [
            "Rajgriha (Rajgir)",
            "Pataliputra (Patna)",
            "Kundalvana (Kashmir)",
            "Vaishali"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Tripatikas are the sacred books of the",
        "answer": "Buddhists",
        "choices": [
            "Buddhists",
            "Jains",
            "Hindus",
            "Parsis"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following buddhist literature is not grouped as Tripitaks",
        "answer": "Milind Panha",
        "choices": [
            "Milind Panha",
            "Sutta Pitaka",
            "Vinay Pitaka",
            "Abhidhamma Pitaka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Where is the highest Vishwa Shanti Stupa located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Rajgir",
        "choices": [
            "Rajgir",
            "Vaishali",
            "Patna",
            "Nalanda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Barabudur is the most wonderful Stupa in the world and its images and sculptures are the finest examples of",
        "answer": "Indo-Javanese Art",
        "choices": [
            "Indo-Javanese Art",
            "Indo-Tibetan Art",
            "Indo-Cambodian Art",
            "Indo-Champan Art"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Gautam Buddha was elevated to the position of God during the period of",
        "answer": "Kanishka",
        "choices": [
            "Kanishka",
            "Ashoka",
            "Chandragupta Vikramaditya",
            "Harsha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Where is Odantipuri (Uddandapura) Mahavihar located?",
        "answer": "Bihar Sharif",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar Sharif",
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Nalanda",
            "Bengal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Odantipuri (Uddandapura) Mahavihar was established by",
        "answer": "Gopal",
        "choices": [
            "Gopal",
            "Kumargupta",
            "Dharampala",
            "Ajatshatru"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Nalanda University was founded during the dynasty of",
        "answer": "Gupta",
        "choices": [
            "Gupta",
            "Kushan",
            "Maurya",
            "Pala"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Why was Nalanda University famous in the world?",
        "answer": "Buddhist Religious Philosophy",
        "choices": [
            "Buddhist Religious Philosophy",
            "Medical Science",
            "Philosophy",
            "Chemical Science"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the founder of Nalanda University?",
        "answer": "Kumargupta",
        "choices": [
            "Kumargupta",
            "Chandragupta Vikramaditya",
            "Dharampala",
            "Pushyagupta"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Nav Nalanda Mahavihar is famous for",
        "answer": "Pali Research Centre",
        "choices": [
            "Pali Research Centre",
            "Museum",
            "Hsuan-Tsang Memorial",
            "Birth place of Mahavir"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which one of the following is not common between Buddhism and Jainism?",
        "answer": "Self-Mortification",
        "choices": [
            "Self-Mortification",
            "Ahimsa",
            "Indifference to Vedas",
            "Rejection of Rituals"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The painting of Bodhisattva Padmapani is located at",
        "answer": "Ajanta",
        "choices": [
            "Ajanta",
            "Ellora",
            "Rajgir",
            "Barabar Hills"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Where was Mahavira Swami born",
        "answer": "Kundgram (Vaishali)",
        "choices": [
            "Kundgram (Vaishali)",
            "Pataliputra (Patna)",
            "Rajgriha (Rajgir)",
            "Lumbini"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Mahavir Jain breathed his last at",
        "answer": "Pavapuri",
        "choices": [
            "Pavapuri",
            "Kundgram (Vaishali)",
            "Rajgriha (Rajgir)",
            "Kapilvastu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The salvation place of Mahavirji, the originator of Jain religion, is located at",
        "answer": "Jrimbhikagrama (Jamui)",
        "choices": [
            "Jrimbhikagrama (Jamui)",
            "Kundgram (Vaishali)",
            "Rajgriha (Rajgir)",
            "Bodh Gaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Triratna or Three Jewels i.e. right knowledge, right faith and right action are related to which of the following?",
        "answer": "Jainism",
        "choices": [
            "Jainism",
            "Buddhism",
            "Hinduism",
            "Christianity"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following is the earliest holy book of Jain?",
        "answer": "Fourteen Purvas",
        "choices": [
            "Fourteen Purvas",
            "Fourteen Uppurva",
            "Twelve angas",
            "Twelve Upangas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the first disciple of Lord Mahavira",
        "answer": "Jamali",
        "choices": [
            "Jamali",
            "Yashoda",
            "Bipin",
            "Prabhash"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Ajivika sect was founded by",
        "answer": "Makkhali Gosala",
        "choices": [
            "Makkhali Gosala",
            "Anand",
            "Rahulabhadra ",
            "Upali"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who used the caves of Barabar as their shelter-house?",
        "answer": "Ajivikas",
        "choices": [
            "Ajivikas",
            "Jains",
            "Tantrikas",
            "Buddhists"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who of the following kings was strongly inclined towards Jainism?",
        "answer": "Kharavela",
        "choices": [
            "Kharavela",
            "Dasaratha",
            "Brihadrath",
            "Huvishk"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Gorathagiri in the Barabar Hills was conquered by",
        "answer": "Kharavela",
        "choices": [
            "Kharavela",
            "Rajaraja Chola",
            "Menander",
            "Pushyamitra Sunga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Nathpanthis, Siddhas and Yogis made devotional religion popular in",
        "answer": "Northern India",
        "choices": [
            "Northern India",
            "Southern India",
            "Eastern India",
            "Western India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who contributes the most in the development of Bhagavata sect?",
        "answer": "Gupta",
        "choices": [
            "Gupta",
            "Persian",
            "Indo-Greek people",
            "Kushan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In ancient times, the area to the south of the Ganga was known as",
        "answer": "Magadh",
        "choices": [
            "Magadh",
            "Chola",
            "Anarta",
            "Takshashila"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which was the first capital of ancient Mahajanapada Magadh?",
        "answer": "Rajgriha (Rajgir)",
        "choices": [
            "Rajgriha (Rajgir)",
            "Pataliputra (Patna)",
            "Vaishali",
            "Anga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which ruler founded the beautiful city, Pataliputra?",
        "answer": "Ajatashatru",
        "choices": [
            "Ajatashatru",
            "Bimbisara",
            "Bindusara",
            "Udayin"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "By which ruler Pataliputra was chosen as a capital for the first time?",
        "answer": "Udayin",
        "choices": [
            "Udayin",
            "Ajatashatru",
            "Kalashoka",
            "Kanishka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "According to Mahavamsa, Bimbisara ascended the throne at the age of ",
        "answer": "15 years",
        "choices": [
            "15 years",
            "18 years",
            "20 years",
            "12 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In which century did the first Magadhan Empire rise?",
        "answer": "6th centurey BCE",
        "choices": [
            "6th centurey BCE",
            "4th centurey BCE",
            "7th centurey BCE",
            "5th centurey BCE"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Magadha and Anga plains are part of which of the following?",
        "answer": "Middle Ganga Valley",
        "choices": [
            "Middle Ganga Valley",
            "Upper Ganga Valley",
            "Lower Ganga Valley",
            "Lower Brahmputra Valley"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Where was the world's first republican system in the 6th century BCE?",
        "answer": "Vaishali",
        "choices": [
            "Vaishali",
            "Athens",
            "Pataliputra",
            "Spata"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The list of sixteen Mahajanapadas is available in",
        "answer": "Anguttar Nikaya",
        "choices": [
            "Anguttar Nikaya",
            "Mahabharata",
            "Chandogya Upanishad",
            "Samyukta Nikaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "What was the name of the dynasty of Ajatashatru?",
        "answer": "Haryanka",
        "choices": [
            "Haryanka",
            "Maurya",
            "Gupta",
            "Nanda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the physician of Magadha ruler Bimbisara?",
        "answer": "Jeevaka",
        "choices": [
            "Jeevaka",
            "Shilabhadra",
            "Vijayaena",
            "Manu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which dynasty did rule over Magadha after Nanda Dynasty?",
        "answer": "Maurya",
        "choices": [
            "Maurya",
            "Shunga",
            "Gupta",
            "Kushan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the last king of Karnata dynasty?",
        "answer": "Harisimhadev",
        "choices": [
            "Harisimhadev",
            "Ramsimhadev",
            "Nanyadeva",
            "Narsimhadeva"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which one of the following rulers of the Magadha was the contemporary of Alexander?",
        "answer": "Dhanananda",
        "choices": [
            "Dhanananda",
            "Mahapadmananda",
            "Sukalpa",
            "Chandragupta Maurya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The first empire was established by which ruler in India?",
        "answer": "Chandragupta Maurya",
        "choices": [
            "Chandragupta Maurya",
            "Ashoka",
            "Kanishka",
            "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Chandragupta Maurya figures prominently in the book of",
        "answer": "Vishakhadatta",
        "choices": [
            "Vishakhadatta",
            "Bhasa",
            "Surdraka",
            "Ashvaghosha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who recognised Sandoorkottos as Chandragupta Maurya?",
        "answer": "William Jones",
        "choices": [
            "William Jones",
            "V. Smith",
            "R. K. Mukharjee",
            "D. R. Bhandarkar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Chandragupta's palace situated at Pataliputra is mainly made up of",
        "answer": "Woods",
        "choices": [
            "Woods",
            "Bricks",
            "Stones",
            "Clay"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who amongst the following Mauryan rulers did conquer the Deccan?",
        "answer": "Chandragupta Maurya",
        "choices": [
            "Chandragupta Maurya",
            "Ashoka",
            "Bindusara",
            "Kunala"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which book describe Bindusara as an anointed Kshtriya?",
        "answer": "Divyadana",
        "choices": [
            "Divyadana",
            "Rajatarangini",
            "Arthashastra",
            "Indica"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The inscription which proves Chandragupta's sway over western India is",
        "answer": "Junagarh Rock Inscription of Rudradaman",
        "choices": [
            "Junagarh Rock Inscription of Rudradaman",
            "Kalinga Rock Inscriptions",
            "Girnar Rock Inscription of Ashoka",
            "Sopara Rock Inscription of Ashoka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which one territory of the following was not a part of Ashoka's empire?",
        "answer": "Sri Lanka",
        "choices": [
            "Sri Lanka",
            "Afghanistan",
            "Bihar",
            "Kalinga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "A Buddhist Council during the reign of  Ashoka was held at",
        "answer": "Pataliputra",
        "choices": [
            "Pataliputra",
            "Vaishali",
            "Rajgir",
            "Kanauj"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Language used in the incription of Ashoka is ",
        "answer": "Prakrit",
        "choices": [
            "Prakrit",
            "Sanskrit",
            "Pali",
            "Hindi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which one of the following scripts of ancient India was written from right to left?",
        "answer": "Kharosthi",
        "choices": [
            "Kharosthi",
            "Brahmi",
            "Devanagri",
            "Kaithi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who first discovered the Brahmi script?",
        "answer": "James Prinsep",
        "choices": [
            "James Prinsep",
            "A Cunningham",
            "A. H. Dani",
            "Buhler"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The name by which Ashoka is referred to in his incriptions is",
        "answer": "Priyadarshi",
        "choices": [
            "Priyadarshi",
            "Chakravarti",
            "Dharamadeva",
            "Dharmakirti"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The only pillar on which Ashoka declares himself as the emperor of Magadha",
        "answer": "Bhabru Pillar",
        "choices": [
            "Bhabru Pillar",
            "Minor Pillar of Maski",
            "Rummindei Pillar",
            "Queen Pillar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Megasthenes was the ambassador of",
        "answer": "Seleucus I Nicator",
        "choices": [
            "Seleucus I Nicator",
            "Alexander",
            "Darius",
            "Napolean"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In how many categories did Megasthenes divide the Indian society?",
        "answer": "Seven",
        "choices": [
            "Seven",
            "Six",
            "Five",
            "Four"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The division of Mauryan society into seven classes is particularly mentioned in",
        "answer": "The Indica of Megasthenes",
        "choices": [
            "The Indica of Megasthenes",
            "Kautilya's Arthashastra",
            "Ashokan Rock Edicts",
            "The Puranas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The description of the administration of Pataliputra is available in",
        "answer": "The Indica of Megasthenes",
        "choices": [
            "The Indica of Megasthenes",
            "Kautilya's Arthashastra",
            "Ashokan Rock Edicts",
            "Divyanadan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "What is the name of Megasthenes book?",
        "answer": "Indica",
        "choices": [
            "Indica",
            "Rig Veda",
            "Purana",
            "Economics"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the author of Indica?",
        "answer": "Megasthenes",
        "choices": [
            "Megasthenes",
            "Deimachus",
            "Vishnugupta",
            "Pliny"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The last Mauryan emperor was",
        "answer": "Brihadratha",
        "choices": [
            "Brihadratha",
            "Jaloka",
            "Avanti Verma",
            "Nandi Vardhana"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The decline of the Mauryan Empire was largely due to the economic consequences of Ashoka's policy. Who believed in this fact?",
        "answer": "Romila Thapar",
        "choices": [
            "Romila Thapar",
            "V. A. Smith",
            "D. N. Jha",
            "H. C. Raychaudhari"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Pradyota was the king of",
        "answer": "Avanti",
        "choices": [
            "Avanti",
            "Kasi",
            "Koshala",
            "Magadha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which inscription tells about the various achievements of Rudraman-I?",
        "answer": "Junagadh",
        "choices": [
            "Junagadh",
            "Bhitari",
            "Nasik",
            "Sanchi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "According to the rock inscription in Sanskrit, composed around 2nd Century CE, Sudarshan Lake, an artificial reservoir, was repaired by",
        "answer": "Rudradaman",
        "choices": [
            "Rudradaman",
            "Harsha",
            "Kanishka",
            "Ashoka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who among the following first issued gold coins on a large scale?",
        "answer": "Vima Kadphises",
        "choices": [
            "Vima Kadphises",
            "Pushyamitra Shunga",
            "Menander",
            "Gautamiputra Satkarni"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which dynasty ruled over India after Shunga dynasty?",
        "answer": "Kanva",
        "choices": [
            "Kanva",
            "Satvahana",
            "Gupta",
            "Kushan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Art of Gandhara style flourished during the reign of",
        "answer": "Kushans",
        "choices": [
            "Kushans",
            "Guptas",
            "Mauryas",
            "Kanvas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "King Kharavela is related to",
        "answer": "Hathigumpha Inscription",
        "choices": [
            "Hathigumpha Inscription",
            "Piller inscription of Girnar",
            "Pillar inscription of Junagarh",
            "Sarnath Inscription"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Kaling king Kharavel was related to ",
        "answer": "Mahameghavahana / Chedi Dynasty",
        "choices": [
            "Mahameghavahana / Chedi Dynasty",
            "Satvahana Dynasty",
            "Rath-Bhojak Dynasty",
            "Maurya Dynasty"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which Gupta ruler assumed the throne after killing his elder brother?",
        "answer": "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya",
        "choices": [
            "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya",
            "Shri Gupta",
            "Samudragupta",
            "Skandagupta"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who is called the Napolean of Ancient India?",
        "answer": "Samudragupta",
        "choices": [
            "Samudragupta",
            "Shri Gupta",
            "Chandragupta Maurya",
            "Pushyamitra Sunga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "According to Chinese source, Meghavarman, the ruler of Sri Lanka, sent a missionary to which of the following Gupta Kings for permission to build a Buddhist temple at Gaya?",
        "answer": "Samudragupta",
        "choices": [
            "Samudragupta",
            "Chandragupta I",
            "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya",
            "Shir Gupta"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The Gupta emperor who defeated the Hunas was",
        "answer": "Skandagupta",
        "choices": [
            "Skandagupta",
            "Chandragupta I",
            "Samudragupta",
            "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which Gupta ruler is mentioned as Param Bhagawata in Nalanda Copper Plates?",
        "answer": "Samudragupta",
        "choices": [
            "Samudragupta",
            "Chandragupta I",
            "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya",
            "Skandagupta"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "In Pre-Gupta times, a large number of lead coins were issued by the",
        "answer": "Satavahanas",
        "choices": [
            "Satavahanas",
            "Shakas",
            "Kushans",
            "Mauryas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The gradual decline of towns was an important feature of which period?",
        "answer": "Gupta period",
        "choices": [
            "Gupta period",
            "Pratihara era",
            "Rashtrakut era",
            "Satavahana era"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which ruling dynasty donated maximum villages to temples and Brahmins?",
        "answer": "Gupta Dynasty",
        "choices": [
            "Gupta Dynasty",
            "Pala Dynasty",
            "Rashtrakuta",
            "Pratihara"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "What was the land revenue rate in Gupta age?",
        "answer": "Sixth part of the production",
        "choices": [
            "Sixth part of the production",
            "tenth part of the production",
            "half part of the production",
            "third part of the production"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "What is the land revenue rate in religious books?",
        "answer": "One-sixth",
        "choices": [
            "One-sixth",
            "One-eighth",
            "One-third",
            "One-fourth"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which type of land was called Aprahat",
        "answer": "Without cultivated forest land",
        "choices": [
            "Without cultivated forest land",
            "Irrigated land",
            "Dense Forest Land",
            "Cultivated Land"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Chinese traveller Sungyun or Song Yun came to India during",
        "answer": "518 to 521 CE",
        "choices": [
            "518 to 521 CE",
            "525 to 5529 CE",
            "545 to 552 CE",
            "592 to 597 CE"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The account of the Moroccan traveller Ibn Battuta is known as",
        "answer": "Rihla",
        "choices": [
            "Rihla",
            "Tarikh-i-Rashidi",
            "Subh-u'l-Asha",
            "Riyaz-us-salatin"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following philosophies of India propounded the atom theory?",
        "answer": "Vaisheshika",
        "choices": [
            "Vaisheshika",
            "Nyaya",
            "Sankhya",
            "Yoga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who has written the Harshacharita",
        "answer": "Banabhatta",
        "choices": [
            "Banabhatta",
            "Aryabhatta",
            "Vishnugupta",
            "Parimalgupta"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who laid the foundation of Vardhana Dynasty?",
        "answer": "Pushyabhuti",
        "choices": [
            "Pushyabhuti",
            "Rajyavardhana",
            "Harshavardhana",
            "Prabhakarvardhana"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which Chinese traveller visited India during Haravardhana's rule?",
        "answer": "Hiuen-Tsang",
        "choices": [
            "Hiuen-Tsang",
            "Fa-Hien",
            "I-Tsing",
            "Taranath"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The famous Chinese pilgrim Fa-Hien visited India during the reign of",
        "answer": "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya",
        "choices": [
            "Chandragupta II - Vikramaditya",
            "Harshavardhana",
            "Ramagupta",
            "Chandragupta I"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "During Hiuen-Tsang tour in India most famous city for the production of cotton clothes was",
        "answer": "Mathura",
        "choices": [
            "Mathura",
            "Varanasi",
            "Pataliputra",
            "Kanchi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Chinese traveller Hiuen-Tsang studied at which univesity",
        "answer": "Nalanda",
        "choices": [
            "Nalanda",
            "Taxilla",
            "Vikramshila",
            "Uddandapura"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Chinese traveller I-tsing was on the tour of Bihar in about",
        "answer": "671 CE",
        "choices": [
            "671 CE",
            "405 CE",
            "635 CE",
            "637 CE"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Nalanda Vihar was destroyed by",
        "answer": "Bakhtiyar Khalji",
        "choices": [
            "Bakhtiyar Khalji",
            "Qutubuddin Aibak",
            "Muhammad Bin Tughlaq",
            "Alauddin Khalji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the real founder of Turk rule in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Bakhtiyar Khalji",
        "choices": [
            "Bakhtiyar Khalji",
            "Malik Husarnuddin",
            "Ibrahim",
            "Dariya Khan Noohani"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "How many rulers of Aryavarta have been mentioned in 21st line of Allahabad Pillar Inscription?",
        "answer": "Nine",
        "choices": [
            "Nine",
            "Eight",
            "Seven",
            "Six"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who has argued that the Gupta and post-Gupta periods saw a decline in the money economy?",
        "answer": "R. S. Sharma",
        "choices": [
            "R. S. Sharma",
            "R. S. Tripathi",
            "Radha Kumud Mookerjee",
            "D. C. Sircar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the ruler of India during the 7th cneture CE known for his patronage of Buddhism and support for cultural activities?",
        "answer": "Harsha",
        "choices": [
            "Harsha",
            "Ashoka",
            "Chandragupta Maurya",
            "Vikramaditya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The associates of Khajuraho Temple Architecture were",
        "answer": "Chandela",
        "choices": [
            "Chandela",
            "Chahamana",
            "Gurjara-Pratihara",
            "Paramara"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The attractive doors of the temples of South India are called",
        "answer": "Gopuram",
        "choices": [
            "Gopuram",
            "Shikhara",
            "Devalaya",
            "Mandapam"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who established trade relations with Roman empire?",
        "answer": "Cheras",
        "choices": [
            "Cheras",
            "Kushanas",
            "Western Shakas",
            "Vakatakas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The Chola age was most famous for",
        "answer": "Village Assemblies",
        "choices": [
            "Village Assemblies",
            "Trade with Ceylon",
            "Advancement in Tamil Culture",
            "War with the Rashtrakutas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the founder of Chola Dynasty?",
        "answer": "Vijayalaya",
        "choices": [
            "Vijayalaya",
            "Karikal",
            "Aditya I",
            "Rajaraja I"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which of the following dynasties is not mentioned in Sangam literature?",
        "answer": "Kadamb",
        "choices": [
            "Kadamb",
            "Chola",
            "Chera",
            "Pandya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Why was uraiyur famous in Sangam Era?",
        "answer": "Important trade centre of cotton",
        "choices": [
            "Important trade centre of cotton",
            "Important trade centre of spices",
            "Important trade centre of domestic trade",
            "Important trade centre of foreign trade"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the writer of Mudrarakshasa?",
        "answer": "Vishakhadatta",
        "choices": [
            "Vishakhadatta",
            "Aswaghosha",
            "Kalidasa",
            "Bhasa"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Kumarsambhavam an epic poem was composed by",
        "answer": "Kalidasa",
        "choices": [
            "Kalidasa",
            "Banabhatta",
            "Harishena",
            "Chanda Bardai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "What is the name of Kalhana's book?",
        "answer": "Rajtarangini",
        "choices": [
            "Rajtarangini",
            "Arthashastra",
            "Indica",
            "Purana"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "The author of Swapanavasavadatta is",
        "answer": "Bhasa",
        "choices": [
            "Bhasa",
            "Kalidasa",
            "Bhavabhutti",
            "Rajashekhara"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who wrote the book Kiratarjuniya?",
        "answer": "Bharavi",
        "choices": [
            "Bharavi",
            "Bhatti",
            "Shudrak",
            "Kalidasa"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Epigraphic records (Inscriptions) suggest that in ancient India, the rulers of Bihar had contact with",
        "answer": "Java-Sumatra",
        "choices": [
            "Java-Sumatra",
            "Thailand",
            "Burma",
            "Cambodia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Which ruler of Bengal founded the ancient University called Vikramshila",
        "answer": "Dharampala",
        "choices": [
            "Dharampala",
            "Gopala",
            "Devpala",
            "Mahipala"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who was the author of the famous Allahabad Prasasti?",
        "answer": "Harisena",
        "choices": [
            "Harisena",
            "Kalidasa",
            "Ravikirti",
            "Shudraka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryAncient",
        "question": "Who is the author of Ashtanga Hridayam, a famous book for Ayurveda?",
        "answer": "Vagbhata",
        "choices": [
            "Vagbhata",
            "Banabhatta",
            "Charaka",
            "Dhanvantari"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Muhammad Ghori granted first Iqta in India to",
        "answer": "Qutbuddin Aibak",
        "choices": [
            "Qutbuddin Aibak",
            "Tajuddin Yalduz",
            "Shamsuddin Iltutmish",
            "Nazir-ud-din Qubacha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who was the first ruler of the Slave Dynasty?",
        "answer": "Qutbuddin Aibak",
        "choices": [
            "Qutbuddin Aibak",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Raziyya",
            "Balban"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which Sultan of Delhi Sultanate was known as Lakh Baksh?",
        "answer": "Qutbuddin Aibak",
        "choices": [
            "Qutbuddin Aibak",
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Raziyya",
            "Balban"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "The capital of Qutbuddin Aibak was",
        "answer": "Lahore",
        "choices": [
            "Lahore",
            "Ajmer",
            "Delhi",
            "Agra"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "The Qutub Minar was completed by",
        "answer": "Iltutmish",
        "choices": [
            "Iltutmish",
            "Qutbuddin Aibak",
            "Ulugh Khan",
            "Raziya Sultan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Iltutmish appointed his first subedar in Bihar to",
        "answer": "Malik Jani",
        "choices": [
            "Malik Jani",
            "Aivaj",
            "Nasiruddin Mahmud",
            "Alimardan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who was the first ruler to formulate the Theory of Kingship similar to the theory of divine right of the kings?",
        "answer": "Balban",
        "choices": [
            "Balban",
            "Aibak",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Alauddin"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which Sultan of Delhi introduced the practice of Sijda?",
        "answer": "Balban",
        "choices": [
            "Balban",
            "Qutbuddin Aibak",
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Muhammad Bin Tuqhlaq"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which Delhi Sultan is known for adopting the blood and iron policy?",
        "answer": "Balban",
        "choices": [
            "Balban",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Muhammad Bin Tuqhlaq"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who among the following introduced the Persian festival Nowruz in India?",
        "answer": "Balban",
        "choices": [
            "Balban",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Firuz Shah Tughlaq"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who was the first Muslim conqueror of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Bakhtiyar Khalji",
        "choices": [
            "Bakhtiyar Khalji",
            "Malik Ibrahim",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Alauddin Khalji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Tughril Khan raised a standard of revolt during whose reign?",
        "answer": "Balban",
        "choices": [
            "Balban",
            "Khizr Khan",
            "Firuz Shah Tughlaq",
            "Alauddin Khalji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who was deputed for the conquest of Dvarasamudra by Alauddin Khalji?",
        "answer": "Malik Kafur",
        "choices": [
            "Malik Kafur",
            "Khizr Khan",
            "Alp Khan",
            "Umar Khan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "When he attained Kingship, he was fully independent from rules and orders of Shariat. For which Sultan barani made this statement?",
        "answer": "Alauddin Khalji",
        "choices": [
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Balban",
            "Muhammad Bin Tuqhlaq"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who reduced the Khuts and Muqaddams to such an extent that their wives served in the house of Muslims?",
        "answer": "Alauddin Khalji",
        "choices": [
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Balban",
            "Muhammad Bin Tuqhlaq",
            "Firuz Shah Tughlaq"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who among army-commanders of Alauddin Khalji died fighting against Mongols?",
        "answer": "Zafar Khan",
        "choices": [
            "Zafar Khan",
            "Nusrat Khan",
            "Alp Khan",
            "Ulugh Khan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Padmini is associated with Alauddin conquest of Chittor. She was wife of",
        "answer": "Rana Ratan Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Rana Ratan Singh",
            "Ranjit Singh",
            "Maharana Pratap Singh",
            "Raja Man Singh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who was the ruler of Devagiri at the time of Alauddin Khalji's invasion?",
        "answer": "Ramachandra Dev",
        "choices": [
            "Ramachandra Dev",
            "Prataprudra Dev",
            "Malik Kafur",
            "Rana Ratan Singh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "During the regime of which Sultan was the Khalisa land developed on a large scale?",
        "answer": "Alauddin Khalji",
        "choices": [
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Ghiyasuddin Balban",
            "Muhammad Bin Tuqhlaq",
            "Firuz Shah Tughlaq"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who started Public Distribution System in Sultanate period?",
        "answer": "Alauddin Khalji",
        "choices": [
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Sikandar Lodhi",
            "Muhammad Bin Tuqhlaq",
            "Firuz Shah Tughlaq"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which one of the following Sultans provided employment to the unemployed?",
        "answer": "Firuz Shah Tughlaq",
        "choices": [
            "Firuz Shah Tughlaq",
            "Sher Shah Suri",
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Muhammad Bin Tuqhlaq"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which of the following Sultans had most numbers of slaves in his court?",
        "answer": "Firuz Shah Tughlaq",
        "choices": [
            "Firuz Shah Tughlaq",
            "Balban",
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Muhammad Bin Tuqhlaq"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which Delhi Sultan built the maximum number of canals?",
        "answer": "Firuz Shah Tughlaq",
        "choices": [
            "Firuz Shah Tughlaq",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Balban",
            "Sikandar Khan Lodi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which one of the following Sultans of Delhi introduced measures of improving the quality of fruits?",
        "answer": "Firuz Shah Tughlaq",
        "choices": [
            "Firuz Shah Tughlaq",
            "Muhammad Bin Tughlaq",
            "Sher Shah Suri",
            "Sikandar Khan Lodi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "What was Dar-ul-Shafa established by Firuz Shah Tughlaq?",
        "answer": "Charitable Hospital",
        "choices": [
            "Charitable Hospital",
            "Atmosphere",
            "Library",
            "Guest House for Pilgrims"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which Sultan of Delhi Sultanate established a charitable hospital named Dar-ul-Shifa?",
        "answer": "Firuz Shah Tughlaq",
        "choices": [
            "Firuz Shah Tughlaq",
            "Balban",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Muhammad Bin Tuqhlaq"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which one of the following dynasties ruled over India after the invasion of Timur?",
        "answer": "Sayyid Dynasty",
        "choices": [
            "Sayyid Dynasty",
            "Lodi Dynasty",
            "Tughlaq Dynasty",
            "Khalji Dynasty"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which of the following Sultans founded a town where now stands Agra?",
        "answer": "Sikandar Khan Lodi",
        "choices": [
            "Sikandar Khan Lodi",
            "Firuz Shah Tughlaq",
            "Muhammad Bin Tuqhlaq",
            "Bahlul Lodi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Identify the first ruler of Vijayanagara who captured Goa from Bahamani's?",
        "answer": "Harihara II",
        "choices": [
            "Harihara II",
            "Harihara I",
            "Bukka II",
            "Devaraya II"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who was the founder of Vijayanagara Empire?",
        "answer": "Harihara-Bukka",
        "choices": [
            "Harihara-Bukka",
            "Devaray",
            "Krishanadevaray",
            "Vir Narsimharay"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "With whom the king of Vijayanagara, Krishnadevaraya fought the battle of Golconda?",
        "answer": "Quli Qutb Shah",
        "choices": [
            "Quli Qutb Shah",
            "Qutbuddin Aibak",
            "Ismail Adil Khan",
            "Gajapati"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which among the following King's region Persian traveller Abdur Razzak came to India?",
        "answer": "Devaraya II",
        "choices": [
            "Devaraya II",
            "Devaraya I",
            "Krishanadevaraya I",
            "Krishnna Rai II"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which famous war took place in 1565 BCE?",
        "answer": "Talikota War",
        "choices": [
            "Talikota War",
            "Panipat I War",
            "Panipat II War",
            "Khanwa War"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "What was the chief characterstic of the finanacial system of Vijayanagara Empire?",
        "answer": "Land Revenue",
        "choices": [
            "Land Revenue",
            "Surplus rent",
            "Income from seaports",
            "Monetary System"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "The remains of Vijayanagara Empire are found in?",
        "answer": "Hampi",
        "choices": [
            "Hampi",
            "Bijapur",
            "Golconda",
            "Baroda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who among the following famous rulers founded a suburban township of Nagalapuram, near Vijayanagara, after his mother's name?",
        "answer": "Krishnadevaraya",
        "choices": [
            "Krishnadevaraya",
            "Harihara",
            "Bukka",
            "Gajapati"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "During the Delhi Sultanate, the designation Muqaddam or Chaudhari was used for",
        "answer": "Village Headman",
        "choices": [
            "Village Headman",
            "Revenue Officials",
            "Village Accountant",
            "Peasants"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Diwan-i-Arz department was associated with",
        "answer": "Defence",
        "choices": [
            "Defence",
            "Royal Correspondence",
            "Foreign",
            "Finanace"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Zawabits were concerned with",
        "answer": "State Laws",
        "choices": [
            "State Laws",
            "Laws relating to mansab system",
            "Laws regulating mint house",
            "Agricultural taxes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Coins-Tanka, Shashgani and Jital of Sultanate period was made of which of the following metals",
        "answer": "Silver, Copper",
        "choices": [
            "Silver, Copper",
            "Gold, Silver, Copper",
            "Silver, Zinc, Copper",
            "Gold, Zinc, Copper"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "The famous Buland Darwaza at Fatehpur Sikri forms which entrance to the Jama Masjid?",
        "answer": "Southern",
        "choices": [
            "Southern",
            "Northern",
            "Eastern",
            "Western"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who built the Buland Darwaza at Fathepur Sikri",
        "answer": "Akbar",
        "choices": [
            "Akbar",
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Qutubuddin Aibak",
            "Firuz Shah Tughlaq"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which Sultan built Alai Darwaza?",
        "answer": "Alauddin Khalji",
        "choices": [
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Akbar",
            "Qutubuddin Aibak",
            "Firuz Shah Tughlaq"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who was the author of Tabaqat-i-Nasiri?",
        "answer": "Minhaz-us-Siraj",
        "choices": [
            "Minhaz-us-Siraj",
            "Shaikh Jamaluddin",
            "Al-Biruni",
            "Ziyauddin Barani"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "The earliest description of Bakhtiyar Khalji's invasion of Bihar is in",
        "answer": "Tabaqat-i-Nasiri",
        "choices": [
            "Tabaqat-i-Nasiri",
            "Tarikh-i-Hind",
            "Tuj-ul-Maasir",
            "Tarikh-i-Mubarak Shahi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which Sultan demanded half of the crops on land after measurement as revenue?",
        "answer": "Alauddin Khalji",
        "choices": [
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Balban",
            "Muhammad Bin Tuqhlaq"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who among the following rulers divided his troops into units of two hundred, two hundred fifty and five hundred?",
        "answer": "Islam Shah",
        "choices": [
            "Islam Shah",
            "Sikandar Shah",
            "Bahlul Lodi",
            "Sher Shah Suri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which city of India was called Shiraj-i-Mashriq (East) in the medieval age?",
        "answer": "Jaunpur",
        "choices": [
            "Jaunpur",
            "Delhi",
            "Agra",
            "Lucknow"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who was the founder of Bahamani Kingdom?",
        "answer": "Alauddin Hasan Gangu",
        "choices": [
            "Alauddin Hasan Gangu",
            "Firuz Shah Tughlaq",
            "Asaf Khan",
            "Mahmud Gaonwa"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "A common feature of all Bhakti Saints was that they",
        "answer": "composed their verses in the language understood by their followers",
        "choices": [
            "composed their verses in the language understood by their followers",
            "rejected the authority of the priestly class",
            "encouraged women to go to the temples",
            "encouraged idol worship"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which of the following Sultans of Delhi was refused an audience by Nizamuddin Auliya?",
        "answer": "Alauddin Khalji",
        "choices": [
            "Alauddin Khalji",
            "Jalaluddin Khalji",
            "Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq",
            "Muhammad Bin Tuqhlaq"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "In which sufi order was sufi saint Sharfuddin Yahya Maneri associated",
        "answer": "Firdausi",
        "choices": [
            "Firdausi",
            "Chisti",
            "Suhrawardi",
            "Qadiri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Shaikh Bahauddin Zakaria belonged to which sect?",
        "answer": "Suhrawardi",
        "choices": [
            "Suhrawardi",
            "Chisti",
            "Firdausi",
            "Rishi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who composed Barahmasa?",
        "answer": "Malik Muhammad Jayasi",
        "choices": [
            "Malik Muhammad Jayasi",
            "Imami",
            "Amir Khusrau",
            "Raskhan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "The main reason for Babur's victory in the battle of Panipat was",
        "answer": "His skilled warfare",
        "choices": [
            "His skilled warfare",
            "His horse riding force",
            "Tulghuma system",
            "Internal disputes among Afghans"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "In which language was Tuzuk-i-Baburi written?",
        "answer": "Turkish",
        "choices": [
            "Turkish",
            "Persian",
            "Arabic",
            "Urdu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who wrote Humayun Nama?",
        "answer": "Gulbadan Begum",
        "choices": [
            "Gulbadan Begum",
            "Babur",
            "Humayun",
            "Jahangir"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Arrange properly as per dates of four important battles fought by Humayun",
        "answer": "Devara, Chausa, Kannuaj, Sirhind",
        "choices": [
            "Devara, Chausa, Kannuaj, Sirhind",
            "Chausa, Devara, Kannuaj, Sirhind",
            "Devara, Kannuaj, Chausa, Sirhind",
            "Sirhind, Devara, Chausa, Kannuaj"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which of the following rulers at first assumed the title of Hazrat-e-Ala and afterward Sultan?",
        "answer": "Sher Shah Suri",
        "choices": [
            "Sher Shah Suri",
            "Bahlul Lodi",
            "Sikandar Lodi",
            "Islam Shah Suri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Where is Sher Shah's tomb located?",
        "answer": "Sasaram",
        "choices": [
            "Sasaram",
            "Maner",
            "Sitamarhi",
            "Pavapuri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "When Humayun invaded the Chunar Fort for the first time?",
        "answer": 1532,
        "choices": [
            1532,
            1531,
            1536,
            1533
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who among the following made an offer to Humayun that he would surrender Bihar and pay an annual tribute of 10 lakh dinars if he was allowed to retain Bengal?",
        "answer": "Sher Khan",
        "choices": [
            "Sher Khan",
            "Bahadur Shah",
            "Bairam Khan",
            "Sher Shah Suri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who among the following has constructed mausoleum for his emperoro husband?",
        "answer": "Haji Begum",
        "choices": [
            "Haji Begum",
            "Shah Begum",
            "Mumtaz Mahal Begum",
            "Nurnissa Begum"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who was the commander of Rana Pratap's army in the battle of Haldighati?",
        "answer": "Hakim Khan Sur",
        "choices": [
            "Hakim Khan Sur",
            "Amar Singh",
            "Man Singh",
            "Shakti Singh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Yousuf Shah Chak, the last Muslim ruler of Kashmir valley, who was exiled to Bihar by the Mughal emperor Akbar, was buried in",
        "answer": "Nalanda",
        "choices": [
            "Nalanda",
            "Rajgir",
            "Pataliputra",
            "Munger"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who of the following Muslim rulers abolished the pilgrimage tax?",
        "answer": "Akbar",
        "choices": [
            "Akbar",
            "Bahlul Lodi",
            "Sher Shah Suri",
            "Humayun"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Zabti system was introduced by",
        "answer": "Akbar",
        "choices": [
            "Akbar",
            "Ghiyasuddin Tughlaq",
            "Sikandar Lodi",
            "Sher Shah Suri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who promulgated Din-e-Elahi?",
        "answer": "Akbar",
        "choices": [
            "Akbar",
            "Babur",
            "Shah Jahan",
            "Jahangir"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "European paintings were introduced in the court of",
        "answer": "Akbar",
        "choices": [
            "Akbar",
            "Jahangir",
            "Humayun",
            "Shah Jahan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Daswant and Basawan famour painters were courtier of Mughal emperor",
        "answer": "Akbar",
        "choices": [
            "Akbar",
            "Jahangir",
            "Aurangzeb",
            "Shah Jahan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who was the ruler of India when the English East India was formed?",
        "answer": "Akbar",
        "choices": [
            "Akbar",
            "Jahangir",
            "Aurangzeb",
            "Humayun"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Akbar merged Bengal and Bihar in his empire in",
        "answer": "1576 CE",
        "choices": [
            "1576 CE",
            "1590 CE",
            "1575 CE",
            "1572 CE"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Ain-e-Akbari was written by",
        "answer": "Abul Fazal",
        "choices": [
            "Abul Fazal",
            "Akbar",
            "Abdul Qadir",
            "Khwaja Nizamuddin Ahmad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Tabaqat-i-Akbari, which has been sometimes considered more reliable than Abul Fazl's Akbarnama, was written by",
        "answer": "Khwaja Nizamuddin Ahmad",
        "choices": [
            "Khwaja Nizamuddin Ahmad",
            "Gulbadan Begum",
            "Abdul Hamid Lahori",
            "Abul Fazal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who introduced Do-aspa and Sih-aspa system?",
        "answer": "Jahangir",
        "choices": [
            "Jahangir",
            "Akbar",
            "Shah Jahan",
            "Aurangzeb"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Whom of the following Englishmen did Jahangir respected with title English Khan?",
        "answer": "Hawkins",
        "choices": [
            "Hawkins",
            "Sir Thomas Roe",
            "Edward Terry",
            "Robert Clive"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Itmad-ud-Daula's tomb at Agra was built by",
        "answer": "Nur Jahan",
        "choices": [
            "Nur Jahan",
            "Akbar",
            "Jahangir",
            "Shah Jahan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "During the times of which Mughal Emperor did Sir Thomas Roe came to India?",
        "answer": "Jahangir",
        "choices": [
            "Jahangir",
            "Akbar",
            "Shah Jahan",
            "Babur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "What was the root of dispute between Shah of Iran and Mughal rulers?",
        "answer": "Qandhar",
        "choices": [
            "Qandhar",
            "Kabul",
            "Ghazni",
            "Kunduz"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who made the Red Fort in Delhi?",
        "answer": "Shah Jahan",
        "choices": [
            "Shah Jahan",
            "Akbar",
            "Nur Jahan",
            "Jahangir"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who was the first Mughal ruler who fought against the British?",
        "answer": "Aurangzeb",
        "choices": [
            "Aurangzeb",
            "Jahangir",
            "Akbar",
            "Shah Jahan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "The meaning of Jihad carried on by Aurangzeb is",
        "answer": "Holy War",
        "choices": [
            "Holy War",
            "Dar-ul-Harb",
            "Dar-ul-Islam",
            "Jizya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who wrote Alamgir-Nama?",
        "answer": "Mirza Muhammad Kazim",
        "choices": [
            "Mirza Muhammad Kazim",
            "Muhammad Saqi Mustaid Khan",
            "Aqil Khan Razi",
            "Ishwar Das"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "In the Mughal administration Muhtasib was",
        "answer": "An Officer-in-charge of public morals",
        "choices": [
            "An Officer-in-charge of public morals",
            "Officer of correspondence Department",
            "Head of Foreign Affairs",
            "Military Officer"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "In Medieval India, why was the mansabdari system introduced?",
        "answer": "Ensuring clean administration",
        "choices": [
            "Ensuring clean administration",
            "For revenue collection",
            "Facilitating recruitment to the army",
            "To establish religious harmony"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Madad-i-Maash indicates in Mughal administration",
        "answer": "Revenue-free land grant for charitable reasons",
        "choices": [
            "Revenue-free land grant for charitable reasons",
            "Toll Tax",
            "Pension provided to military officials",
            "Cultivation Tax"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "The meaning of word Bantai during Medieval period was?",
        "answer": "System of revenue collection",
        "choices": [
            "System of revenue collection",
            "Religious Tax",
            "Wealth Tax",
            "Property Tax"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Mughal paintings reached its zenith under",
        "answer": "Jahangir",
        "choices": [
            "Jahangir",
            "Humayun",
            "Shah Jahan",
            "Akbar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which Mughal ruler established Karkhanas for painting?",
        "answer": "Akbar",
        "choices": [
            "Akbar",
            "Jahangir",
            "Shah Jahan",
            "Humayun"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which among the following ports was called Babul Makka during the Mughal period?",
        "answer": "Surat",
        "choices": [
            "Surat",
            "Calicut",
            "Cambay",
            "Broach"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which Sultan was reputed to be Akbar of Kashmir",
        "answer": "Sultan Zainul Abidin",
        "choices": [
            "Sultan Zainul Abidin",
            "Sultan Shamsuddin Shah",
            "Sultan Qutbuddin",
            "Sultan Sikandar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who stated the five thousand to twenty thousand men worked for forty years to build the palace of forty pillars at Allhabad in Akbar's time?",
        "answer": "William Finch",
        "choices": [
            "William Finch",
            "Manucci",
            "Tavernier",
            "Abdul Hamid Lahori"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Where was the capital of Shivaji?",
        "answer": "Raigarh",
        "choices": [
            "Raigarh",
            "Sindugarh",
            "Poona",
            "Kolhapur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Ashta Pradhan was established by which ruler?",
        "answer": "Shivaji",
        "choices": [
            "Shivaji",
            "Akbar",
            "Babur",
            "Aurangzeb"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Ashta Pradhan was a council of ministers in whose administration",
        "answer": "Maratha",
        "choices": [
            "Maratha",
            "Gupta",
            "Chola",
            "Vijayanagara"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Saranzami system was related to",
        "answer": "land revenue system of Maratha",
        "choices": [
            "land revenue system of Maratha",
            "Taluqdari system",
            "Qutb Shahi administration",
            "Religious Tax"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who was the last Mughal Emperor to sit on Mayur Singhasan?",
        "answer": "Muhammad Shah",
        "choices": [
            "Muhammad Shah",
            "Shah Alam I",
            "Bahadur Shah",
            "Jahandar Shah"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Which of the following Mughal emperors was not allowed to enter into Delhi by Wazir Ghaziuddin?",
        "answer": "Shah Alam II",
        "choices": [
            "Shah Alam II",
            "Alamgir II",
            "Akbar II",
            "Bahadur Shah II"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who established Lodi Dyansty",
        "answer": "Bahlul Khan Lodi",
        "choices": [
            "Bahlul Khan Lodi",
            "Sikandr Khan Lodi",
            "Malik Sultan Khan Lodi",
            "Ibrahim Lodi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "First Sikh Guru",
        "answer": "Guru Nanak",
        "choices": [
            "Guru Nanak",
            "Guru Angad",
            "Guru Gobind Singh",
            "Guru Hargobind"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Last ruling dynasty of Delhi Sultanate",
        "answer": "Lodi",
        "choices": [
            "Lodi",
            "Mameluk",
            "Tughlaq",
            "Khalji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "First ruling dynasty of Delhi Sultanate",
        "answer": "Mameluk",
        "choices": [
            "Mameluk",
            "Lodi",
            "Tughlaq",
            "Khalji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Name the ruler who led to the fall of Constantinople",
        "answer": "Mehmed II",
        "choices": [
            "Mehmed II",
            "Ibrahim II",
            "Murad II",
            "Bayezid II"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who established the Mughal Empire",
        "answer": "Babur",
        "choices": [
            "Babur",
            "Akbar",
            "Jahangir",
            "Shah Jahan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who restored the Grand Trunk Road from the river Indus in the west to Sonargaon in Bengal",
        "answer": "Sher Shah Suri",
        "choices": [
            "Sher Shah Suri",
            "Humayun",
            "Shah Jahan",
            "Akbar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Thomas Roe, the royal envoy of the king of England visited court of which ruler in India",
        "answer": "Jahangir",
        "choices": [
            "Jahangir",
            "Akbar",
            "Humayun",
            "Aurangzeb"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who constructed the Taj Mahal",
        "answer": "Shah Jahan",
        "choices": [
            "Shah Jahan",
            "Akbar",
            "Humayun",
            "Aurangzeb"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who executed Guru Tegh Bahadur",
        "answer": "Aurangzeb",
        "choices": [
            "Aurangzeb",
            "Akbar",
            "Humayun",
            "Shah Jahan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Sikh Guru born in Bihar",
        "answer": "Guru Gobind Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Guru Gobind Singh",
            "Guru Tegh Bahadu",
            "Guru Nanak",
            "Guru Angad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who established the Maratha Kingdom",
        "answer": "Shivaji",
        "choices": [
            "Shivaji",
            "Shambhaji",
            "Nana Pahadi",
            "Tanhaji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "The Khalsa, warrior group of Sikh was established by",
        "answer": "Guru Gobind Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Guru Gobind Singh",
            "Guru Nanak",
            "Guru Tegh Bahadur",
            "Guru Angad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Who established the Sikh Empire",
        "answer": "Ranjit Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Ranjit Singh",
            "Guru Gobind",
            "Guru Nanak",
            "Prithviraj Chouhan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "HistoryMedieval",
        "question": "Futuhat-i-Alamgiri was written by",
        "answer": "Ishwardas Nagar",
        "choices": [
            "Ishwardas Nagar",
            "Bhimsen",
            "Haridas",
            "Todarmal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "India's territorial limit extends towards the sea up to how many nautical miles from the coast?",
        "answer": "12 nautical miles",
        "choices": [
            "12 nautical miles",
            "200 nautical miles",
            "24 nautical miles",
            "100 nautical miles"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "India's Exclusive Economic Zone extends towards the sea up to how many nautical miles from the coast?",
        "answer": "200 nautical miles",
        "choices": [
            "200 nautical miles",
            "12 nautical miles",
            "24 nautical miles",
            "100 nautical miles"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "How many latitudes are there on the globe drawn at 1 degree interval?",
        "answer": 179,
        "choices": [
            179,
            180,
            360,
            359
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "How much is the difference between Indian Standard Time (IST) and Greenwich Mean Time (GMT)?",
        "answer": "plus 5 hour 30 minutes",
        "choices": [
            "plus 5 hour 30 minutes",
            "minus 5 hour 30 minutes",
            "minus 4 hour 30 minutes",
            "plus 4 hour 30 minutes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "On which plateau, the Tropic of Cancer and the Indian Standard Time intersect each other?",
        "answer": "Baghelkhand",
        "choices": [
            "Baghelkhand",
            "Bundelkhand",
            "Kaimur",
            "Chhota-Nagpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "On which longitude does Indian Standard Time coicide?",
        "answer": "82deg 30min E",
        "choices": [
            "82deg 30min E",
            "85deg 30min W",
            "88deg 30min E",
            "80deg 30min W"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Difference of one degree longitude will correspond to how much time",
        "answer": "4 minutes",
        "choices": [
            "4 minutes",
            "6 minutes",
            "60 minutes",
            "30 minutes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "What is the local time of Thimphu (Bhutan) located at 90deg E longitude when the time at Greenwich (0deg) is 12:00 noon?",
        "answer": "6:00 pm",
        "choices": [
            "6:00 pm",
            "4:00 pm",
            "5:00 pm",
            "6:00 am"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The foothills region of Himalayas is",
        "answer": "Shiwalik",
        "choices": [
            "Shiwalik",
            "Great Himalayas",
            "Trans-Himalayas",
            "Lesser Himalayas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which of the following areas is not landslide-prone area?",
        "answer": "Eastern Ghats",
        "choices": [
            "Eastern Ghats",
            "Western Ghats",
            "Himalayan Region",
            "North-Eastern Region"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The highest peak in the Eastern Ghats of India is",
        "answer": "Arma Konda (Jhindhagada)",
        "choices": [
            "Arma Konda (Jhindhagada)",
            "Mahendragiri",
            "Anai Mudi",
            "Kanchenjunga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The highest peak in the Western Ghats of India is",
        "answer": "Anai Mudi",
        "choices": [
            "Anai Mudi",
            "Mahendragiri",
            "Arma Konda (Jhindhagada)",
            "Kanchenjunga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The highest mountain peak in India?",
        "answer": "K2 (Godwin-Austen)",
        "choices": [
            "K2 (Godwin-Austen)",
            "Everest",
            "Nanda Devi",
            "Kanchenjunga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The Kailash Range is part of which larger mountain system?",
        "answer": "Trans-Himalaya",
        "choices": [
            "Trans-Himalaya",
            "Great Himalayas",
            "Shiwalik",
            "Lesser Himalayas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Mount Everest lies in which mountain range?",
        "answer": "Great Himalayas",
        "choices": [
            "Great Himalayas",
            "Trans-Himalaya",
            "Shiwalik",
            "Lesser Himalayas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which is the highest mountain peak entirely within India (not on the border)?",
        "answer": "Nanda Devi",
        "choices": [
            "Nanda Devi",
            "Kanchenjunga",
            "Trishul",
            "Kamet"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Shiwalik series was formed in",
        "answer": "Cenozoic",
        "choices": [
            "Cenozoic",
            "Proterozoic",
            "Mesozoic",
            "Palaeozoic"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Someshwar range is a part of which of the following mountain ranges?",
        "answer": "Shiwalik",
        "choices": [
            "Shiwalik",
            "Satpura",
            "Vindhayan",
            "Eastern Ghats"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Atal Tunnel is across which one of the following Himalayan ranges?",
        "answer": "Eastern Pir Panjal",
        "choices": [
            "Eastern Pir Panjal",
            "Western Pir Panjal",
            "Zanskar",
            "Ladakh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "At which of the following hills the Eastern Ghats join the Western Ghats?",
        "answer": "Nilgiri Hills",
        "choices": [
            "Nilgiri Hills",
            "Palni Hills",
            "Anaimudi Hills",
            "Shevaroy Hills"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Western Ghats in Maharashtra and Karnataka is known as",
        "answer": "Sahyadri",
        "choices": [
            "Sahyadri",
            "Nilgiri",
            "Shiwalik",
            "Nandi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The Hills situated closer to Kanyakumari are",
        "answer": "Cardamom Hills",
        "choices": [
            "Cardamom Hills",
            "Nilgiri Hills",
            "Anaialai Hills",
            "Shevaroy Hills"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which of the following is not a part of the Meghalaya Plateau?",
        "answer": "Bhuban Hills",
        "choices": [
            "Bhuban Hills",
            "Garo Hills",
            "Khasi Hills",
            "Jaintia Hills"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Extra peninsular mountains of India were formed during",
        "answer": "Cenozoic Era",
        "choices": [
            "Cenozoic Era",
            "Palaeozoic Era",
            "Aozoic Era",
            "Mesozoic Era"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Chhota-Nagpur Plateau is a",
        "answer": "front sloping",
        "choices": [
            "front sloping",
            "pitfall",
            "foothill",
            "plain subland"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which one of the following districts does not have Dharwar geological formations?",
        "answer": "Rohtas",
        "choices": [
            "Rohtas",
            "Jamui",
            "Munger",
            "Nawada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "How many coastal states are there in India?",
        "answer": "Nine",
        "choices": [
            "Nine",
            "Eight",
            "Thirteen",
            "Eleven"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Island group Lakshadweep is",
        "answer": "Accumulation of Coral Reef",
        "choices": [
            "Accumulation of Coral Reef",
            "Accumulation of Volcanic substances",
            "Sedimentated Soil",
            "None of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Lakshadweep consists of how many islands?",
        "answer": 36,
        "choices": [
            36,
            16,
            17,
            26
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The Ramsar Convention is associated with the conservation of",
        "answer": "Wetlands",
        "choices": [
            "Wetlands",
            "Drylands",
            "Forests",
            "Hills"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which gas contributes to global warming through its greenhouse effect?",
        "answer": "All of these",
        "choices": [
            "All of these",
            "Methane",
            "Nitrous Oxide",
            "Carbon Dioxide"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which of the following gas is responsible for the depletion of Ozone layer?",
        "answer": "Chlorofluorocarbons",
        "choices": [
            "Chlorofluorocarbons",
            "Carbon Monoxide",
            "Carbon Dioxide",
            "Nitrous Oxide"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "What is the percentage of forest and tree cover in the total geographical area of India according to Indian State of Forest Report 2023?",
        "answer": "25.17 percent",
        "choices": [
            "25.17 percent",
            "21.76 percent",
            "3.41 percent",
            "91.33 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "What is the percentage of forest cover in the total geographical area of India according to Indian State of Forest Report 2023?",
        "answer": "21.76 percent",
        "choices": [
            "21.76 percent",
            "25.17 percent",
            "3.41 percent",
            "91.33 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The largest percentage of forest area is in",
        "answer": "Lakshadweep",
        "choices": [
            "Lakshadweep",
            "Mizoram",
            "Andman & Nicobar",
            "Madhya Pradesh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "State having largest forest cover in India",
        "answer": "Madhya Pradesh",
        "choices": [
            "Madhya Pradesh",
            "Arunanchal Pradesh",
            "Chhattisgarh",
            "Sikkim"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "In National Park protection is given to",
        "answer": "Whole Ecosystem",
        "choices": [
            "Whole Ecosystem",
            "Only Fauna",
            "Only Flora",
            "Only Birds"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which of the following areas in India does not grow tropical wet evergreen forests?",
        "answer": "Eastern Ghats",
        "choices": [
            "Eastern Ghats",
            "Western Ghats",
            "Andaman Islands",
            "North-Eastern Region"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "In which forest do the majority of species of birds inhabit the mountainous areas?",
        "answer": "Pine Forest",
        "choices": [
            "Pine Forest",
            "Bush Forest",
            "Oak Forest",
            "Maple Forest"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "India's first Dolphin Observatory is being built in",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Kolkata",
            "Odisha",
            "Delhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "The state of India with maximum number of wildlife sanctuaries is",
        "answer": "Maharashtra",
        "choices": [
            "Maharashtra",
            "Karnataka",
            "Madhya Pradesh",
            "Tamil Nadu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which one of the following is the well-publicised wildife campaign in the world launched in 1973?",
        "answer": "Project Tiger",
        "choices": [
            "Project Tiger",
            "Sunderbans Project",
            "Project Big Cat",
            "Project Elephant"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Which one of the following is not included under in-situ conservation?",
        "answer": "Botanical Garden",
        "choices": [
            "Botanical Garden",
            "National Parks",
            "Wildlife Sanctuaries",
            "Biosphere Reserves"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Geography",
        "question": "Total Ramsar sites in India?",
        "answer": 91,
        "choices": [
            91,
            90,
            19,
            45
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The first session of Constituent Assembly was held on",
        "answer": "9th December 1946",
        "choices": [
            "9th December 1946",
            "15th August 1947",
            "26th November 1949",
            "26th January 1946"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Indian Constitution was adopted by the Constituent Assembly on",
        "answer": "26th Novemeber 1949",
        "choices": [
            "26th Novemeber 1949",
            "26th Novemeber 1950",
            "26th January 1950",
            "15th August 1949"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "January 26 was selected as the date for the inaugaration of the Constitution, because",
        "answer": "The Congress had observed it as the Independence Day in 1930",
        "choices": [
            "The Congress had observed it as the Independence Day in 1930",
            "It was considered to be an auspicious day",
            "On that day the Quit India Movement was started in 1942",
            "MK Gandhi returned to India on that day"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who of the following was the chairman of the Provincial Constitution Committee of the Constituent Assembly of India",
        "answer": "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
        "choices": [
            "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Bhim Rao Ambedkar",
            "K. M. Munshi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who was the labour Minister in Jawaharlal Nehru's Provisional Government?",
        "answer": "Jagjivan Ram",
        "choices": [
            "Jagjivan Ram",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Aruna Asaf Ali",
            "C. Rajgopalachari"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Indian Constitution was adopted by",
        "answer": "Constituent Assembly",
        "choices": [
            "Constituent Assembly",
            "British Parliament",
            "Governor-General",
            "Indian Parliament"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Constitution Day of India is celebrated on",
        "answer": "26th Novemeber",
        "choices": [
            "26th Novemeber",
            "26th January",
            "15th August",
            "14th August"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who was the President of Indian National Congress at the time of partition of India?",
        "answer": "J. B. Kripalani",
        "choices": [
            "J. B. Kripalani",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Maulana Abul Kalam Azad",
            "C. Rajgopalachari"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "In Indian political system which one is supereme?",
        "answer": "The Constitution",
        "choices": [
            "The Constitution",
            "The Supreme Court",
            "The President",
            "The Parliament"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following subject lies in the concurrent list?",
        "answer": "Education",
        "choices": [
            "Education",
            "Police",
            "Defence",
            "Agriculture"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Constitution Tenth schedule relates to",
        "answer": "Anti-Defection Law",
        "choices": [
            "Anti-Defection Law",
            "National Language of India",
            "Administration of SC and ST Area",
            "Judicial Review"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Land Reform comes under the subjects of",
        "answer": "State List",
        "choices": [
            "State List",
            "Union List",
            "Concurrent List",
            "National List"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is not a part in the Eleventh Schedule of the Constitution?",
        "answer": "Rural Sports",
        "choices": [
            "Rural Sports",
            "Libraries",
            "Fuel and Fodder",
            "Technical Training"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What was the duration in the making of the Indian Constitution?",
        "answer": "2 years 11 monts and 18 days",
        "choices": [
            "2 years 11 monts and 18 days",
            "1 years 11 monts and 18 days",
            "3 years 11 monts and 18 days",
            "2 years 10 monts and 18 days"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The provision of amending the constitutional provision is given in",
        "answer": "Part XX Article 368",
        "choices": [
            "Part XX Article 368",
            "Part XIX Article 356",
            "Part XX Article 356",
            "Part XXI Article 368"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which one of the following characterstics is not true for unitary form of Government?",
        "answer": "Ideal for large countries",
        "choices": [
            "Ideal for large countries",
            "Flexible",
            "Swift Decision",
            "Uniformity of Laws"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Democracy of India is based on the fact that",
        "answer": "Public enjoys the right to choose and change the Government",
        "choices": [
            "Public enjoys the right to choose and change the Government",
            "Fundamental Rights have been provided",
            "The Constitution is written",
            "Directive Principles of State policy have been provided for here"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which one of the following statements is correct regarding parliamentary form of government?",
        "answer": "Executive is responsible to the legislature",
        "choices": [
            "Executive is responsible to the legislature",
            "The legislature is responsible to Executive",
            "The Legislative and the Executive are independent",
            "The Legislature is responsible to Judiciary"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the nature of the Indian Constitution",
        "answer": "Federal in nature but unitary in spirit",
        "choices": [
            "Federal in nature but unitary in spirit",
            "Federal",
            "Unitary",
            "Parliamentary"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "After Independence, in which year were the Indian states reorganised on the linguistic basis?",
        "answer": 1956,
        "choices": [
            1956,
            2000,
            1947,
            1950
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Chief Minister of Union Territory, where such a setup exists, is appointed by the",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Governor",
            "Lieutenant Governor",
            "Chief Justice of India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Creation of a new state requires which majority for Consitutional Amendment.",
        "answer": "Simple",
        "choices": [
            "Simple",
            "Two-third",
            "Three-fourth",
            "Two-third plus ratification by half of all states"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Delhi is a/an",
        "answer": "Union Territory",
        "choices": [
            "Union Territory",
            "State",
            "Autonomous Council",
            "Dominion"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Sikkim became an associate state of India under",
        "answer": "35th Amendment",
        "choices": [
            "35th Amendment",
            "45th Amendment",
            "42nd Amendment",
            "36th Amendment"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "On which day Sikkim gained full statehood in India",
        "answer": "16th May 1975",
        "choices": [
            "16th May 1975",
            "15th May 1975",
            "16th June 1975",
            "15th July 1975"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "In which year did the state of Jharkhand come into existence?",
        "answer": 2000,
        "choices": [
            2000,
            1975,
            1956,
            1987
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Bihar as an Indian State was formed in ",
        "answer": 1912,
        "choices": [
            1912,
            1956,
            1987,
            1911
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The phrase equality before law used in Article 14 of the Indian Constitution has been borrowed from the Constitution of",
        "answer": "Britain",
        "choices": [
            "Britain",
            "USA",
            "France",
            "Canada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The phrase equality protection of law used in Article 14 of the Indian Constitution has been borrowed from the Constitution of",
        "answer": "USA",
        "choices": [
            "USA",
            "Britain",
            "France",
            "Canada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "From which country, the Indian Constitution has taken reference for the idea of the Fundamental Rights?",
        "answer": "United States of America",
        "choices": [
            "United States of America",
            "Ireland",
            "United Kingdom",
            "Canada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is given the power to enforce the Fundamental Rights by the Constitution?",
        "answer": "The Supreme Court and High Courts",
        "choices": [
            "The Supreme Court and High Courts",
            "All Courts in India",
            "The Parliament",
            "The President"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is meant by Rule of Law",
        "answer": "One act for all and one judiciary for all",
        "choices": [
            "One act for all and one judiciary for all",
            "One act for all and one state for all",
            "One state for all and one judicary for all",
            "All acts for one and one judiciary for all"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The description of Fundamental Rights for the Indian cititzens is in",
        "answer": "Article 12 to 35",
        "choices": [
            "Article 12 to 35",
            "Article 25 to 50",
            "Article 16 to 40",
            "Article 15 to 39"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Supreme Court's judgement of Indra Sawhney vs Union of India Case is related to which issue?",
        "answer": "Regarding OBC reservation in Government Employment",
        "choices": [
            "Regarding OBC reservation in Government Employment",
            "Doctrine of Basic Structure of Constitution",
            "Reservation on promotion of SC",
            "Extended reservation for ST"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which article of the Constitution of India is related with the Freedom of Press.",
        "answer": "Article 19",
        "choices": [
            "Article 19",
            "Article 20",
            "Article 21",
            "Article 22"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following can a court issue for enforcement of the Fundamental Rights?",
        "answer": "Writ",
        "choices": [
            "Writ",
            "Decree",
            "Ordinance",
            "Bill"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following is not a fundamental right?",
        "answer": "Right to Property",
        "choices": [
            "Right to Property",
            "Right to Constitutional Remedy",
            "Right to Peaceful Assembly",
            "Right to free movement all over the country"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Supreme Court has held that hoisting the National Flag atop the private buildings is a fundamental right of every citizen under",
        "answer": "Article 19",
        "choices": [
            "Article 19",
            "Article 14",
            "Article 21",
            "Article 25"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following rights conferred by the Constitution of India is also available to non-citizens?",
        "answer": "Right to Constitutional Remedies",
        "choices": [
            "Right to Constitutional Remedies",
            "Freedom of Speech",
            "Freedom to move and settle in any part of the country",
            "Freedom to accquire property"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "When was the Right to Education added through the amendment in the Constitution of India?",
        "answer": "1st April 2010",
        "choices": [
            "1st April 2010",
            "1st August 2010",
            "2nd October 2010",
            "1st December 2010"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Untouchability is abolished by which article of the Indian Constitution?",
        "answer": "Article 17",
        "choices": [
            "Article 17",
            "Article 19",
            "Article 15",
            "Article 14"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which part of the Indian Constitution contains the Directive Principles of State Policy?",
        "answer": "Part IV",
        "choices": [
            "Part IV",
            "Part III",
            "Part V",
            "Part VI"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "How are Directive Principles of State Policy different from Fundamental Rights?",
        "answer": "DPSPs are not enforceable while Fundamental Rights are enforceable",
        "choices": [
            "DPSPs are not enforceable while Fundamental Rights are enforceable",
            "DPSPs are enforceable by courts, while Fundamental Rights are not.",
            "DPSPs are not part of Constitution while Fundamental Rights are",
            "DPSPs are part of Constitution while Fundamental Rights are not"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The concept of welfare state included in the Constitution of India in the",
        "answer": "Directive Principles of State Policy",
        "choices": [
            "Directive Principles of State Policy",
            "Fourth Schedule of the Constitution",
            "Fundamental Rights",
            "Preamble of Constitution"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Panchayat Raj System in India is laid down under",
        "answer": "Directive Principles of State Policy",
        "choices": [
            "Directive Principles of State Policy",
            "Fundamental Rights",
            "Fundamental Duties",
            "Election Commission Act"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Ministry of Panchayati Raj was created in the Central Government of India in",
        "answer": 2004,
        "choices": [
            2004,
            2001,
            2000,
            2003
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which one of the following Articles directs the State to organise the Panchayats?",
        "answer": "Article 40",
        "choices": [
            "Article 40",
            "Aritcle 50",
            "Article 33",
            "Article 36"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The concept of Directive Principles of State Policy in the Indian Constitution was borrowed from the Constitution of",
        "answer": "Ireland",
        "choices": [
            "Ireland",
            "Switzerland",
            "England",
            "United States of America"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Fundamental Duties are laid down in",
        "answer": "42nd Amendment",
        "choices": [
            "42nd Amendment",
            "43rd Amendment",
            "40th Amendment",
            "39th Amendment"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The 10 commandments, which were added in 42nd Amendment Act in Constitution of India, are called as ",
        "answer": "Fundamental Duties",
        "choices": [
            "Fundamental Duties",
            "Fundamental Rights",
            "Panchayati Raj Principles",
            "Directive Principles of State Policy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which one of the following is a Fundamental Duty in India?",
        "answer": "To value and preserve the rich heritage of our composite culture",
        "choices": [
            "To value and preserve the rich heritage of our composite culture",
            "Separation of judiciary from executive",
            "Free and compulsory education",
            "Abolition of Untouchability"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Electoral College for the election of the President of India consits of",
        "answer": "All elected members of both members of Parliament and elected members of the State Legislative Assemblies",
        "choices": [
            "All elected members of both members of Parliament and elected members of the State Legislative Assemblies",
            "All the elected members of the Rajya Sabha",
            "All the elected members of the Lok Sabha",
            "All the members of the State Legislative Assemblies"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "If there is any dispute regarding the Presidential election, it can be referred to",
        "answer": "Supreme Court of India",
        "choices": [
            "Supreme Court of India",
            "Attorney General of India",
            "Parliament",
            "Special Tribunal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The president of India can be removed from his post by",
        "answer": "Parliament",
        "choices": [
            "Parliament",
            "Chief Justice of India",
            "The Prime Minister of India",
            "Lok Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "If the position of President and Vice-President are vacant, who officiates as the President of India?",
        "answer": "Chief Justice of India",
        "choices": [
            "Chief Justice of India",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Speaker of Lok Sabha",
            "Chairman of Rajya Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Indian President is eligible for re-election for how many times?",
        "answer": "Any number of times",
        "choices": [
            "Any number of times",
            "Once",
            "Twice",
            "Thrice"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who is the Executive Head of State in India?",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Leader of the Opposition",
            "Chief Secretary, Government of India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who of the following has been vested with the executive powers  of the central government under the constitution of India?",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Central Cabinet",
            "All of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "President of India exercises his powers",
        "answer": "either directly or through officers subordinate to him",
        "choices": [
            "either directly or through officers subordinate to him",
            "through ministers",
            "through Prime Minister",
            "through Cabinet"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The President",
        "answer": "is a part of Parliament",
        "choices": [
            "is a part of Parliament",
            "is not a part of parliament",
            "is a part of parliament and sits in the parliament",
            "can vote in parliament"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Constitution doesn't empower the President of India with the right of",
        "answer": "Appointment of Chief Minister in states",
        "choices": [
            "Appointment of Chief Minister in states",
            "Appointment of Prime Minister",
            "Being the supreme commander of Defence Forces",
            "Executing emergency in any part of the country"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The first President of Independent India - Rajendra Prasad belonged to which state",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Andhra Pradesh",
            "Tamil Nadu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who was among the following to receive first Bharat Ratna?",
        "answer": "Sarvapalli Radhakrishnan",
        "choices": [
            "Sarvapalli Radhakrishnan",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Lal Bahadur Shastri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "A bill presented in Parliament becomes an Act after",
        "answer": "the President has given his assent",
        "choices": [
            "the President has given his assent",
            "It is passed by both the houses of Parliament",
            "the Prime Minister has signed it",
            "the Supreme Court has declared it to be within the competence of the Union-Parliament"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who among the following had been the first unopposed and unanimously elected President of India?",
        "answer": "Neelam Sanjeeva Reddy",
        "choices": [
            "Neelam Sanjeeva Reddy",
            "Savapalli Radhakrishnan",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Zakir Hussain"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the minimum age to be eligible for contesting election of President in India?",
        "answer": "35 years",
        "choices": [
            "35 years",
            "25 years",
            "32 years",
            "21 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the minimum age to be eligible for contesting election of Vice-President in India?",
        "answer": "35 years",
        "choices": [
            "35 years",
            "25 years",
            "32 years",
            "21 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "To whom does the President of India address his resignation letter?",
        "answer": "Vice-President",
        "choices": [
            "Vice-President",
            "Chief Justice",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Speaker of Lok Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "To whom does the Vice-President of India address his resignation letter?",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Chief Justice",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Speaker of Rajya Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who is the ex-officio Chairman of the Rajya Sabha?",
        "answer": "Vice-President",
        "choices": [
            "Vice-President",
            "President",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Chief Justice of India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Electoral College for the 17th Vice Presidential Election of India for 2025 consists of how many members?",
        "answer": "788 members",
        "choices": [
            "788 members",
            "543 members",
            "245 members",
            "565 members"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The serial number of next Vice-President of India will be",
        "answer": "17th",
        "choices": [
            "17th",
            "16th",
            "15th",
            "18th"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Council of Ministers is responsible to the",
        "answer": "Lok Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "Lok Sabha",
            "President",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Rajya Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Council of Ministers shall hold office during the pleasure of the",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Speaker of Lok Sabha",
            "Chief Justice of India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Prime Minister of India is responsible to the",
        "answer": "Lok Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "Lok Sabha",
            "President",
            "Prime Minister",
            "Rajya Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who administers the oaths of office and secrecy to Prime Minister?",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Chief Justice of India",
            "Speaker of Lok Sabha",
            "Vice-President"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who administers the oaths of office and secrecy to Vice-President?",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Chief Justice of India",
            "Speaker of Rajya Sabha",
            "Prime Minister"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who administers the oaths of office and secrecy to the President?",
        "answer": "Chief Justice of India",
        "choices": [
            "Chief Justice of India",
            "Vice-President",
            "Speaker of Rajya Sabha",
            "Prime Minister"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The word Matrimandal (Cabinet) is mentioned is which article?",
        "answer": "Article 352",
        "choices": [
            "Article 352",
            "Article 356",
            "Article 75",
            "Article 74"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who is the highest Civil Services Officers of the Central Government?",
        "answer": "Cabinet Secretary",
        "choices": [
            "Cabinet Secretary",
            "Attorney General of India",
            "Home Secretary",
            "Finance Secretary"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which of the following Constitutional Amendment Act resitricted the size of the Council of Ministers to 15 percent of the total members of the Lok Sabha?",
        "answer": "91st Amendment, 2003",
        "choices": [
            "91st Amendment, 2003",
            "95th Amendment, 2009",
            "93rd Amendment, 2005",
            "90th Amendment, 2002"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who advises the Government of India on legal matters?",
        "answer": "Attorney General",
        "choices": [
            "Attorney General",
            "Comptroller & Auditor General",
            "Chief Justice of the Supreme Court",
            "Chairman, Law Commission"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which officer of the Government of India has the right to take part in the proceedings of Parliament of India even though he is not a member?",
        "answer": "Attorney General",
        "choices": [
            "Attorney General",
            "Comptroller & Auditor General",
            "Vice-President",
            "Election Commissioner"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who advises the State Government on legal matters?",
        "answer": "Advocate-General",
        "choices": [
            "Advocate-General",
            "Attorney General",
            "Solicitor General",
            "Chief Justice of the High Court"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Parliament's expenditure is controlled by the ",
        "answer": "Comptroller & Auditor General",
        "choices": [
            "Comptroller & Auditor General",
            "President",
            "NITI Aayog",
            "Finance Commission"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Lok Sabha can be dissolved before the completion of its term",
        "answer": "by the president on the recommendation of the Prime Minister",
        "choices": [
            "by the president on the recommendation of the Prime Minister",
            "at the discretion of the President",
            "at the discretion of the Prime Minister",
            "at the discretion of the speaker of Lok Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the minimum age laid down for a person to seek election to the Lok Sabha?",
        "answer": "25 years",
        "choices": [
            "25 years",
            "30 years",
            "35 years",
            "20 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the minimum age laid down for a member of the Parliament?",
        "answer": "25 years",
        "choices": [
            "25 years",
            "30 years",
            "35 years",
            "20 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the minimum age laid down for a member of the Rajya Sabha?",
        "answer": "30 years",
        "choices": [
            "30 years",
            "25 years",
            "35 years",
            "20 years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Generally how many sessions are there in the Lok Sabha?",
        "answer": "Three",
        "choices": [
            "Three",
            "Two",
            "Four",
            "Five"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "A candidate of Lok Sabha poll loses his security amount if he/she does not get",
        "answer": "one-sixth of valid votes",
        "choices": [
            "one-sixth of valid votes",
            "one-third of valid votes",
            "one-fourth of valid votes",
            "one-fifth of valid votes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The state-wise allocation of seats in Lok Sabha is based on the 1971 Census. Up to which year does this remain intact?",
        "answer": 2026,
        "choices": [
            2026,
            2025,
            2031,
            2047
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Presently the number of seats each state in Lok Sabha is allotted on the basis of",
        "answer": "Census of 1971",
        "choices": [
            "Census of 1971",
            "Census of 1951",
            "Census of 1961",
            "Census of 1981"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Fifth Schedule deals with the governance and protection of which specific group of people?",
        "answer": "Scheduled Tribes",
        "choices": [
            "Scheduled Tribes",
            "Scheduled Castes",
            "Religious Minorities",
            "Linguistic Minorities"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "In which Article of the Constitution of India was the provision for reservation of scheduled castes in Lok Sabha made?",
        "answer": "Article 330",
        "choices": [
            "Article 330",
            "Article 331",
            "Article 332",
            "Article 333"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Session of Lok Sabha is called for at least",
        "answer": "two times in a year",
        "choices": [
            "two times in a year",
            "three times in a year",
            "once in a year",
            "four times in a year"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Which State sends the largest number of members in Lok Sabha?",
        "answer": "Uttar Pradesh",
        "choices": [
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Bihar",
            "West Bengal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "So long as the representation in Lok Sabha is concerned, which states rank second and third?",
        "answer": "Maharashtra & West Bengal",
        "choices": [
            "Maharashtra & West Bengal",
            "Bihar & Maharashtra",
            "Madhya Pradesh & Tamil Nadu",
            "Bihar & Tamil Nadu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "First General Election of Lok Sabha was held in",
        "answer": 1952,
        "choices": [
            1952,
            1950,
            1946,
            1947
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Who is the leader of the Lok Sabha?",
        "answer": "Prime Minister",
        "choices": [
            "Prime Minister",
            "President",
            "Speaker",
            "Whip"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "A seat of an MP can be declared vacant if he absents himself from the house for a continous period of",
        "answer": "60 days",
        "choices": [
            "60 days",
            "30 days",
            "45 days",
            "90 days"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Speaker of the Lok Sabha is elected by",
        "answer": "all members of Lok Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "all members of Lok Sabha",
            "all members of parliament",
            "public directly",
            "the members of party in majority"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Attorney General of India is appointed by the",
        "answer": "President",
        "choices": [
            "President",
            "Law Minister",
            "Speaker of the Lok Sabha",
            "Prime Minister"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Rajya Sabha consits of",
        "answer": "250 members of which 12 are nominated",
        "choices": [
            "250 members of which 12 are nominated",
            "280 members of which 20 are nominated",
            "275 members of which 18 are nominated",
            "252 members of which 12 are nominated"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Maximum members in The Lok Sabha",
        "answer": 550,
        "choices": [
            550,
            530,
            543,
            545
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Representation of States in Council of States is based on",
        "answer": "ratio of their Population",
        "choices": [
            "ratio of their Population",
            "ratio of their revenue",
            "ratio of their area",
            "equal for all states"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Member of Rajya Sabha is elected for",
        "answer": "6 years",
        "choices": [
            "6 years",
            "5 years",
            "4 years",
            "life long"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Member of Lok Sabha is elected for",
        "answer": "5 years",
        "choices": [
            "5 years",
            "6 years",
            "4 years",
            "life long"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "According to our Constitution, the Rajya Sabha",
        "answer": "is not subject to dissolution",
        "choices": [
            "is not subject to dissolution",
            "is dissolved once in two years",
            "is dissolved once in five years",
            "is dissolved once in six years"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Right to dissolve the Rajya Sabha is vested in",
        "answer": "None of these",
        "choices": [
            "None of these",
            "President",
            "Vice-President",
            "Supreme Court"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The number of members nominated by the President in Rajya Sabha is",
        "answer": 12,
        "choices": [
            12,
            10,
            11,
            20
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "In which House is the presiding officer not a member of that House?",
        "answer": "Rajya Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "Rajya Sabha",
            "Lok Sabha",
            "Vidhan Sabha",
            "Vidhan Parishad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Under which Article, the speaker can allow any member of the House to speak in his/her mother tongue?",
        "answer": "Article 120",
        "choices": [
            "Article 120",
            "Article 110",
            "Article 122",
            "Article 115"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What can be the maximum interval between the two consecutive sessions of Parliament?",
        "answer": "six months",
        "choices": [
            "six months",
            "12 months",
            "3 months",
            "9 months"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Zero Hour in political jargon refers to",
        "answer": "Question-Answer Session",
        "choices": [
            "Question-Answer Session",
            "Suspended Motion",
            "Adjourned Time",
            "Day when no business in parliament is done"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Joint session of both Houses of Parliament is concerned ",
        "answer": "to discuss and pass sucha a bill where both Houses have different opinion",
        "choices": [
            "to discuss and pass sucha a bill where both Houses have different opinion",
            "for the election of the President of India",
            "for the election of the vice-president of India",
            "to pass the bill relating to the amendment of Constitution"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Money Bill can be presented",
        "answer": "Only in Lok Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "Only in Lok Sabha",
            "Only in Rajya Sabha",
            "In both the Houses",
            "in joint meeting of both the Houses"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Of the following statements, which one is not correct?",
        "answer": "Money bill is introduced in the Rajya Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "Money bill is introduced in the Rajya Sabha",
            "The Rajya Sabha is powerless in money matters",
            "The Rajya Sabha has to pass the Money Bill within 14 days after it has been passed by the Lok Sabha",
            "The Rajya Sabha may pass or return the Money Bill with some recommendations to the Lok Sabha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "Vote on Account is meant for",
        "answer": "Appropriating funds pending passing of budget",
        "choices": [
            "Appropriating funds pending passing of budget",
            "vote on the report of CAG",
            "to meet unforeseen expenditure",
            "Budget"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "What is the object of Cut Motion",
        "answer": "to move a proposal to reduce expenditure in the Budget proposals",
        "choices": [
            "to move a proposal to reduce expenditure in the Budget proposals",
            "to put check on the policies of the Government",
            "to stop the functioning of ruling party",
            "rejection of complete financial dealings of the Government"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The Public Accounts Committee submits its report to",
        "answer": "Speaker of the Lok Sabha",
        "choices": [
            "Speaker of the Lok Sabha",
            "Comptroller & Auditor General",
            "Prime Minister",
            "President"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Polity",
        "question": "The split system in the Indian Administration relates to",
        "answer": "Policy / Implementation",
        "choices": [
            "Policy / Implementation",
            "Audit / Accounts",
            "Union / States",
            "All India Service / Central Service"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Physics involves the study of",
        "answer": "Nature & Natural Phenomena",
        "choices": [
            "Nature & Natural Phenomena",
            "Humans",
            "Birds & Animals",
            "Plants"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Classical Physics does not include subjects like",
        "answer": "Elementary Particles",
        "choices": [
            "Elementary Particles",
            "Mechanics",
            "Heat",
            "Sound"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Size of universe is of the order of",
        "answer": "10^26 m",
        "choices": [
            "10^26 m",
            "10^18 m",
            "10^40 m",
            "10^16 m"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Einstein was awarded Nobel Prize in Physics for",
        "answer": "Law of Photoelectric Effect",
        "choices": [
            "Law of Photoelectric Effect",
            "Theory of Relativity",
            "Law of Gravition",
            "Special Relativity"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Fundamental unit of luminous intensity",
        "answer": "Candela",
        "choices": [
            "Candela",
            "Watt",
            "Joule",
            "Lux"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Weber is derived unit of",
        "answer": "Magnetic Flux",
        "choices": [
            "Magnetic Flux",
            "Magnetic Moment",
            "Luminous Flux",
            "None of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "The prefix femto stands for",
        "answer": "10^-15",
        "choices": [
            "10^-15",
            "10^15",
            "10^12",
            "10^-12"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Number of basic SI Unit is ",
        "answer": 7,
        "choices": [
            7,
            6,
            8,
            5
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Light-year is a unit of ",
        "answer": "Distance",
        "choices": [
            "Distance",
            "Light",
            "Intensity of Light",
            "Time"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Speed of light in a vacuum is approximately ",
        "answer": "3 x 10^8 m/s",
        "choices": [
            "3 x 10^8 m/s",
            "3 x 10^8 km/s",
            "3 x 10^6 m/s",
            "3 x 10^6 km/s"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Ampere is unit of",
        "answer": "Electric Current",
        "choices": [
            "Electric Current",
            "Electric Charge",
            "Magentic Flux",
            "Electric Resistance"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "SI unit of pressure",
        "answer": "Pascal",
        "choices": [
            "Pascal",
            "Dyne",
            "Newton",
            "Joule"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Decibel is unit of",
        "answer": "Intensity of Sound",
        "choices": [
            "Intensity of Sound",
            "Intensity of Light",
            "Speed of Light",
            "None of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "SI unit of electric charge",
        "answer": "Coulomb",
        "choices": [
            "Coulomb",
            "Volts",
            "Ohm",
            "Ampere"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "One astronomical unit (AU) is the average distance between",
        "answer": "Earth & Sun",
        "choices": [
            "Earth & Sun",
            "Earth & Moon",
            "Sun & Moon",
            "Sun & Pluto"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Physical quantity without any unit",
        "answer": "Strain",
        "choices": [
            "Strain",
            "Stress",
            "Force",
            "Pressure"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "One Newton equals to",
        "answer": "1 Kg m/s^2",
        "choices": [
            "1 Kg m/s^2",
            "1 Kg m s",
            "1 Kg m/s",
            "1 Kg m s^2"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "SI unit of acceleration is",
        "answer": "m/s^2",
        "choices": [
            "m/s^2",
            "m/s",
            "ms",
            "ms^2"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "SI unit of electric resistance is",
        "answer": "Ohm",
        "choices": [
            "Ohm",
            "Ampere",
            "Volt",
            "Coulomb"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "1 kWh equals to",
        "answer": "3.6 x 10^6 J",
        "choices": [
            "3.6 x 10^6 J",
            "3.6 x 10^5 J",
            "3.6 x 10^-6 J",
            "3.6 x 10^-5 J"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Electric Potential is measured in",
        "answer": "Joule / Coulomb",
        "choices": [
            "Joule / Coulomb",
            "Watt",
            "Newton-second",
            "Joule"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following pairs have the same units",
        "answer": "Work & Energy",
        "choices": [
            "Work & Energy",
            "Force & Pressure",
            "Power & Energy",
            "Force & Work"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Rate of change of momentum of a body is ",
        "answer": "Impulse",
        "choices": [
            "Impulse",
            "Energy",
            "Power",
            "Force"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "SI unit of power is",
        "answer": "Watt",
        "choices": [
            "Watt",
            "Joule-Second",
            "Joule",
            "Newton-Second"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following equations represents Pressure in Physics",
        "answer": "Force / Area",
        "choices": [
            "Force / Area",
            "Force x Area",
            "Mass / Acceleration",
            "Mass x Acceleration"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following is a scalar quantity",
        "answer": "Mass",
        "choices": [
            "Mass",
            "Momentum",
            "Weight",
            "Gravity"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "One horsepower is approximately equal to",
        "answer": "746 W",
        "choices": [
            "746 W",
            "647 W",
            "476 W",
            "764 W"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Molecular formula of Methyl Isocynate",
        "answer": "C2H3NO",
        "choices": [
            "C2H3NO",
            "C3H5NO",
            "C4H7NO",
            "C4H9NO"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Ore of Thorium",
        "answer": "Monzite",
        "choices": [
            "Monzite",
            "Pitchblende",
            "Carnotite",
            "Hematite"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Ore of Uranium",
        "answer": "Pitchblende",
        "choices": [
            "Pitchblende",
            "Monzite",
            "Thorite",
            "Hematite"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following acids is secreted in the stomach",
        "answer": "Hydrochloric acid",
        "choices": [
            "Hydrochloric acid",
            "Sulphuric acid",
            "Nitric acid",
            "Phosphoric Acid"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "The meter used to measure the distance moved by the vehicle is known as",
        "answer": "Odometer",
        "choices": [
            "Odometer",
            "Ammeter",
            "Speedometer",
            "Chronometer"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Heat transfer that does not require a medium is called",
        "answer": "Radiation",
        "choices": [
            "Radiation",
            "Reflection",
            "Conduction",
            "Convection"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "What type of rock is formed from the cooling and solidification of lava",
        "answer": "Igneous",
        "choices": [
            "Igneous",
            "Sedimentary",
            "Metamorphic",
            "Crystal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following represents the suitable condition for the liquefaction of gases",
        "answer": "Low Temperature, High Pressure",
        "choices": [
            "Low Temperature, High Pressure",
            "Low Temperature, Low Pressure",
            "High Temperature, High Pressure",
            "High Temperature, Low Pressure"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following is an Iron ore",
        "answer": "Limonite",
        "choices": [
            "Limonite",
            "Cinnabar",
            "Bauxite",
            "Pyrite"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which component of fertilizer is used for stimulating early growth",
        "answer": "Phosphorus",
        "choices": [
            "Phosphorus",
            "Nitrogen",
            "Potassium",
            "Oxygen"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following are the constituents of a sodia acid fire extinguisher",
        "answer": "Dilute sulphuric acid and sodium bicarbonate solution",
        "choices": [
            "Dilute sulphuric acid and sodium bicarbonate solution",
            "Dilute sulphuric acid and sodium carbonate",
            "Concentrated sulphuric acid and sodium carbonate solution",
            "Concentrated sulphuric acid and aluminium suplhate"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following bacterial diseases is called splenic fever",
        "answer": "Anthrax",
        "choices": [
            "Anthrax",
            "Typhoid",
            "Cholera",
            "None of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following radiation is used to get relief from body aches",
        "answer": "Infrared",
        "choices": [
            "Infrared",
            "UV",
            "Visible",
            "None of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which one of the following is an example of melamine used for making floor tiles",
        "answer": "Thermosetting Plastics",
        "choices": [
            "Thermosetting Plastics",
            "Thermoplastics",
            "Polythene",
            "PVC"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following is the first artificially prepared element",
        "answer": "Tc",
        "choices": [
            "Tc",
            "Te",
            "Th",
            "TI"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following has a highly elongated elliptical orbit",
        "answer": "Comet",
        "choices": [
            "Comet",
            "Asteroid",
            "Meteorite",
            "Meteor"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following is the fluid part of the blood",
        "answer": "Plasma",
        "choices": [
            "Plasma",
            "WBC",
            "RBC",
            "Platelets"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following minerals occur in Minas Gerais province of Brazil",
        "answer": "Iron",
        "choices": [
            "Iron",
            "Bauxite",
            "Mica",
            "Coal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following is a non-contact force",
        "answer": "Magnetic",
        "choices": [
            "Magnetic",
            "Frictional",
            "Impact",
            "None of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "What is the structural and functional unit of Life",
        "answer": "Cell",
        "choices": [
            "Cell",
            "Organ",
            "Tissue",
            "Organism"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following, corundrum and cryolite are important ore",
        "answer": "Aluminium",
        "choices": [
            "Aluminium",
            "Silver",
            "Tin",
            "Iron"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following is the resistance of wire",
        "answer": "R = V/I",
        "choices": [
            "R = V/I",
            "R = IV",
            "R = I/V",
            "I = R/V"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "What is the value of solar constant",
        "answer": "1.4 kW/m2",
        "choices": [
            "1.4 kW/m2",
            "1.6 kW/m2",
            "1.2 kW/m2",
            "1.8 kW/m2"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following the chlorophyll in photosyntesis is used for",
        "answer": "Absorbing light",
        "choices": [
            "Absorbing light",
            "Reduction of CO2",
            "Breaking downs water molecules",
            "No Function"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which part of alimentary canal receives bile from the liver",
        "answer": "Small Intestine",
        "choices": [
            "Small Intestine",
            "Stomach",
            "Oesophagus",
            "Large Intestine"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "The process of breaking down organic matter by micro-organisms is called",
        "answer": "Decomposition",
        "choices": [
            "Decomposition",
            "Respiration",
            "Photosynthesis",
            "Fermentation"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following is a major cause of pollution",
        "answer": "Burning of Fossil Fuels",
        "choices": [
            "Burning of Fossil Fuels",
            "Disposal of Plastics",
            "Deforestation",
            "Execessive use of pesticides"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Who was the first to propose a model for the structure of an atom",
        "answer": "J J Thomson",
        "choices": [
            "J J Thomson",
            "E Goldstein",
            "Rutherford",
            "Neil Bohr"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "In the following which is fundamental physical quantitiy?",
        "answer": "Electric Current",
        "choices": [
            "Electric Current",
            "Force",
            "Velocity",
            "Work"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "At time of a short circuit, the current in the circuit",
        "answer": "increases heavily",
        "choices": [
            "increases heavily",
            "varies continously",
            "reduces substantially",
            "does not change"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Frequency is measured in",
        "answer": "Hertz",
        "choices": [
            "Hertz",
            "metre/second",
            "radian",
            "watt"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "What is measured in hertz?",
        "answer": "Frequency",
        "choices": [
            "Frequency",
            "Energy",
            "Heat",
            "Work"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Bolometer is used to measure",
        "answer": "Heat Radiations",
        "choices": [
            "Heat Radiations",
            "Frequency",
            "Velocity",
            "Wavelength"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "What is hearing frequency range of Human",
        "answer": "20Hz to 20kHz",
        "choices": [
            "20Hz to 20kHz",
            "2Hz to 20kHz",
            "2Hz to 20Hz",
            "2kHz to 20kHz"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Ohm-meter is unit of ",
        "answer": "Resistivity",
        "choices": [
            "Resistivity",
            "Resistance",
            "Charge",
            "Conductance"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Angstrom is a unit of ",
        "answer": "Wavelength",
        "choices": [
            "Wavelength",
            "Energy",
            "Frequency",
            "Velocity"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "1 Zepto is equal to",
        "answer": "10^-21",
        "choices": [
            "10^-21",
            "10^21",
            "10^-12",
            "10^12"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "One micron is equal to",
        "answer": "10^-6 m",
        "choices": [
            "10^-6 m",
            "10^6 m",
            "10^-3 m",
            "10^3 m"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "One picogram is equal to",
        "answer": "10^-12",
        "choices": [
            "10^-12",
            "10^-21",
            "10^-9",
            "10^-6"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "What is the unit of pressure?",
        "answer": "Newton / sq. meter",
        "choices": [
            "Newton / sq. meter",
            "Newton-meter",
            "Newton",
            "Newton/meter"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Magnetic field is a ",
        "answer": "Vector Quantity",
        "choices": [
            "Vector Quantity",
            "Scalar Quantity",
            "Dimensionless Quantity",
            "None of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "What is Galvanometer used to measure",
        "answer": "Electric Current",
        "choices": [
            "Electric Current",
            "Electric Charge",
            "Electric Resistance",
            "Electric Potential"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following is used to measure the intensity of earthquake?",
        "answer": "Mercalli Scale",
        "choices": [
            "Mercalli Scale",
            "Ritcher Scale",
            "Seismograph",
            "Accelerometer"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Hot-wire ammeters are used to measure",
        "answer": "both AC and DC",
        "choices": [
            "both AC and DC",
            "only DC",
            "only AC",
            "neither AC nor DC"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which instrument is used for measuring electric potential?",
        "answer": "Potentiometer",
        "choices": [
            "Potentiometer",
            "Ammeter",
            "Galvanometer",
            "Accelerometer"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "The device used to measure electric current is",
        "answer": "Ammeter",
        "choices": [
            "Ammeter",
            "Potentiometer",
            "Voltmeter",
            "Voltameter"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "The resistance of an ideal voltmeter is ",
        "answer": "infinite",
        "choices": [
            "infinite",
            "negative",
            "zero",
            "one"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which instrument is used to measure humidity",
        "answer": "Hygrometer",
        "choices": [
            "Hygrometer",
            "Hydrometer",
            "Pyrometer",
            "Lactometer"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Electroencephalogram (EEG) is used in monitoring",
        "answer": "Brain",
        "choices": [
            "Brain",
            "Heart",
            "Liver",
            "Kidney"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "For a satellite, escape velocity is 11km/s. If the satellite is launched at an angle of 60 degree with the vertical, then the escape velocity will be",
        "answer": "does not change",
        "choices": [
            "does not change",
            "increases",
            "decreases",
            "becomes zero"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "What is the law in which under the same conditions of temperature and pressure, equal volumes of all gases contain equal number of molecules?",
        "answer": "Avogadro's Law",
        "choices": [
            "Avogadro's Law",
            "Graham's Law",
            "Pascal's Law",
            "Coriolis Effect"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "A goalkeeper in a game of football pull his hands backwards after holding the ball shot at the goal. This enables the goalkeeper to",
        "answer": "decrease the rate of change of momentum",
        "choices": [
            "decrease the rate of change of momentum",
            "increase the force exerted by the ball on hands",
            "exert large force on the ball",
            "increases the score"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "When the stone is brought from the surface of the moon to the earth, then",
        "answer": "its weight will change, but mass will not change",
        "choices": [
            "its weight will change, but mass will not change",
            "it mass will change",
            "both weight and mass will change",
            "neither weight nor mass will change"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following is not a vector quantity",
        "answer": "volume",
        "choices": [
            "volume",
            "velocity",
            "displacement",
            "force"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following is not a vector quantity",
        "answer": "speed",
        "choices": [
            "speed",
            "velocity",
            "torque",
            "displacement"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following is a scalar quantity",
        "answer": "Pressure",
        "choices": [
            "Pressure",
            "Force",
            "Acceleration",
            "Velocity"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Current density is",
        "answer": "a vector quantity",
        "choices": [
            "a vector quantity",
            "a scalar quantity",
            "Dimensionless Quantity",
            "None of these"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "A sudden rise in the barometric height indicates",
        "answer": "extremely dry weather",
        "choices": [
            "extremely dry weather",
            "coming of storm or cyclone",
            "possibility of rain",
            "dry weather"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "The time period of a pendulum clock is ",
        "answer": "1 second",
        "choices": [
            "1 second",
            "2 seconds",
            "1 minute",
            "1 hour"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which physical quantity is represented by the ratio of momentum and velocity of the body?",
        "answer": "Mass",
        "choices": [
            "Mass",
            "velocity",
            "Acceleration",
            "Force"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which is the correct formula of acceleration?",
        "answer": "a = (v-u)/t",
        "choices": [
            "a = (v-u)/t",
            "a = u + vt",
            "a = (u + v )/t",
            "a = u + v/t"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Force is the product of ",
        "answer": "Mass & Acceleration",
        "choices": [
            "Mass & Acceleration",
            "Mass & Velocity",
            "Weight & Density",
            "Weight & Acceleration"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Ball bearings are used to convert static friction into",
        "answer": "rolling friction",
        "choices": [
            "rolling friction",
            "drag",
            "sliding friction",
            "torque"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following energy changes involves frictional force?",
        "answer": "Kinetic Energy to Heat Energy",
        "choices": [
            "Kinetic Energy to Heat Energy",
            "Chemical energy to Heat Energy",
            "Kinetic Energy to Electric Energy",
            "Potential Energy to Sound Energy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Lenz's law is derived from the law of conservation of ",
        "answer": "Energy",
        "choices": [
            "Energy",
            "Charge",
            "Momentum",
            "Magnetism"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "If a feather, a rubber ball and a wooden ball are failing freely simultaneously from the same height in the vacuum then",
        "answer": "all three will reach the ground together",
        "choices": [
            "all three will reach the ground together",
            "the wooden ball will reach the ground first",
            "the rubber ball will reach the ground first",
            "the feather will reach the ground last"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "When a body falls freely towards the Earth, then its total energy",
        "answer": "remains constant",
        "choices": [
            "remains constant",
            "increases",
            "decreases",
            "becomes zero"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "A second pendulum is mounted in a rocket. Its period of oscillation decreases when the rocket",
        "answer": "moves up with uniform acceleration",
        "choices": [
            "moves up with uniform acceleration",
            "comes down with uniform acceleration",
            "moves round the earth in a geostationary orbit",
            "moves up with uniform velocity"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "For a body moving with constant speed in a horizontal circle, which of the following remains constant?",
        "answer": "Kinetic Energy",
        "choices": [
            "Kinetic Energy",
            "velocity",
            "Acceleration",
            "Centripetal Force"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "If the spinning speed of the earth increases, then the weight of the body at equator will",
        "answer": "decrease",
        "choices": [
            "decrease",
            "increase",
            "remains same",
            "be doubled"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "The time period of a pendulum",
        "answer": "depends on its length",
        "choices": [
            "depends on its length",
            "depends on the mass",
            "depends on time",
            "depends on temperature"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "You are standing in an elevator. The force exerted by your weight on the floor of the elevator",
        "answer": "will be zero when the lift comes down with an acceleration of 9.8m/s2",
        "choices": [
            "will be zero when the lift comes down with an acceleration of 9.8m/s2",
            "will be zero when the lift goes up with an acceleration of 9.8m/s2",
            "Zero when the lift moves in any direction with an acceleration of 9.8m/s2",
            "will not be affected by the change in the rate of acceleration of the lift"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "A bus is moving along a straight path and takes a sharp turn to the right side suddenly, the passengers in the bus will",
        "answer": "bent towards left side",
        "choices": [
            "bent towards left side",
            "bent towards right side",
            "fall in forward direction ",
            "fall in backward direction"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "A man pushes more weight on the Earth at",
        "answer": "standing position",
        "choices": [
            "standing position",
            "sitting position",
            "lying position",
            "sleeping position"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Environment is a composite state of",
        "answer": "All of these",
        "choices": [
            "All of these",
            "Biotic Factors",
            "Abiotic Factors",
            "Physiographic Factors"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "What is the thin layer of gases around the earth called?",
        "answer": "Atmosphere",
        "choices": [
            "Atmosphere",
            "Biosphere",
            "Hydroshpere",
            "Lithoshpere"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "The atmosphere is mainly heated by the ",
        "answer": "long-wave terrestrial radiation",
        "choices": [
            "long-wave terrestrial radiation",
            "short-wave solar radiation",
            "volcanic emission",
            "emission from distant stars"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Air is a/an",
        "answer": "Mixture",
        "choices": [
            "Mixture",
            "Compound",
            "Element",
            "Electrolyte"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "The highest percentage of gas in the air is",
        "answer": "Nitrogen",
        "choices": [
            "Nitrogen",
            "Hydrogen",
            "Oxygen",
            "Carbon Dioxide"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "The tallest known living tree",
        "answer": "Sequoia",
        "choices": [
            "Sequoia",
            "Eucalyptus",
            "Deodar",
            "Parnang"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "The major component of CNG is",
        "answer": "CH4",
        "choices": [
            "CH4",
            "N2",
            "CO2",
            "H2"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Pollutant emission gas in vehichle exhaust is mainly",
        "answer": "Carbon Monoxide",
        "choices": [
            "Carbon Monoxide",
            "Carbon Dioxide",
            "Nitrogen Oxide",
            "Marsh Gas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Inhalation of air polluted with Carbon Monoxide is dangerous because",
        "answer": "It combines with hemoglobin",
        "choices": [
            "It combines with hemoglobin",
            "it combines with oxygen in blood",
            "it removes water from the body and causes dehydration",
            "it causes coagulation of proteins in the body"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "The components of acid rain is/are",
        "answer": "HNO3 & H2SO4",
        "choices": [
            "HNO3 & H2SO4",
            "HNO3",
            "H2SO4",
            "CO2"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "The major and top source of oxygen in the atmosphere is",
        "answer": "Photosynthesis by oceanic phytoplanktons",
        "choices": [
            "Photosynthesis by oceanic phytoplanktons",
            "Photosynthesis by forest plants",
            "photosynthesis by grassland ecosystem",
            "photosynthesis be wtland algaes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "In which year International Space Station was launched?",
        "answer": 1998,
        "choices": [
            1998,
            1999,
            2000,
            1997
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Name the world's first Space Station",
        "answer": "Salyut 1",
        "choices": [
            "Salyut 1",
            "Mir",
            "Skylab",
            "Tiangong"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "First country to launch space station in the world",
        "answer": "USSR",
        "choices": [
            "USSR",
            "USA",
            "China",
            "India"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Name the first person in the world to travel in space?",
        "answer": "Yuri Gagrin",
        "choices": [
            "Yuri Gagrin",
            "Rakesh Sharma",
            "Shubhanshu Shukla",
            "Alan Shepard"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "The indigenous malaria vaccine candidate developed under the aegis of ICMR is called",
        "answer": "AdFalciVax",
        "choices": [
            "AdFalciVax",
            "R21/Matrix-M",
            "RTS,S",
            "Covaxin"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": " AdFalciVax, the malaria vaccine candidate developed in India, is primarily targeted against which malaria parasite?",
        "answer": "Plasmodium falciparum",
        "choices": [
            "Plasmodium falciparum",
            "Plasmodium vivax",
            "Plasmodium ovale",
            "Plasmodium malariae"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "What is the typical electrical output range of Small Modular Reactors (SMRs)?",
        "answer": "50 to 300 MW",
        "choices": [
            "50 to 300 MW",
            "10 to 50 MW",
            "300 to 1000 MW",
            "More than 2000 MW"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "What is the key feature of a Small Modular Reactor (SMR) compared to traditional nuclear reactors?",
        "answer": "Can be manufactured in a factory and assembled on-site",
        "choices": [
            "Can be manufactured in a factory and assembled on-site",
            "Uses only thorium as fuel",
            "Requires high population density",
            "Requires extremely large cooling towers"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Chikungunya is caused by which type of microorganism?",
        "answer": "Virus",
        "choices": [
            "Virus",
            "Bacteria",
            "Fungus",
            "Protozoa"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Chikungunya virus is primarily transmitted by which mosquito?",
        "answer": "Aedes Aegypti",
        "choices": [
            "Aedes Aegypti",
            "Culex",
            "Anopheles",
            "Tabanus"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "What is the most characteristic symptom of Chikungunya?",
        "answer": "Severe joint pain",
        "choices": [
            "Severe joint pain",
            "Skin Ulcers",
            "Swelling of lympt nodes",
            "Paralysis"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Science",
        "question": "Which of the following diseases is not transmitted by Aedes mosquitoes?",
        "answer": "Malaria",
        "choices": [
            "Malaria",
            "Chikungunya",
            "Zika",
            "Dengue"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "GeneralKnowledge",
        "question": "World Biofuel Day is observed every year on which date?",
        "answer": "10th August",
        "choices": [
            "10th August",
            "8th June",
            "14th Novemeber",
            "16th September"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "GeneralKnowledge",
        "question": "When is World Earth Day celebrated",
        "answer": "22nd April",
        "choices": [
            "22nd April",
            "5th June",
            "9th August",
            "2nd October"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "GeneralKnowledge",
        "question": "When is World Environment Day celebrated?",
        "answer": "5th June",
        "choices": [
            "5th June",
            "22nd April",
            "9th August",
            "2nd October"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "GeneralKnowledge",
        "question": "When is World Sparrow Day celebrated?",
        "answer": "20th March",
        "choices": [
            "20th March",
            "20th May",
            "20th April",
            "20th June"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "GeneralKnowledge",
        "question": "Who is considered the founder of ISRO?",
        "answer": "Dr Vikram Sarabhai",
        "choices": [
            "Dr Vikram Sarabhai",
            "Dr Homi Bhabha",
            "DR APJ Abdul Kalam",
            "Dr Satish Shawan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "GeneralKnowledge",
        "question": "Where is the headquarters of ISRO located?",
        "answer": "Bengaluru",
        "choices": [
            "Bengaluru",
            "Hyderabad",
            "Mumbai",
            "Chennai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "GeneralKnowledge",
        "question": "Name the first President of India",
        "answer": "Rajendra Prasad",
        "choices": [
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Savapalli Radhakrishnan",
            "Zakir Hussain",
            "Pratibha Patil"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "GeneralKnowledge",
        "question": "Name the first female President of India",
        "answer": "Pratibha Patil",
        "choices": [
            "Pratibha Patil",
            "Draupadi Murmu",
            "Indira Gandhi",
            "Rekha Gupta"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "GeneralKnowledge",
        "question": "Name the first President of India belonging to minority religon",
        "answer": "Zakir Hussain",
        "choices": [
            "Zakir Hussain",
            "Draupadi Murmu",
            "Pratibha Patil",
            "Sarvapalli Radhakrishnan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "GeneralKnowledge",
        "question": "Name the first President of India belonging to tribal community",
        "answer": "Draupadi Murmu",
        "choices": [
            "Draupadi Murmu",
            "V V Giri",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Zakir Hussain"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "GeneralKnowledge",
        "question": "Name the longest serving president of India till now?",
        "answer": "Rajendra Prasad",
        "choices": [
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Savapalli Radhakrishnan",
            "Mohammad Hamid Ansari",
            "Pratibha Patil"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Which type of economy does India have?",
        "answer": "Mixed",
        "choices": [
            "Mixed",
            "Socialist",
            "Gandhian",
            "Free"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "The main source of national income of India is",
        "answer": "Service",
        "choices": [
            "Service",
            "Manufacturing",
            "Agriculture",
            "Foreign Remittances"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "As the economy develops, the national income share of tertiary sector",
        "answer": "goes on increasing",
        "choices": [
            "goes on increasing",
            "first decreases, then increase",
            "first increase, then decrease",
            "goes on decreasing"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "One of the problems in calculating National Income in India is",
        "answer": "non-organised sector",
        "choices": [
            "non-organised sector",
            "under-employment",
            "inflation",
            "low level of savings"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Which of the following is not a method to calculate the Gross Domestic Product (GDP)?",
        "answer": "Diminishing Cost Method",
        "choices": [
            "Diminishing Cost Method",
            "Product Method",
            "Income Method",
            "Expenditure Method"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Which one does not come under economic infrastructure?",
        "answer": "Education or Health",
        "choices": [
            "Education or Health",
            "Energy",
            "Roads",
            "Railway"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Hindu growth is related to",
        "answer": "GDP",
        "choices": [
            "GDP",
            "Money",
            "Population",
            "GNP"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "What is money?",
        "answer": "Commodity",
        "choices": [
            "Commodity",
            "Income",
            "Wealth",
            "Savings"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "The economist who for the first time scientifically determined National Income in India?",
        "answer": "V K R V Rao",
        "choices": [
            "V K R V Rao",
            "D R Gadgil",
            "Manmohan Singh",
            "Y V Alagh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Who was the remarkable person who took the action for calculating the national income of India before Independence?",
        "answer": "Dadabhai Naoroji",
        "choices": [
            "Dadabhai Naoroji",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Surendranath Banerjee"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Which of the following offices or institutes releases data of the National Income in India?",
        "answer": "Nationa Statistical Office (NSO)",
        "choices": [
            "Nationa Statistical Office (NSO)",
            "National Sample Survey Office (NSSO)",
            "Central Statistical Office (CSO) ",
            "NITI Ayog"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Which organisation carries out the survey for determining the poverty line?",
        "answer": "Nationa Statistical Office (NSO)",
        "choices": [
            "Nationa Statistical Office (NSO)",
            "National Sample Survey Office (NSSO)",
            "Reserve Bank of India (RBI)",
            "NITI Ayog"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Which ministry is responsible for calculating GDP of India?",
        "answer": "Ministry of Central Statistical and Program Implementation",
        "choices": [
            "Ministry of Central Statistical and Program Implementation",
            "Ministry of Commerce and Industry",
            "Ministry of Finance",
            "Ministry of Consumer Affairs"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "The best index of economic income can be provided by",
        "answer": "increase in per capita real income per year",
        "choices": [
            "increase in per capita real income per year",
            "increase in national income at current price",
            "increase in savings ration",
            "improvement in balance of payment position"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Per Capita income of a country is obtained from",
        "answer": "both National Income and Population",
        "choices": [
            "both National Income and Population",
            "Population",
            "National Income",
            "GDP"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "The latest per capita income at constant prices is lowest for which state of India?",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Jharkhand",
            "Manipur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "The latest per capita income at constant prices is highest for which state of India?",
        "answer": "Sikkim",
        "choices": [
            "Sikkim",
            "Goa",
            "Telangana",
            "Karnataka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Which state of India has highest Gross State Domestic Product (GSDP)?",
        "answer": "Maharashtra",
        "choices": [
            "Maharashtra",
            "Karnataka",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Tamil Nadu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Which sector of Indian economy contributes the most to the Gross National Product (GNP)?",
        "answer": "Tertiary Sector",
        "choices": [
            "Tertiary Sector",
            "Secondary Sector",
            "Primary Sector",
            "Public Sector"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Which organization publishes the global Sustainable Development Report (SDR)?",
        "answer": "UN Sustainable Development Solutions Network",
        "choices": [
            "UN Sustainable Development Solutions Network",
            "NITI Aayog",
            "United Nations Development Programme (UNDP)",
            "World Bank"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "As per the Sustainable Development Report (SDR) 2025, what is India's rank in the SDG Index out of 167 countries?",
        "answer": "99th",
        "choices": [
            "99th",
            "109th ",
            "112th",
            "121st"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Which Indian organization is responsible for monitoring the progress of SDGs at the sub-national level (States and UTs)?",
        "answer": "NITI Aayog",
        "choices": [
            "NITI Aayog",
            "Ministry of Finance",
            "Reserve Bank of India (RBI)",
            "Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation (MoSPI)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "The SDG Index measures a country's progress towards which set of goals?",
        "answer": "17 goals",
        "choices": [
            "17 goals",
            "10 goals",
            "15 goals",
            "20 goals"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "The Human Capital Index (HCI) is published by which of the following international organizations?",
        "answer": "World Bank",
        "choices": [
            "World Bank",
            "United Nations Development Programme (UNDP)",
            "World Health Organisation (WHO)",
            "International Monetary Fund (IMF)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "In India, the agricultural crop year period is",
        "answer": "1st July to 30th June",
        "choices": [
            "1st July to 30th June",
            "1st June to 31st May",
            "1st April to 31st March",
            "1st January to 31st December"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "What is the theme of the Union Budget 2025-26?",
        "answer": "Sabka Vikas",
        "choices": [
            "Sabka Vikas",
            "Sabka Vikas Sabka Prayas",
            "Sabka Sath",
            "Viksit Bharat"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Union Economic Survey 2024-25, what is the expected Real GDP growth for FY2025?",
        "answer": "6.4 percent",
        "choices": [
            "6.4 percent",
            "4.6 percent",
            "5.4 percent",
            "4.5 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Union Economic Survey 2024-25, what is the expected Real GVA growth for FY2025?",
        "answer": "6.4 percent",
        "choices": [
            "6.4 percent",
            "4.6 percent",
            "5.4 percent",
            "4.5 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "In the Union Budget 2025-26 what are the four engines of Economic Growth?",
        "answer": "Agriculture, MSME, Investment and Exports",
        "choices": [
            "Agriculture, MSME, Investment and Exports",
            "Agriculture, Defence, Tourism, Banking",
            "Defence, Tourism, Exports, Banking",
            "Tourism, Banking, MSME, Sports"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "In the Union Budget 2025-26 what are the four focus point?",
        "answer": "Poor, Youth, Farmers, Women",
        "choices": [
            "Poor, Youth, Farmers, Women",
            "Poor, Science, Tourism, Health",
            "Youth, Health, Sports, AI",
            "AI, Crypto, Energy, Infrastructure"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "The quote - A country is not just its soil; a country is its people, mentioned in the Union Budget 2025–26 speech, is attributed to which Indian personality?",
        "answer": "Gurajada Appa Rao",
        "choices": [
            "Gurajada Appa Rao",
            "Rabindranath Tagore",
            "Mahatma Gandhi",
            "Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Under the broad principles of Viksit Bharat announced in the Union Budget 2025-26, what percentage of women should be engaged in economic activities?",
        "answer": "70% by 2047",
        "choices": [
            "70% by 2047",
            "60% by 2040",
            "80% by 2050",
            "50% by 2030"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "In the Union Budget 2025-26 which among the following is considered as the fuel for economic growth?",
        "answer": "Reforms",
        "choices": [
            "Reforms",
            "Inclusivity",
            "Devlopment",
            "Technology"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "In the Union Budget 2025-26 which among the following is considered as the guiding spirit for economic growth?",
        "answer": "Inclusivity",
        "choices": [
            "Inclusivity",
            "Reforms",
            "Devlopment",
            "Technology"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "In the Union Budget 2025-26 which among the following is considered as the destination of economic growth?",
        "answer": "Viksit Bharat",
        "choices": [
            "Viksit Bharat",
            "Inclusivity",
            "Devlopment",
            "Reforms"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Union Economic Survey 2024–25, India’s rank in global services exports is:",
        "answer": "Seventh",
        "choices": [
            "Seventh",
            "Third",
            "Fifth",
            "Tenth"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Union Economic Survey 2024–25, what was the approximate size of India’s forex reserves by the end of December 2024?",
        "answer": "USD 640.3 billion",
        "choices": [
            "USD 640.3 billion",
            "USD 640.3 million",
            "USD 634.6 billion",
            "USD 652.9 million"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Union Budget 2025-26, how many Atal Tinkering Labs will be open in government schools?",
        "answer": 50000,
        "choices": [
            50000,
            30000,
            20000,
            10000
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Union Economic Survey 2024-25, what is the Labour Force Participation ratio (LFPR) of India?",
        "answer": "60.1 percent",
        "choices": [
            "60.1 percent",
            "58.2 percent",
            "57.9 percent",
            "56.0 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Union Economic Survey 2024-25, what is the Worker Population Ratio (WPR) of India?",
        "answer": "58.2 percent",
        "choices": [
            "58.2 percent",
            "60.1 percent",
            "57.9 percent",
            "56.0 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Union Economic Survey 2024-25, what is the Unemployment rate in India?",
        "answer": "3.2 percent",
        "choices": [
            "3.2 percent",
            "2.8 percent",
            "3.0 percent",
            "2.5 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "Under the six-year Mission for Aatmanirbharta in Pulses, which of the following pulses is not explicitly given special focus?",
        "answer": "Moong",
        "choices": [
            "Moong",
            "Tur",
            "Masoor",
            "Urad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Union Economic Survey 2024–25, which category represents the largest share of the total workforce in India?",
        "answer": "Self-employed",
        "choices": [
            "Self-employed",
            "Casual Labour",
            "Regular Wage / Salaried",
            "Unpaid Workers"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Union Budget 2025–26, what is the revised investment and turnover limit for an enterprise to be classified as a Micro MSME?",
        "answer": "Investement up to 2.5 crore and turnover upto 10 crore",
        "choices": [
            "Investement up to 2.5 crore and turnover upto 10 crore",
            "Investement up to 1 crore and turnover upto 5 crore",
            "Investement up to 25 crore and turnover upto 100 crore",
            "Investement up to 125 crore and turnover upto 500 crore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Union Budget 2025–26, what is the revised investment and turnover limit for an enterprise to be classified as a Small MSME?",
        "answer": "Investement up to 25 crore and turnover upto 100 crore",
        "choices": [
            "Investement up to 25 crore and turnover upto 100 crore",
            "Investement up to 10 crore and turnover upto 50 crore",
            "Investement up to 5 crore and turnover upto 10 crore",
            "Investement up to 125 crore and turnover upto 500 crore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Union Budget 2025–26, what is the revised investment and turnover limit for an enterprise to be classified as a Medium MSME?",
        "answer": "Investement up to 125 crore and turnover upto 500 crore",
        "choices": [
            "Investement up to 125 crore and turnover upto 500 crore",
            "Investement up to 50 crore and turnover upto 250 crore",
            "Investement up to 25 crore and turnover upto 100 crore",
            "Investement up to 2.5 crore and turnover upto 10 crore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "UnionEconomy",
        "question": "In the Union Budget 2024–25, which ministry received the highest budget allocation?",
        "answer": "Ministry of Defense",
        "choices": [
            "Ministry of Defense",
            "Ministry of Agriuculture & Farmers Welfare",
            "Ministry of Railways",
            "Ministry of Education"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, what was the literacy rate of Bihar?",
        "answer": "61.8 percent",
        "choices": [
            "61.8 percent",
            "58.5 percent",
            "65.3 percent",
            "70.2 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "What was the literacy rate of India as per the Census 2011?",
        "answer": "74.0 percent",
        "choices": [
            "74.0 percent",
            "61.8 percent",
            "65.4 percent",
            "68.7 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, which district has highest literacy rate in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Rohtas",
        "choices": [
            "Rohtas",
            "Patna",
            "Purnea",
            "Gopalganj"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, which district has lowest literacy rate in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Purnea",
        "choices": [
            "Purnea",
            "Munger",
            "Rohtas",
            "Gopalganj"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, what was the male literacy rate in Bihar?",
        "answer": "71.2 percent",
        "choices": [
            "71.2 percent",
            "61.8 percent",
            "74.0 percent",
            "51.5 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, what was the female literacy rate in Bihar?",
        "answer": "51.5 percent",
        "choices": [
            "51.5 percent",
            "61.8 percent",
            "74.0 percent",
            "71.2 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "Which state had the highest literacy rate according to Census 2011?",
        "answer": "Kerala",
        "choices": [
            "Kerala",
            "Bihar",
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Maharashtra"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "Which state had the lowest literacy rate according to Census 2011?",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Jharkhand",
            "West Bengal",
            "Assam"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, what is the sex-ratio of Bihar?",
        "answer": 918,
        "choices": [
            918,
            943,
            950,
            981
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, what is the sex-ratio of India?",
        "answer": 943,
        "choices": [
            943,
            918,
            948,
            952
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, which district has the highest sex-ratio in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Gopalganj",
        "choices": [
            "Gopalganj",
            "Munger",
            "Purnea",
            "Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, which district has the lowest sex-ratio in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Munger",
        "choices": [
            "Munger",
            "Gopalganj",
            "Sheohar",
            "Kaimur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, what is the population density of Bihar?",
        "answer": "1106 sq km",
        "choices": [
            "1106 sq km",
            "382 sq km",
            "812 sq km",
            "1206 sq km"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, what is the population density of India?",
        "answer": "382 sq km",
        "choices": [
            "382 sq km",
            "1106 sq km",
            "812 sq km",
            "1206 sq km"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, which district has the highest population density in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Sheohar",
        "choices": [
            "Sheohar",
            "Sheikhpura",
            "Kaimur",
            "Rohtas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, which district has the lowest population density in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Kaimur",
        "choices": [
            "Kaimur",
            "Sheikhpura",
            "Sheohar",
            "Rohtas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, which district has the lowest population in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Sheikhpura",
        "choices": [
            "Sheikhpura",
            "Sheohar",
            "Kaimur",
            "Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, which district has the highest population in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Patna",
        "choices": [
            "Patna",
            "Sheohar",
            "Kaimur",
            "Sheikhpura"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "Which State has the highest population according to Census 2011?",
        "answer": "Uttar Pradesh",
        "choices": [
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Bihar",
            "Maharashtra",
            "West Bengal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "Which State has the lowest population according to Census 2011?",
        "answer": "Sikkim",
        "choices": [
            "Sikkim",
            "Manipur",
            "Tripura",
            "Goa"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "Which Union Territory has the lowest population according to Census 2011?",
        "answer": "Lakshadweep",
        "choices": [
            "Lakshadweep",
            "Andmand & Nicobar Islands",
            "Puducherry",
            "Ladakh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "Which Union Territory has the highest population according to Census 2011?",
        "answer": "Delhi",
        "choices": [
            "Delhi",
            "Ladakh",
            "Jammu & Kashmir",
            "Chandigarh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, which district has the lowest population in India?",
        "answer": "Dibang Valley, Arunachal Pradesh",
        "choices": [
            "Dibang Valley, Arunachal Pradesh",
            "Leh, Ladakh",
            "Mahe, Puducherry",
            "Diu, Daman & Diu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, which district has the highest population in India?",
        "answer": "Thane, Maharashtra",
        "choices": [
            "Thane, Maharashtra",
            "Sheohar, Bihar",
            "Varanasi, Uttar Pradesh",
            "Bhopal, Madhya Pradesh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "Which State has the highest population density according to Census 2011?",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Mahrashtra",
            "Sikkim"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "Which State has the lowest population density according to Census 2011?",
        "answer": "Arunachal Pradesh",
        "choices": [
            "Arunachal Pradesh",
            "Assam",
            "Sikkim",
            "Goa"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "Which Union Territory has the highest population density according to Census 2011?",
        "answer": "Delhi",
        "choices": [
            "Delhi",
            "Lakshadweep",
            "Andman & Nicobar Islands",
            "Ladakh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "Which Union Territory has the lowest population density according to Census 2011?",
        "answer": "Andman & Nicobar Islands",
        "choices": [
            "Andman & Nicobar Islands",
            "Lakshadweep",
            "Daman & Diue",
            "Ladakh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, what was the total population of India?",
        "answer": "121 crore",
        "choices": [
            "121 crore",
            "11 crore",
            "110 crore",
            "112 crore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, what was the total population of Bihar?",
        "answer": "10.4 crore",
        "choices": [
            "10.4 crore",
            "14 crore",
            "104 crore",
            "41 crore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, Bihar’s population is approximately what percent of India’s total population?",
        "answer": "8.6 percent",
        "choices": [
            "8.6 percent",
            "7.2 percent",
            "9.4 percent",
            "10.2 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "In terms of population, what is the rank of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Third",
        "choices": [
            "Third",
            "Second",
            "First ",
            "Fourth"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, the percentage of urban and rural population of Bihar is respectively",
        "answer": "11.3% and 88.7%",
        "choices": [
            "11.3% and 88.7%",
            "13.4% and 86.6%",
            "17.3% and 82.7%",
            "10.2% and 89.8%"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "In terms of urban population, Bihar ranks among the states/union territories of the country?",
        "answer": "12th",
        "choices": [
            "12th",
            "11th",
            "13th",
            "14th"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, which is the most populous Scheduled Tribe in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Santhal",
        "choices": [
            "Santhal",
            "Bhil",
            "Gond",
            "Munda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, which is the most populous Scheduled Tribe in India?",
        "answer": "Bhil",
        "choices": [
            "Bhil",
            "Santhal",
            "Gond",
            "Munda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, what percentage of tribal population lives in India?",
        "answer": "8.6 percent",
        "choices": [
            "8.6 percent",
            "1.3 percent",
            "9.4 percent",
            "7.2 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "Census",
        "question": "According to Census 2011, what percentage of tribal population lives in Bihar?",
        "answer": "1.3 percent",
        "choices": [
            "1.3 percent",
            "8.6 percent",
            "9.4 percent",
            "7.2 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Bihar State Formation Day",
        "answer": "22nd March 1912",
        "choices": [
            "22nd March 1912",
            "22nd March 1913",
            "12nd March 1922",
            "23rd March 1912"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "North most latitude of Bihar",
        "answer": "27 deg 31 min 15 sec N",
        "choices": [
            "27 deg 31 min 15 sec N",
            "24 deg 20 min 10 sec N",
            "83 deg 19 min 50 sec N",
            "88 deg 17 min 40 sec N"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "South most latitude of Bihar",
        "answer": "24 deg 20 min 10 sec N",
        "choices": [
            "24 deg 20 min 10 sec N",
            "27 deg 31 min 15 sec N",
            "83 deg 19 min 50 sec N",
            "88 deg 17 min 40 sec N"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "East most longitude of Bihar",
        "answer": "88 deg 17 min 40 sec E",
        "choices": [
            "88 deg 17 min 40 sec E",
            "27 deg 31 min 15 sec E",
            "83 deg 19 min 50 sec E",
            "24 deg 20 min 10 sec E"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "West most longitude of Bihar",
        "answer": "83 deg 19 min 50 sec E",
        "choices": [
            "83 deg 19 min 50 sec E",
            "27 deg 31 min 15 sec E",
            "88 deg 17 min 40 sec E",
            "24 deg 20 min 10 sec E"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "North-South extent of Bihar",
        "answer": "345 km",
        "choices": [
            "345 km",
            "453 km",
            "435 km",
            "543 km"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "East-West extent of Bihar",
        "answer": "483 km",
        "choices": [
            "483 km",
            "834 km",
            "384 km",
            "438 km"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Total area of Bihar",
        "answer": "94,163 sq km",
        "choices": [
            "94,163 sq km",
            "91,463 sq km",
            "96,143 sq km",
            "93,164 sq km"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Area of Bihar compared to area of India",
        "answer": "2.86 percent",
        "choices": [
            "2.86 percent",
            "3.28 percent",
            "8.32 percent",
            "2.38 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Height of Bihar above mean sea-level in feet",
        "answer": "173 ft",
        "choices": [
            "173 ft",
            "371 ft",
            "137 ft",
            "317 ft"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Height of Bihar above mean sea-level in meters",
        "answer": "53 m",
        "choices": [
            "53 m",
            "52 m",
            "51 m",
            "50 m"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Total number of Divisions in Bihar",
        "answer": 9,
        "choices": [
            9,
            8,
            10,
            7
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Total number of Districts in Bihar",
        "answer": 38,
        "choices": [
            38,
            39,
            37,
            36
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Total number of Sub-Divisions in Bihar",
        "answer": 101,
        "choices": [
            101,
            100,
            102,
            103
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Total number of Blocks in Bihar",
        "answer": 534,
        "choices": [
            534,
            535,
            533,
            532
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Total number of Panchayat in Bihar",
        "answer": 8406,
        "choices": [
            8406,
            8405,
            8407,
            8403
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "How many district of Bihar shares international boundary with Nepal",
        "answer": 7,
        "choices": [
            7,
            8,
            3,
            6
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Northern-most district of Bihar",
        "answer": "West Champaran",
        "choices": [
            "West Champaran",
            "Gaya",
            "Kishanganj",
            "Kaimur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Southern-most district of Bihar",
        "answer": "Gaya",
        "choices": [
            "Gaya",
            "West Champaran",
            "Kishanganj",
            "Kaimur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Eastern-most district of Bihar",
        "answer": "Kishanganj",
        "choices": [
            "Kishanganj",
            "West Champaran",
            "Gaya",
            "Kaimur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Western-most district of Bihar",
        "answer": "Kaimur",
        "choices": [
            "Kaimur",
            "West Champaran",
            "Gaya",
            "Kishanganj"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Area wise largest district of Bihar",
        "answer": "West Champaran",
        "choices": [
            "West Champaran",
            "Gaya",
            "Kaimur",
            "Rohtas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Area wise smallest district of Bihar",
        "answer": "Sheohar",
        "choices": [
            "Sheohar",
            "Sheikhpura",
            "Arwal",
            "Jehanabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "District with highest rainfall in Bihar",
        "answer": "Kishanganj",
        "choices": [
            "Kishanganj",
            "Kaimur",
            "Araria",
            "Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "District with least rainfall in Bihar",
        "answer": "Kaimur",
        "choices": [
            "Kaimur",
            "Kishanganj",
            "Araria",
            "Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Average number of rainy days in Bihar in a year",
        "answer": "52.5 days",
        "choices": [
            "52.5 days",
            "53.5 days",
            "55.5 days",
            "51.5 days"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Official language of Bihar",
        "answer": "Hindi",
        "choices": [
            "Hindi",
            "Bhojpuri",
            "Maithili",
            "Magahi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "In which constitutional amendment Maithili was included in the 8th Schedule of Constitution",
        "answer": "92nd",
        "choices": [
            "92nd",
            "91st",
            "93rd",
            "90th"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "What is the population percentage of Bihar compared to India according to Census 2011",
        "answer": "8.6 percent",
        "choices": [
            "8.6 percent",
            "6.8 percent",
            "9.6 percent",
            "6.9 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "What is the population percentage density of Bihar according to Census 2011",
        "answer": "1,106 person per sq km",
        "choices": [
            "1,106 person per sq km",
            "1,006 person per sq km",
            "1,306 person per sq km",
            "1,206 person per sq km"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "District with highest population density in Bihar",
        "answer": "Sheohar",
        "choices": [
            "Sheohar",
            "Sheikhpura",
            "Patna",
            "Kaimur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "District with least population density in Bihar",
        "answer": "Kaimur",
        "choices": [
            "Kaimur",
            "Sheikhpura",
            "Patna",
            "Sheohar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Most populated district of Bihar",
        "answer": "Patna",
        "choices": [
            "Patna",
            "Kaimur",
            "Sheohar",
            "Sheikhpura"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Least populated district of Bihar",
        "answer": "Sheikhpura",
        "choices": [
            "Sheikhpura",
            "Patna",
            "Kaimur",
            "Sheohar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Sex Ratio of Bihar according to Census 2011",
        "answer": 918,
        "choices": [
            918,
            819,
            981,
            891
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Child Sex Ratio of Bihar according to Census 2011",
        "answer": 935,
        "choices": [
            935,
            918,
            953,
            943
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "District with highest sex ratio in Bihar",
        "answer": "Gopalganj",
        "choices": [
            "Gopalganj",
            "Munger",
            "Patna",
            "Rohtas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "District with least sex ratio in Bihar",
        "answer": "Munger",
        "choices": [
            "Munger",
            "Gopalganj",
            "Patna",
            "Rohtas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Literacy rate of Bihar according to Census 2011",
        "answer": "61.80 percent",
        "choices": [
            "61.80 percent",
            "68.10 percent",
            "81.60 percent",
            "86.10 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "District with highest literacy rate in Bihar",
        "answer": "Rohtas",
        "choices": [
            "Rohtas",
            "Patna",
            "Purnea",
            "Munger"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "District with lowest literacy rate in Bihar",
        "answer": "Purnea",
        "choices": [
            "Purnea",
            "Patna",
            "Rohtas",
            "Munger"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "What is the urbanisation rate of Bihar according to Census 2011",
        "answer": "11.29 percent",
        "choices": [
            "11.29 percent",
            "21.92 percent",
            "12.29 percent",
            "12.92 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Most urbanised district of Bihar",
        "answer": "Patna",
        "choices": [
            "Patna",
            "Vaishali",
            "Gaya",
            "Nalanda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Least urbanised district of Bihar",
        "answer": "Munger",
        "choices": [
            "Munger",
            "Gopalganj",
            "Buxar",
            "Bhojpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "What is the tribal population of Bihar compared to India according to Census 2011",
        "answer": "1.30 percent",
        "choices": [
            "1.30 percent",
            "1.68 percent",
            "1.03 percent",
            "1.86 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "What is the tribal population of Bihar compared to India according to Caste Survey 2022",
        "answer": "1.68 percent",
        "choices": [
            "1.68 percent",
            "1.30 percent",
            "1.03 percent",
            "1.86 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Rank of Bihar among all state & UTs of India in terms of Population",
        "answer": "3rd",
        "choices": [
            "3rd",
            "1st",
            "2nd",
            "4th"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Rank of Bihar among all state & UTs of India in terms of Area",
        "answer": "12th",
        "choices": [
            "12th",
            "11th",
            "13th",
            "10th"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Decadal population growth of Bihar till 2011",
        "answer": "25.42 percent",
        "choices": [
            "25.42 percent",
            "24.52 percent",
            "25.24 percent",
            "24.25 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Total seats in Bihar Vidhan Shabha (Legislative Assembly)",
        "answer": 243,
        "choices": [
            243,
            234,
            245,
            254
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Total seats in Bihar Vidhan Parishad (Legislative Council)",
        "answer": 75,
        "choices": [
            75,
            85,
            65,
            95
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Total Lok Shabha seats from Bihar",
        "answer": 40,
        "choices": [
            40,
            35,
            45,
            50
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Total Rajya Shabha seats from Bihar",
        "answer": 16,
        "choices": [
            16,
            15,
            14,
            18
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who was the first Governor of Bihar post independence",
        "answer": "Shri Jairam Daulatram",
        "choices": [
            "Shri Jairam Daulatram",
            "Shri Krishna Sinha",
            "Shri Rajendra Prasad",
            "Shri Arif Mohammad Khan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who was the first Chief Minister of Bihar",
        "answer": "Shri Krishna Sinha",
        "choices": [
            "Shri Krishna Sinha",
            "Shri Jairam Daulatram",
            "Shri Rajendra Prasad",
            "Shri Arif Mohammad Khan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Bihar state is situated in the north of",
        "answer": "Tropic of Cancer",
        "choices": [
            "Tropic of Cancer",
            "Tropic of Capricon",
            "Equator",
            "Artic Circle"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "In which district of Bihar Dharwad period rocks are found",
        "answer": "All of these",
        "choices": [
            "All of these",
            "Munger",
            "Jamui",
            "Navada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "In which district of Bihar Vindhyan series rocks are found",
        "answer": "Kaimur & Rohtas",
        "choices": [
            "Kaimur & Rohtas",
            "Kaimur",
            "Rohtas",
            "Gaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "When were rocks of Vindhyan series formed",
        "answer": "Pre-Cambrian Period",
        "choices": [
            "Pre-Cambrian Period",
            "Tertiary Period",
            "Quaternary Period",
            "Cambrian Period"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "When were rocks of Dharwad series formed",
        "answer": "Archeon",
        "choices": [
            "Archeon",
            "Protetozoic",
            "Milocene",
            "Pliestocene"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Tertiary rocks are found in which Himalayan series",
        "answer": "Shivalik",
        "choices": [
            "Shivalik",
            "Aravali",
            "Lesser Himalaya",
            "Greater Himalaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Kaimur or Rohtas plateau is part of",
        "answer": "Vindhya",
        "choices": [
            "Vindhya",
            "Aravali",
            "Satpuda",
            "Dharwad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Kaimur plateau is seperated from Chhota-Nagpur plateau by which river",
        "answer": "Son",
        "choices": [
            "Son",
            "Mahananda",
            "Ganga",
            "Falgu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "New Alluvium soil is also known as",
        "answer": "Khadar",
        "choices": [
            "Khadar",
            "Bhangar",
            "Terai",
            "Keral-Keval"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Terai Soil is found along which border of Bihar",
        "answer": "Northern",
        "choices": [
            "Northern",
            "Southern",
            "Eastern",
            "Western"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Peidmont Swamp soil is found in which district of Bihar",
        "answer": "West Champaran",
        "choices": [
            "West Champaran",
            "Rohtas",
            "Kaimur",
            "Gaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "What do we extract from Pyrite mineral",
        "answer": "Sulphur",
        "choices": [
            "Sulphur",
            "Asbestos",
            "Sand",
            "Tungusten"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Pyrite is mainly found in which district of Bihar",
        "answer": "Rohtas",
        "choices": [
            "Rohtas",
            "Jamui",
            "Samstipur",
            "Banka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which mineral is also known as Fool's Gold",
        "answer": "Pyrite",
        "choices": [
            "Pyrite",
            "Bauxite",
            "Hematite",
            "Quartzite"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Gold reserve of Bihar",
        "answer": "Jamui",
        "choices": [
            "Jamui",
            "Purnea",
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Munger"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "According to Koppen climate classification, Bihar falls under which category",
        "answer": "Cwa",
        "choices": [
            "Cwa",
            "Cfb",
            "Bwh",
            "Csc"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The most famous river for changing its route in Bihar is",
        "answer": "Kosi",
        "choices": [
            "Kosi",
            "Bagmati",
            "Gandak",
            "Mahananda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which river flows from west to east in the middle of Bihar",
        "answer": "Ganga",
        "choices": [
            "Ganga",
            "Bagmati",
            "Gandak",
            "Mahananda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "State the total length of Ganga in kms",
        "answer": "2525 km",
        "choices": [
            "2525 km",
            "5050 km",
            "2550 km",
            "5025 km"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "What is the length of Ganga within territory of Bihar",
        "answer": "445 km",
        "choices": [
            "445 km",
            "545 km",
            "345 km",
            "245 km"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is the origin of the river Ganga",
        "answer": "Uttrakhand",
        "choices": [
            "Uttrakhand",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Himachal Pradesh",
            "West Bengal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Ganga river first enters in which district of Bihar from Uttar Pradesh",
        "answer": "Buxar",
        "choices": [
            "Buxar",
            "Saran",
            "Bhojpur",
            "Siwan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which of the following rivers decide the borders of Bihar and Uttar Pradesh",
        "answer": "All of these",
        "choices": [
            "All of these",
            "Ganga",
            "Gandak",
            "Karmanasha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The river Ganga touches how many districts of Bihar",
        "answer": 12,
        "choices": [
            12,
            11,
            10,
            13
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which district of Bihar touches the river Ganga the longest",
        "answer": "Patna",
        "choices": [
            "Patna",
            "Munger",
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Katihar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The river Ganga terminates in",
        "answer": "Bay of Bengal",
        "choices": [
            "Bay of Bengal",
            "Indian Ocean",
            "Pacific Ocean",
            "Arabian Sea"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which river enters into Ganga 10 kms away from Danapur near west Maner",
        "answer": "Sone",
        "choices": [
            "Sone",
            "Punpun",
            "Falgu",
            "Gandak"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Origin of river Ghagra",
        "answer": "Nepal",
        "choices": [
            "Nepal",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Uttarakhand",
            "Himachal Pradesh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which of the following rivers is also known as Saryu",
        "answer": "Ghaghra",
        "choices": [
            "Ghaghra",
            "Gandak",
            "Punpun",
            "Son"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Ghaghra river merges with Ganga in which district of Bihar",
        "answer": "Saran",
        "choices": [
            "Saran",
            "Vaishali",
            "Bhojpur",
            "Buxar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The river Gandak enters in which district of Bihar first",
        "answer": "West Champaran",
        "choices": [
            "West Champaran",
            "Gopalganj",
            "Buxar",
            "Siwan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "In which district Valmiki Nagar Barrage has been built",
        "answer": "West Champaran",
        "choices": [
            "West Champaran",
            "Gopalganj",
            "Buxar",
            "Siwan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Valmiki Nagar Barrage is built upon which river",
        "answer": "Gandak",
        "choices": [
            "Gandak",
            "Son",
            "Kosi",
            "Ganga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Name of the world famous fair held at the confluence of Gandak river",
        "answer": "Harihar Kshetra Mela",
        "choices": [
            "Harihar Kshetra Mela",
            "Pitrpaksha Mela",
            "Makar Sankranti Mela",
            "Babadham Mela"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "World's largest cattle fair is organised at confluence of which river",
        "answer": "Gandak",
        "choices": [
            "Gandak",
            "Son",
            "Kosi",
            "Ganga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which river flows in the eastern part parallel to the river Gandak",
        "answer": "Budhi Gandak",
        "choices": [
            "Budhi Gandak",
            "Saryu",
            "Karmanasha",
            "Bagmati"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which river has it's origin in Chautarva Chaur near Vishambharpur under Someshwar series hills",
        "answer": "Budhi Gandak",
        "choices": [
            "Budhi Gandak",
            "Gandak",
            "Bagmati",
            "Kosi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which of the following rivers has shifted 150 kms from east to west in the last 200 years",
        "answer": "Kosi",
        "choices": [
            "Kosi",
            "Gandak",
            "Bagmati",
            "Mahananda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "At which place the river Kosi forms a delta before merging with river Ganga",
        "answer": "Kursela",
        "choices": [
            "Kursela",
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Chhapra",
            "Hajipur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which of the following is the major tributary of Budhi-Gandak",
        "answer": "Bagmati",
        "choices": [
            "Bagmati",
            "Gandak",
            "Punpun",
            "Kosi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The origin of Bagmati has occurred in Nepal from which mountain range",
        "answer": "Mahabharat",
        "choices": [
            "Mahabharat",
            "Annapurna",
            "Aravali",
            "Someshwar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which river enters in Terai area after passing through Mahabharat range in Nepal",
        "answer": "Budhi-Gandak",
        "choices": [
            "Budhi-Gandak",
            "Kamala",
            "Gandak",
            "Punpun"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Ancient name of river Kosi",
        "answer": "Kaushiki",
        "choices": [
            "Kaushiki",
            "Saptaprabha",
            "Keshaki",
            "Kaushik"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "All the seven currents of Kosi merge at which place where it also known as Sapta Kosi",
        "answer": "Triveni (Nepal)",
        "choices": [
            "Triveni (Nepal)",
            "Balmiki Nagar",
            "Rajgir",
            "Pavapuri"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which of the following river is also known as Bihar ka shok",
        "answer": "Kosi",
        "choices": [
            "Kosi",
            "Mahananda",
            "Gandak",
            "Son"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Mount Everest and Kanchenjunga falls under catchement area of which river",
        "answer": "Kosi",
        "choices": [
            "Kosi",
            "Mahananda",
            "Gandak",
            "Son"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which of the following rivers is a river of the east following through North Bihar",
        "answer": "Mahananda",
        "choices": [
            "Mahananda",
            "Kamala",
            "Bagmati",
            "Son"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which river determines the borders of Bengal & Bihar",
        "answer": "Mahananda",
        "choices": [
            "Mahananda",
            "Kamala",
            "Bagmati",
            "Son"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Origin of which river lies in Amarkantak in Madhya Pradesh",
        "answer": "Son",
        "choices": [
            "Son",
            "Bagmati",
            "Punpun",
            "Falgu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which river is the longest flowing tributary of the Ganga in Southern Bihar",
        "answer": "Son",
        "choices": [
            "Son",
            "Karmanasha",
            "Punpun",
            "Falgu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Son river first enters in which district of Bihar",
        "answer": "Rohtas",
        "choices": [
            "Rohtas",
            "Jamui",
            "Gaya",
            "Jehanabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "On which of the following rivers Indrapuri Barrage is located",
        "answer": "Son",
        "choices": [
            "Son",
            "Gandak",
            "Punpun",
            "Falgu"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "On the riverbed of which of the following rivers, Gautam Buddha attained awakening",
        "answer": "Falgu",
        "choices": [
            "Falgu",
            "Gandak",
            "Punpun",
            "Son"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where in Bihar, Pitrapaksha Mela is held",
        "answer": "Gaya",
        "choices": [
            "Gaya",
            "Patna",
            "Sonpur",
            "Bhagalpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "In which of the following rivers, the ritual of Pind-dan is performed",
        "answer": "Falgu",
        "choices": [
            "Falgu",
            "Gandak",
            "Punpun",
            "Son"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which river gets divided in two parts in Jehanabad district near Barabar Hills",
        "answer": "Falgu",
        "choices": [
            "Falgu",
            "Karmanasha",
            "Punpun",
            "Son"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Origin of the river Punpun",
        "answer": "Chhota-Nagpur Plataeu",
        "choices": [
            "Chhota-Nagpur Plataeu",
            "Kaimur Hills",
            "Aravalli Hills",
            "Amarkantak Hills"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "At which place Punpun river merges with Ganga",
        "answer": "Fatuha",
        "choices": [
            "Fatuha",
            "Maner",
            "Chhapra",
            "Danapur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which river has its ancient name as Hiranyavah",
        "answer": "Son",
        "choices": [
            "Son",
            "Gandak",
            "Karmanasha",
            "Punpun"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which art form of Bihar has a sequential representation of stories, hence also known as scroll painting",
        "answer": "Manjusha Art",
        "choices": [
            "Manjusha Art",
            "Mithila Art",
            "Tikuli Art",
            "Sujini Embroidery"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Bihula-Bishahari Gatha is related to with art form of Bihar",
        "answer": "Manjusha Art",
        "choices": [
            "Manjusha Art",
            "Mithila Art",
            "Tikuli Art",
            "Sujini Embroidery"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Origin of Manjusha Art ",
        "answer": "Bhagalpur",
        "choices": [
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Madhubani",
            "Gaya",
            "Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Origin of Tikuli Art",
        "answer": "Patna",
        "choices": [
            "Patna",
            "Madhubani",
            "Gaya",
            "Bhagalpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which art form is also know as Firangi Kalam or as the white man's art",
        "answer": "Patna Kalam",
        "choices": [
            "Patna Kalam",
            "Kalamkari",
            "Patachitra",
            "Madhubani Painting"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The subject of these paintings were common man and their mundane routines, name the art form",
        "answer": "Patna Kalam",
        "choices": [
            "Patna Kalam",
            "Sujini Embroidery",
            "Manjusha Art",
            "Madhubani Painting"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Kakolat Waterfall located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Nawada",
        "choices": [
            "Nawada",
            "Rohtas",
            "Kaimur",
            "Munger"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Tutla Bhawani Waterfall located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Rohtas",
        "choices": [
            "Rohtas",
            "Nawada",
            "Kaimur",
            "Munger"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Telhar Kund Waterfall located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Kaimur",
        "choices": [
            "Kaimur",
            "Nawada",
            "Rohtas",
            "Munger"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Karakat Waterfall located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Kaimur",
        "choices": [
            "Kaimur",
            "Nawada",
            "Rohtas",
            "Munger"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Manjhar Kund located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Rohtas",
        "choices": [
            "Rohtas",
            "Nawada",
            "Kaimur",
            "Munger"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Dhua Kund located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Rohtas",
        "choices": [
            "Rohtas",
            "Nawada",
            "Kaimur",
            "Munger"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Kanwar Lake located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Begusarai",
        "choices": [
            "Begusarai",
            "Rohtas",
            "Kaimur",
            "Nawada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "How may Ramsar sites are there in Bihar as of 2025",
        "answer": "Three",
        "choices": [
            "Three",
            "Four",
            "Two",
            "Five"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Muchalinda Lake in Bihar",
        "answer": "Bodhgaya",
        "choices": [
            "Bodhgaya",
            "Rohtas",
            "Kaimur",
            "Nawada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Sarai Man Lake in Bihar",
        "answer": "West Champaran",
        "choices": [
            "West Champaran",
            "Bodhgaya",
            "Munger",
            "Rajgir"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Moti Jheel located in Bihar",
        "answer": "East Champaran",
        "choices": [
            "East Champaran",
            "West Champaran",
            "Munger",
            "Rajgir"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Pandu Pokhar located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Rajgir",
        "choices": [
            "Rajgir",
            "West Champaran",
            "Munger",
            "Rohtas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Ghorakatora Lake located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Rajgir",
        "choices": [
            "Rajgir",
            "West Champaran",
            "Munger",
            "Rohtas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which type of forest is found in Bihar",
        "answer": "Moist Deciduos",
        "choices": [
            "Moist Deciduos",
            "Dry Deciduos",
            "Moist Evergreen",
            "Dry Evergreen"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which is most abundantly found in forests of Bihar",
        "answer": "Sal",
        "choices": [
            "Sal",
            "Shisham",
            "Teak",
            "Kadamb"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "How much is the natural forest cover in Bihar",
        "answer": "7.27 percent",
        "choices": [
            "7.27 percent",
            "2.72 percent",
            "3.72 percent",
            "7.32 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "How many National Parks are there in Bihar",
        "answer": "One",
        "choices": [
            "One",
            "Two",
            "Zero",
            "Three"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Valmiki National Park is located in",
        "answer": "West Champaran",
        "choices": [
            "West Champaran",
            "East Champaran",
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Munger"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Vikramshila Gangetic Dolphin Wildlife Sanctuary is located in",
        "answer": "Bhagalpur",
        "choices": [
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Begusarai",
            "Patna",
            "Munger"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Bhimbandh Wildlife Sanctuary located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Munger",
        "choices": [
            "Munger",
            "Begusarai",
            "Patna",
            "Bhagalpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Gautam Buddha Wildlife Sanctuary located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Gaya",
        "choices": [
            "Gaya",
            "Begusarai",
            "Patna",
            "Bhagalpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Udaypur Wildlife Sanctuary located in Bihar",
        "answer": "West Champaran",
        "choices": [
            "West Champaran",
            "Begusarai",
            "Patna",
            "Bhagalpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Nakti Dam located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Jamui",
        "choices": [
            "Jamui",
            "Begusarai",
            "Patna",
            "Bhagalpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Nagi Dam located in Bihar",
        "answer": "Jamui",
        "choices": [
            "Jamui",
            "Begusarai",
            "Patna",
            "Bhagalpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The name of the Hindi weekly which was the mouthpiece of the agrarian and peasant movements in Bihar in 1940 was",
        "answer": "Hunkar",
        "choices": [
            "Hunkar",
            "Lokmat",
            "Sarathi",
            "Leader"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who was author of Hunkar - a Hindi weekly voicing for peasants in Bihar",
        "answer": "Swami Sahajanand Saraswati",
        "choices": [
            "Swami Sahajanand Saraswati",
            "Ram Manohar Lohia",
            "Jagadish Prasad",
            "Jayaprakash Narayan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who was the first provisional premier of Bihar under Provincial Autonomy in 1937",
        "answer": "Mohammad Yunus",
        "choices": [
            "Mohammad Yunus",
            "Shri Krishna Sinha",
            "Ramsunder Singh",
            "Jagdal Chaudhary"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who was the first premier of Bihar under Provincial Autonomy in 1937",
        "answer": "Shri Krishna Sinha",
        "choices": [
            "Shri Krishna Sinha",
            "Mohammad Yunus",
            "Ramsunder Singh",
            "Jagdal Chaudhary"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The first Indian National Congress session in Bihar after bcoming a separate province was held in",
        "answer": "Patna, 1912",
        "choices": [
            "Patna, 1912",
            "Gaya, 1922",
            "Patna, 1934",
            "Gaya, 1934"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Indian National Congress Session of 1922 was held at which place in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Gaya",
        "choices": [
            "Gaya",
            "Patna",
            "Munger",
            "Bhagalpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who organised the Hindu Mela",
        "answer": "Nabagopal Mitra",
        "choices": [
            "Nabagopal Mitra",
            "Satyendranath Tagore",
            "Aurobindo Ghosh",
            "Rajnarayan Bose"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who was the commissioner of Patna divison during the revolt of 1857?",
        "answer": "William Taylor",
        "choices": [
            "William Taylor",
            "H. C. Wake",
            "Brigadier Douglas",
            "R. P. Harrison"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Kunwar Singh returned to Jagdishpur Palace on",
        "answer": "23rd April 1858",
        "choices": [
            "23rd April 1858",
            "23rd April 1859",
            "26th April 1859",
            "26th April 1858"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "When did Kunwar Singh, leader of revolt of 1857 in Bihar, breathed his last?",
        "answer": "26th April 1858",
        "choices": [
            "26th April 1858",
            "23rd April 1859",
            "23rd April 1858",
            "26th April 1859"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Veer Kunwar Singh was the king of",
        "answer": "Jagadishpur",
        "choices": [
            "Jagadishpur",
            "Dheerpur",
            "Rampur",
            "Hamirpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who fought bravely against the British troops under Brigadier Douglas on 21 April, 1858 in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Kunwar Singh",
        "choices": [
            "Kunwar Singh",
            "Ujjal Sahi",
            "Surendra Sahi",
            "Jagdal Choudhary"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Name the revolutionary from Bihar who attended the meeting of Hindustan Socialist Republican Army in September, 1928",
        "answer": "Phanindra Nath Ghosh",
        "choices": [
            "Phanindra Nath Ghosh",
            "Bhagat Singh",
            "Ajay Ghosh",
            "Jyotindra Nath"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Patna was made capital of his state by",
        "answer": "Shershah Suri",
        "choices": [
            "Shershah Suri",
            "Alauddin Hussain Shah",
            "Ibrahim Lodi",
            "Prince Azim"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who was the mentor of Birsa Munda?",
        "answer": "Anand Pandey",
        "choices": [
            "Anand Pandey",
            "Swami Sahajanand Saraswati",
            "Jatra Bhagat",
            "M. N. Roy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "When was Birsa Munda born",
        "answer": "15th November 1875",
        "choices": [
            "15th November 1875",
            "15th November 1975",
            "15th November 1965",
            "15th November 1865"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Birsa Munda was captured in Chakradharpur, while asleep on",
        "answer": "3rd February 1900",
        "choices": [
            "3rd February 1900",
            "1st February 1900",
            "2nd February 1900",
            "4th February 1900"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Identify the region where Santhals declared their government in 1855-56",
        "answer": "Bhagalpur-Rajmahal",
        "choices": [
            "Bhagalpur-Rajmahal",
            "Munger-Bhagalpur",
            "Gaya-Munger",
            "Shahabad-Gaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Bihar Herald was started in 1872 by",
        "answer": "Babu Guru Prasad Sen",
        "choices": [
            "Babu Guru Prasad Sen",
            "Munahi Surajmal",
            "Rai Roshan Lal",
            "Krishan Bhatt"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which was the first English newspaper published from Patna?",
        "answer": "The Bihar Herald",
        "choices": [
            "The Bihar Herald",
            "The Indian Mirror",
            "Searchlight",
            "Hindoo Patriot"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The revolt of 1857 affected many towns of Bihar, Which of the following is the correct sequence of the occurrence of revolt in various town of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Rohini > Patna > Muzaffarpur > Jagdishpur",
        "choices": [
            "Rohini > Patna > Muzaffarpur > Jagdishpur",
            "Muzaffarpur > Patna > Jagadishpur > Rohini",
            "Jagadishpur > Patna > Rohini > Muzaffarpur",
            "Patna > Muzaffarpur > Rohini > Jagadishpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which leader of Bihar along with Mahatma Gandhi led the farmer's movement?",
        "answer": "Raj Kumar Shukla",
        "choices": [
            "Raj Kumar Shukla",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Baba Ramchandra",
            "Rafi Ahmed Kidwai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Raj Kumar Shukla was a resident of which village?",
        "answer": "Murali Bharahwa",
        "choices": [
            "Murali Bharahwa",
            "Murali Bheet",
            "Murali Kher",
            "Murali Dhir"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who highlighted the plight of the peasants of Champaran by writing psedonyms like Dukhi, Dukhi Atma, Dukhi Hriday?",
        "answer": "Pir Mohaammed Munis",
        "choices": [
            "Pir Mohaammed Munis",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Rajkumar Shukla",
            "Sahajanand Saraswati"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who was the author of Biography of Kunwar Singh and Amar Singh",
        "answer": "Kalikinkar Datta",
        "choices": [
            "Kalikinkar Datta",
            "M. N. Roy",
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Sahajanand Saraswati"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Swami Sahajanand Saraswati published a magazine named",
        "answer": "Hunkar",
        "choices": [
            "Hunkar",
            "Jankranti",
            "Krishak Samachar",
            "Vidrohi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "One of the popular beliefs in Bihar during the Non-Cooperation Movement of 1920-22 was that they would be victorious because Gandhi",
        "answer": "was an accomplished politician",
        "choices": [
            "was an accomplished politician",
            "was the epitome of Dharma",
            "knew the way to defeat the English",
            "knew English"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "On which date Linlithgow ordered to fire on the mob of Patna and its surrounding during the August Revolution, 1942?",
        "answer": "11th August 1942",
        "choices": [
            "11th August 1942",
            "1st August 1942",
            "15th August 1942",
            "5th August 1942"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Dr. Rajendra Prasad, who was the first President of India, earlier held the position of",
        "answer": "Chairman of Patna Municipality",
        "choices": [
            "Chairman of Patna Municipality",
            "Chief Minister of Bihar",
            "Head Postmaster at Chapra",
            "Mayor of Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where was the first Zila School of Bihar opened in 1835",
        "answer": "Patna",
        "choices": [
            "Patna",
            "Muzaffarpur",
            "Darbhanga",
            "Munger"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who left Patna College with just 20 days remaining for his examination during the Non-Cooperation movement?",
        "answer": "Jai Prakash Narayan",
        "choices": [
            "Jai Prakash Narayan",
            "Rajendra Prasad",
            "Braj Kishore",
            "Shri Krishna Sinha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Jubba Sahni, a freedom fighter belonged to which district of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Muzaffarpur",
        "choices": [
            "Muzaffarpur",
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Patna",
            "Sasaram"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who led cultivators in Bihar during the Non-Cooperation Movement?",
        "answer": "Swami Vidyanand",
        "choices": [
            "Swami Vidyanand",
            "Shri Krishna Sinha",
            "Raj Kumar Shukla",
            "Sahajanand Saraswati"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who led the peasant movement in the region of Darbhanga Raj?",
        "answer": "Swami Vidyanand",
        "choices": [
            "Swami Vidyanand",
            "Baba Ramchandra",
            "Vinoba Bhave",
            "Sahajanand Saraswati"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "During Salt Satyagraha, in Bihar, in addition to making salt, the people choose to oppose the government by opposing which tax?",
        "answer": "Chowkidari",
        "choices": [
            "Chowkidari",
            "Haathi",
            "Malba",
            "Development"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "When was the Salt Movement started in Bihar?",
        "answer": "12th March 1930",
        "choices": [
            "12th March 1930",
            "12th April 1930",
            "12th May 1930",
            "12th June 1930"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Famous sufi saint of Bihar Sharfuddin Maneri is related to which Sufi order?",
        "answer": "Firdausi",
        "choices": [
            "Firdausi",
            "Chisti",
            "Suhrawardi",
            "Kubrawi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who was the first Muslim conqueror of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Bakhtiyar Khalji",
        "choices": [
            "Bakhtiyar Khalji",
            "Malik Ibrahim",
            "Iltutmish",
            "Ali Mardan Khalji"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Baba Thakur Das established which society in Patna?",
        "answer": "Ramakrishna Mission Society",
        "choices": [
            "Ramakrishna Mission Society",
            "Servants of India Society",
            "Seva Samiti",
            "Social Service League"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who established the branch of Anushila Samiti at Patna in 1913",
        "answer": "Sachindra Nath Sanyal",
        "choices": [
            "Sachindra Nath Sanyal",
            "Bankim Chandra Mitra",
            "Raghubir Singh",
            "Baba Thakur Das"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who established Swaraj Dal in Bihar",
        "answer": "Shri Krishna Sinha",
        "choices": [
            "Shri Krishna Sinha",
            "Bankim Chandra Mitra",
            "Ramlal Singh",
            "Rajendra Prasad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Bihar Congress Socialist Party was formed in ",
        "answer": 1934,
        "choices": [
            1934,
            1939,
            1931,
            1930
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Bihar Socialist party was born in 1934 with its secretary",
        "answer": "Jayaprakash Narayan",
        "choices": [
            "Jayaprakash Narayan",
            "Acharya Narendra Dev",
            "Rambriksh Benipuri",
            "Karpoori Thakur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who formed the Bihar Samajwadi Party in 1931",
        "answer": "Phoolan Prasad Verma & Jayaprakash Narayan",
        "choices": [
            "Phoolan Prasad Verma & Jayaprakash Narayan",
            "Phoolchand Tiwari & Rajendra Prasad",
            "Rajkumar Shukla & Swami Agnivesh",
            "Swami Sahajanand & Swami Yogananda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "When was Bihar Samajwadi Party formed",
        "answer": 1931,
        "choices": [
            1931,
            1934,
            1939,
            1930
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Bihar Provincial Kisan Sabha was formed in",
        "answer": 1929,
        "choices": [
            1929,
            1934,
            1939,
            1930
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who started the Kisan Sabha Movement in Bihar in 1929?",
        "answer": "Swami Sahajanand Saraswati",
        "choices": [
            "Swami Sahajanand Saraswati",
            "Raj Kumar Shukla",
            "Baikuntha Shukla",
            "Acharya Kripalani"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Name the left-wing leader of Bihar Provincial Kisan Sabha who popularised this in Bihar?",
        "answer": "karyanand Sharma",
        "choices": [
            "karyanand Sharma",
            "Wadhwa Ram",
            "P. C. Joshi",
            "Raj Kumar Shukla"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The first Indian Ministry in Bihar in 1937 came into existence under whose leadership?",
        "answer": "Md. Yunus",
        "choices": [
            "Md. Yunus",
            "Shri Krishna Sinha",
            "Wahab Ali",
            "G. S. Lal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The elected Government of Bihar resigned in February 1938 for which reason?",
        "answer": "For the release of political prisoners",
        "choices": [
            "For the release of political prisoners",
            "the participation of India in war",
            "Satyagraha against the British at the call of Gandhi",
            "High taxes being imposed by British"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who led the Ambari Satyagraha in 1939 in Bihar",
        "answer": "Rahul Sankrityayan",
        "choices": [
            "Rahul Sankrityayan",
            "Yadunandan Sharma",
            "Swami Sahajanand",
            "Swami Yoganand"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Who among the following was the leader of the first Congress Ministry in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Shri Krishna Sinha",
        "choices": [
            "Shri Krishna Sinha",
            "Abdul Bari",
            "Anugrah Narayan Sinha",
            "Jayaprakash Narayan"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Gandhiji's Non-Cooperation movement urged people to avoid alcohol. This resulted in a serious loss of revenue for the government. The government of a province circulated a list of prominent individuals who drank alcohol as a device to persuade people to start drinking again. Name the province",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Bombay",
            "Gujarat",
            "Andhra Pradesh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which of the following statement is correct about the Maharajas of Dumrao, Darbhanga and Hatwa during the revolt of 1857",
        "answer": "They helped the English with men and money",
        "choices": [
            "They helped the English with men and money",
            "They helped the English with men but not money",
            "They helped the English with only money but not men",
            "They opposed the English"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The word Bihar originally means",
        "answer": "Buddhist Monastery",
        "choices": [
            "Buddhist Monastery",
            "Land of Angels",
            "Arya Pradesh",
            "Land of Greenry"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "According to following districts, which one has larger area under dense deciduous forest cover?",
        "answer": "Paschim Champaran",
        "choices": [
            "Paschim Champaran",
            "Gaya",
            "Kaimur",
            "Nawada"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "How many UNESCO World Heritage site is there in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Two",
        "choices": [
            "Two",
            "One",
            "Three",
            "Four"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which river divides the northern plain area of Bihar into two parts?",
        "answer": "Bagmati",
        "choices": [
            "Bagmati",
            "Ganga",
            "Gandak",
            "Kosi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which one of the following soils in not found in the Northern Gangetic Plain of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Balthar Mitti",
        "choices": [
            "Balthar Mitti",
            "New Alluvial (Khadar)",
            "Marshy Soil",
            "Bal Sundari Mitti"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The most predominant type of soil found in Bihar is",
        "answer": "Alluvial Soil",
        "choices": [
            "Alluvial Soil",
            "Laterite Soil",
            "Yellow & Red Soil",
            "Black Soil"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which river system is primarily responsible for the formation of the alluvial soils in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Ganga",
        "choices": [
            "Ganga",
            "Godavari",
            "Son",
            "Mahanadi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which district of Bihar is known for patches of laterite soil?",
        "answer": "Gaya",
        "choices": [
            "Gaya",
            "Patna",
            "Purnea",
            "Sitamarhi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Red and yellow soils in Bihar are mainly found in:",
        "answer": "South Bihar Plateau region",
        "choices": [
            "South Bihar Plateau region",
            "North Bihar plains",
            "Floodplains of Kosi",
            "Champaran region"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The soil in the Kosi river basin of Bihar is often less fertile due to:",
        "answer": "Sand Deposition",
        "choices": [
            "Sand Deposition",
            "Salinity",
            "Excess Clay",
            "Rocky Texture"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Harha Valley in Bihar lies between which two geographical features?",
        "answer": "Someshwar Range and Ramnagar Dun",
        "choices": [
            "Someshwar Range and Ramnagar Dun",
            "Chotanagpur Plateau and Rajmahal Hills",
            "Kaimur Hills and Rohtas Plateau",
            "Gandak River and Koshi River"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Harha Valley is also known as:",
        "answer": "Doon Valley",
        "choices": [
            "Doon Valley",
            "Terai Basin",
            "Malwa Plateau",
            "Barind Region"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Harha River is located in which physical division of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Northwestern Shivalik–Terai Region",
        "choices": [
            "Northwestern Shivalik–Terai Region",
            "Middle Ganga Plain",
            "Chhotanagpur Region",
            "Eastern Coastal Plain"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which of the following rivers does not make boundary between Uttar Pradesh and Bihar?",
        "answer": "Son",
        "choices": [
            "Son",
            "Gandak",
            "Ghagra",
            "Karmanasha"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "From which river water comes in Triveni Canal?",
        "answer": "Gandak",
        "choices": [
            "Gandak",
            "Son",
            "Kosi",
            "Mayurkashi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where does the Budhi Gandak river meet the Ganga river?",
        "answer": "Khagaria",
        "choices": [
            "Khagaria",
            "Badalaghat",
            "Kursela",
            "Maner"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Mohana and Lilajan rivers are related to which river?",
        "answer": "Falgu River",
        "choices": [
            "Falgu River",
            "Kosi River",
            "Chandan River",
            "Kiul River"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "With which district is Chandan river related to in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Banka",
        "choices": [
            "Banka",
            "Nawada",
            "Buxar",
            "Madhubani"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Baraila Salim Ali-Zubba Sahni Bird Sanctuary located?",
        "answer": "Vaishali",
        "choices": [
            "Vaishali",
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Begusarai",
            "Rohtas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "When is Bihar Prithvi Divas celebrated?",
        "answer": "9th August",
        "choices": [
            "9th August",
            "22nd April",
            "5th June",
            "2nd October"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Someshwar Range is a part of which major Himalayan foothills?",
        "answer": "Shiwaliks",
        "choices": [
            "Shiwaliks",
            "Karakoram Range",
            "Pir Panjal Range",
            "Lesser Himalayas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which district of Bihar is home to the Someshwar Range?",
        "answer": "West Champaran",
        "choices": [
            "West Champaran",
            "East Champaran",
            "Sitamarhi",
            "Sheohar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "What is the name of the highest peak in the Someshwar Range, which is also the highest point in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Someshwar Fort",
        "choices": [
            "Someshwar Fort",
            "Rajgir Peak",
            "Kaimur Fort",
            "Girnar Peak"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Someshwar Range forms a natural border between Bihar and which neighboring country?",
        "answer": "Nepal",
        "choices": [
            "Nepal",
            "Bangladesh",
            "Bhutan",
            "China"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which river flows through the Valmiki National Park and forms the western boundary of the Valmiki Wildlife Sanctuary, located near the Sumeshwar Range?",
        "answer": "Gandak",
        "choices": [
            "Gandak",
            "Kosi",
            "Ganga",
            "Son"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "What type of rocks primarily make up the Sumeshwar Range?",
        "answer": "Sedimentory Rocks",
        "choices": [
            "Sedimentory Rocks",
            "Igneous Rock",
            "Metamorphic Rock",
            "Granite Rocks"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Apart from the Sumeshwar Range, which of the following is another major hill range in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Vindhya",
        "choices": [
            "Vindhya",
            "Aravalli",
            "Satupura Range",
            "Eastern Ghats"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Valmiki National Park is contiguous with which national park in Nepal?",
        "answer": "Chitwan National Park",
        "choices": [
            "Chitwan National Park",
            "Bardiya National Park",
            "Sagarmatha National Park",
            "Langtang National Park"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Kanti Thermal Power Station is located near which city in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Muzaffarpur",
        "choices": [
            "Muzaffarpur",
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Gaya",
            "Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which power plant, located in the Bhagalpur district of Bihar, is a major source of power for the eastern region of India?",
        "answer": "Kahalgaon Super Thermal Power Station",
        "choices": [
            "Kahalgaon Super Thermal Power Station",
            "Nabinagar Super Thermal Power Project",
            "Muzaffarpur Thermal Power Station",
            "Barauni Thermal Power Station"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "In which district of Bihar is the Nabinagar Super Thermal Power Project located?",
        "answer": "Aurangabad",
        "choices": [
            "Aurangabad",
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Muzaffarpur",
            "Begusarai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Barauni Thermal Power Station, one of the oldest power plants in Bihar, is located in which district?",
        "answer": "Begusarai",
        "choices": [
            "Begusarai",
            "Gaya",
            "Supaul",
            "Muzaffarpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is NTPC Barh Super Thermal Power Plant located in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Patna",
        "choices": [
            "Patna",
            "Begusarai",
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Aurangabad"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which city in Bihar is famously known as the 'Silk City' for its textile manufacturing?",
        "answer": "Bhagalpur",
        "choices": [
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Muzaffarpur",
            "Gaya",
            "Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The famous Tussar silk is a specialty of which city in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Bhagalpur",
        "choices": [
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Nalanda",
            "Vaishali",
            "Darbhanga"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The silk industry in Bihar primarily focuses on which aspect of textile production?",
        "answer": "Weaving and Manufacturing",
        "choices": [
            "Weaving and Manufacturing",
            "Spinning & Reeling",
            "Finishing & Dyeing",
            "Sericulture (rearing Silkwroms)"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where were the two main manufacturing plants of Bharat Wagon & Engineering Company Limited (BWEL) located in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Muzaffarpur & Mokama",
        "choices": [
            "Muzaffarpur & Mokama",
            "Bhagalpur & Nalanda",
            "Darbhanga & Arrah",
            "Patna & Gaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Electric Locomotive Factory in Madhepura is a joint venture between Indian Railways and which company?",
        "answer": "Alstom SA",
        "choices": [
            "Alstom SA",
            "Bombardier",
            "General Electric",
            "Siemens"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Dalmianagar, a major industrial hub in its prime, is located in which district of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Rohtas",
        "choices": [
            "Rohtas",
            "Kaimur",
            "Patna",
            "Gaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Dalmianagar in Bihar is known for",
        "answer": "Cement",
        "choices": [
            "Cement",
            "Silk",
            "Leather",
            "Jute"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "What river is Dalmiyanagar situated on the banks of?",
        "answer": "Son",
        "choices": [
            "Son",
            "Ganga",
            "Falgu",
            "Punpun"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Mica, a mineral used in electrical insulation and electronics, is primarily found in which two districts of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Nawada & Jamui",
        "choices": [
            "Nawada & Jamui",
            "Patna & Bhojpur",
            "Rohtas & Kaimur",
            "Jamui & Banka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Limestone, a crucial raw material for the cement industry, is abundant in which part of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Southern Plateau region",
        "choices": [
            "Southern Plateau region",
            "Ganga Basin",
            "Eastern foothills of Himalayas",
            "Northern Plains"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which district of Bihar is a known source of Quartzite, a mineral used in the production of glass and ceramics?",
        "answer": "Munger",
        "choices": [
            "Munger",
            "Kishanganj",
            "Sheohar",
            "Arwal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which mineral found in Bihar is used in the manufacture of ceramics and is often referred to as 'kaolin'?",
        "answer": "China Clay",
        "choices": [
            "China Clay",
            "Dolomite",
            "Steatite",
            "Bauxite"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Amjhore area in the Rohtas district is particularly famous for the mining of which mineral?",
        "answer": "Pyrites",
        "choices": [
            "Pyrites",
            "Mica",
            "Bauxite",
            "Gold"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Steatite, also known as soapstone, which is used for talcum powder and carvings, is found in which of the following regions of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Gaya",
        "choices": [
            "Gaya",
            "Supaul",
            "Vaishali",
            "Purnia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Gold deposits have been discovered in which district of Bihar, leading to significant geological interest?",
        "answer": "Jamui",
        "choices": [
            "Jamui",
            "Rohtas",
            "Lakhisarai",
            "Saharsa"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which district in Bihar is home to the Barauni Refinery?",
        "answer": "Begusarai",
        "choices": [
            "Begusarai",
            "Munger",
            "Patna",
            "Gaya"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Barauni Refinery was established as a result of a collaboration between India and which other country?",
        "answer": "Soviet Union",
        "choices": [
            "Soviet Union",
            "United Kingdom",
            "France",
            "United States"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which type of soil is predominantly found in the northern part of Bihar and is known for its high fertility?",
        "answer": "Alluvial Soil",
        "choices": [
            "Alluvial Soil",
            "Piedmont Swamp Soil",
            "Red & Yellow Soil",
            "Karail-Kewal Soil"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The older alluvial soil found in Bihar's plains is locally known by which of the following names?",
        "answer": "Bangur",
        "choices": [
            "Bangur",
            "Balthar",
            "Tal",
            "Khadar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The 'Tal' soil, found in the southern Gangetic plain of Bihar, is best suited for the cultivation of which crop?",
        "answer": "Wheat & Pulses",
        "choices": [
            "Wheat & Pulses",
            "Rice (Dhan)",
            "Sugarcane",
            "Tea"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Karail-Kewal soil is a type of soil that is dark in color and has a heavy texture. Where is this soil primarily found?",
        "answer": "Southern part of Gangetic plain",
        "choices": [
            "Southern part of Gangetic plain",
            "Transitional zone between the plains and plateau",
            "Mountainous region of state",
            "Northernmost districts of Bihar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Red and Yellow soils in Bihar are found in the southern plateau region. What is the primary reason for their color?",
        "answer": "Oxidation of Iron Compounds",
        "choices": [
            "Oxidation of Iron Compounds",
            "High content of phosphorus and potash",
            "Presence of humus and other organic matter",
            "Low moisture retention and sandy texture"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which of the following soil types is formed by wind-blown deposits, is light in texture, and is found along the banks of the Ganges River?",
        "answer": "Bal Sundari Soil",
        "choices": [
            "Bal Sundari Soil",
            "Bhat Soil",
            "Doab Soil",
            "Teri Soil"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The soils in the floodplains of the Kosi River are often sandy and have a high pH. What is this soil type called?",
        "answer": "Dhira Soil",
        "choices": [
            "Dhira Soil",
            "Talsand Soil",
            "Tari Soil",
            "Bhangar Soil"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Soil in Bihar is often deficient in which two essential nutrients for plant growth?",
        "answer": "Nitrogen and Phosphorus",
        "choices": [
            "Nitrogen and Phosphorus",
            "Potash and Calcium",
            "Sulphur and Manganese",
            "Iron and Zinc"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which soil type in Bihar is characterized by its reddish-yellow color, is found in the transitional zone between the plains and the plateau, and is often less fertile?",
        "answer": "Balthar Soil",
        "choices": [
            "Balthar Soil",
            "Red and Yellow Soil",
            "Bangur Soil",
            "Tal Soil"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which state in India is the largest producer of litchi?",
        "answer": "Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar",
            "Jharkhand",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "West Bengal"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which city is famously known as the “Litchi Capital of India”?",
        "answer": "Muzaffarpur",
        "choices": [
            "Muzaffarpur",
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Darbhanga",
            "Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "What is the name of the special variety of litchi from Muzaffarpur that has a GI tag?",
        "answer": "Shahi Litchi",
        "choices": [
            "Shahi Litchi",
            "Purbi Litchi",
            "China Litchi",
            "Deshi Litchi"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which of the following is the largest freshwater oxbow lake in Asia and is located in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Kabar Taal (Kanwar Lake)",
        "choices": [
            "Kabar Taal (Kanwar Lake)",
            "Ghogha Lake",
            "Baraila Lake",
            "Kusheshwar Asthan Lake"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which lake in Bihar is a declared bird sanctuary and is famous for attracting a large number of migratory birds during the winter?",
        "answer": "Kusheshwar Asthan Bird Sanctuary",
        "choices": [
            "Kusheshwar Asthan Bird Sanctuary",
            "Baraila Lake",
            "Ghogha Lake",
            "Kanwar Lake"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The Gogra-Barhila wetland, a recognized Ramsar site, is situated in which district of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Saran",
        "choices": [
            "Saran",
            "Begusarai",
            "Darbhanga",
            "Vaishali"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which of the following is a prominent man-made reservoir in Bihar, created for irrigation and power generation?",
        "answer": "Indrapuri Barrage",
        "choices": [
            "Indrapuri Barrage",
            "Ghogha Lake",
            "Kanwar lake",
            "Jal Mandir Lake"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Kusheshwar Asthan, a famous bird sanctuary, is located in which district of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Darbhanga",
        "choices": [
            "Darbhanga",
            "Araria",
            "Madhepura",
            "Katihar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The 'Ghogha Lake' is an important wetland for migratory birds and is located in which district?",
        "answer": "Bhagalpur",
        "choices": [
            "Bhagalpur",
            "Nalanda",
            "Jamui",
            "Araria"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "The monsoon season in Bihar is primarily influenced by which branch of the Indian Monsoon?",
        "answer": "Bay of Bengal branch",
        "choices": [
            "Bay of Bengal branch",
            "South China Sea branch",
            "Arabian Sea branch",
            "Andaman Sea branch"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which district in Bihar has the highest forest cover by area?",
        "answer": "Kaimur (Bhabua)",
        "choices": [
            "Kaimur (Bhabua)",
            "West Champaran",
            "Jamui",
            "Rohtas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which wildlife sanctuary is currently being proposed to become Bihar's second tiger reserve?",
        "answer": "Kaimur Wildlife Sanctuary",
        "choices": [
            "Kaimur Wildlife Sanctuary",
            "Bhimbandh Wildlife Sanctuary",
            "Udaipur Wildlife Sanctuary",
            "Gautam Buddha Wildlife Sanctuary"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which wildlife sanctuary is the largest in Bihar by area?",
        "answer": "Kaimur Wildlife Sanctuary",
        "choices": [
            "Kaimur Wildlife Sanctuary",
            "Valmiki National Park",
            "Bhimbandh Wildlife Sanctuary",
            "Nagi Dam Bird Sanctuary"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which major river, known as the 'Sorrow of Bihar,' is infamous for its frequent changes in course and devastating floods?",
        "answer": "Kosi",
        "choices": [
            "Kosi",
            "Son",
            "Gandak",
            "Mahananda"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "At which of the following locations does the Gandak River join the Ganga?",
        "answer": "Sonpur",
        "choices": [
            "Sonpur",
            "Badalaghat",
            "Chhapra",
            "Khagaria"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Which river originates from the Chota Nagpur Plateau and flows into South Bihar?",
        "answer": "Falgu",
        "choices": [
            "Falgu",
            "Son",
            "Mahananda",
            "Bagmati"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "Where is Bihar's first inland container depot (ICD) located?",
        "answer": "Bihta (Patna)",
        "choices": [
            "Bihta (Patna)",
            "Purnea",
            "Gaya",
            "Banka"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharSpecific",
        "question": "JEEViKA was initially supported by which international organization?",
        "answer": "World Bank",
        "choices": [
            "World Bank",
            "UNDP",
            "UNICEF",
            "IMF"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "What is the size of Bihar's economy at current price in 2023-24",
        "answer": "8.54 lakh crore",
        "choices": [
            "8.54 lakh crore",
            "4.64 lakh crore",
            "6.82 lakh crore",
            "9.32 lakh crore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Nominal Growth rate in Bihar's GSDP at current price for year 2023-24",
        "answer": "14.5 percent",
        "choices": [
            "14.5 percent",
            "9.2 percent",
            "10 percent",
            "11 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Real Growth in Bihar's GSDP at constant (2011-12) price for year 2023-24",
        "answer": "9.2 percent",
        "choices": [
            "9.2 percent",
            "14.5 percent",
            "10 percent",
            "11 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Which economic sector is the hightest contributor in Bihar state GVA for year 2023-24",
        "answer": "Tertiary",
        "choices": [
            "Tertiary",
            "Primary",
            "Secondary",
            "Tourism"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Percentage contribution of Tertiary sector in Bihar state GVA for year 2023-24",
        "answer": "58.6 percent",
        "choices": [
            "58.6 percent",
            "21.5 percent",
            "19.9 percent",
            "11 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Industry contributing the most in Bihar state GVA for year 2023-24",
        "answer": "Non-Metallic Mineral Production",
        "choices": [
            "Non-Metallic Mineral Production",
            "Food Processing",
            "Cement",
            "Textile"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "How much Bihar contributes in total Makhana production of India",
        "answer": "85 percent",
        "choices": [
            "85 percent",
            "90 percent",
            "80 percent",
            "75 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "What is rank of bihar among states in economic growth in India?",
        "answer": "Second",
        "choices": [
            "Second",
            "Third",
            "First",
            "Fourth"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Economic Survey of Bihar 2024-25, what is the contribution of Primary, Secondary and Tertiary Sectors in GSVA respectively?",
        "answer": "20%, 21%, 60%",
        "choices": [
            "20%, 21%, 60%",
            "21%, 60%, 20%",
            "60%, 21%, 20%",
            "21%, 60%, 20%"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Economic Survey of Bihar 2024-25, which of the following is the largest contributor in the GSVA for primary sector?",
        "answer": "Crops",
        "choices": [
            "Crops",
            "Fishery",
            "Forestry",
            "Livestock"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Economic Survey of Bihar 2024-25, which of the following has the highest growth in the GSVA for primary sector?",
        "answer": "Fishery",
        "choices": [
            "Fishery",
            "Crops",
            "Forestry",
            "Livestock"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Economic Survey of Bihar 2024-25, which of the following is the largest contributor in the GSVA for secondary sector?",
        "answer": "Construction",
        "choices": [
            "Construction",
            "Manufacturing",
            "Electricity",
            "Gas"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Which district of Bihar has the lowest per capita income?",
        "answer": "Sheohar",
        "choices": [
            "Sheohar",
            "Sitamarhi",
            "Sheikhpura",
            "Saran"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Which district of Bihar has the highest per capita income?",
        "answer": "Patna",
        "choices": [
            "Patna",
            "Sheohar",
            "Nalanda",
            "Begusarai"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "How much is the Crop Intensity of Bihar?",
        "answer": "144 percent",
        "choices": [
            "144 percent",
            "184 percent",
            "194 percent",
            "164 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Which of the following cereal has the highest productivity in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Maize",
        "choices": [
            "Maize",
            "Wheat",
            "Rice",
            "Gram"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "As per Agriculture Census 2015–16, what percentage of Bihar’s total operational holding area is under marginal farmers (less than 1 ha)?",
        "answer": "57.73 percent",
        "choices": [
            "57.73 percent",
            "91.21 percent",
            "76 percent",
            "97 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "The combined share of operational holding area under marginal and small farmers in Bihar is approximately",
        "answer": "76 percent",
        "choices": [
            "76 percent",
            "91.21 percent",
            "57.73 percent",
            "97 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "High percentage of marginal and small farmers in Bihar indicates",
        "answer": "Land Fragmentation",
        "choices": [
            "Land Fragmentation",
            "Large-scale commercial farming",
            "Land consolidation",
            "Decline in agriculture"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Economic Survey of Bihar 2024-25 what is the per capita income of Bihar at constant price 2023-24?",
        "answer": "36,333 rupees",
        "choices": [
            "36,333 rupees",
            "66,828 rupees",
            "55,424 rupees",
            "38,555 rupees"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Economic Survey of Bihar 2024-25 what is the per capita income of Bihar at current price 2023-24?",
        "answer": "66,828 rupees",
        "choices": [
            "66,828 rupees",
            "36,333 rupees",
            "55,424 rupees",
            "38,555 rupees"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Under the Satat Jeevikaoparjan Yojana a livelihood investment fund upto what amount is allocated to a household?",
        "answer": "2 lakh",
        "choices": [
            "2 lakh",
            "1 lakh",
            "5 lakh",
            "4 lakh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "The JEEViKA program of Bihar was launched in which year?",
        "answer": 2006,
        "choices": [
            2006,
            2005,
            2010,
            2018
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "What is the Gross Fixed Capital formation at current prices for Bihar in 2023-24?",
        "answer": "4.6 percent",
        "choices": [
            "4.6 percent",
            "10 percent",
            "11.4 percent",
            "5.9 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "What is the unemployment rate in Bihar in 2023-24?",
        "answer": "3 percent",
        "choices": [
            "3 percent",
            "4.3 percent",
            "4.5 percent",
            "5.4 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "According to Bihar Economic Survey 2024-25, what is the per capita energy consumption in Bihar in 2023-24?",
        "answer": "363 kWh",
        "choices": [
            "363 kWh",
            "229 kWh",
            "350 kWh",
            "134 kWh"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Which of the following banks has the largest number of branches in Bihar?",
        "answer": "Public Sector Banks",
        "choices": [
            "Public Sector Banks",
            "Regional Rural Banks",
            "Cooperative Banks",
            "Private Sector Banks"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Department with highest Bihar's budget allocation for year 2025-26",
        "answer": "Education",
        "choices": [
            "Education",
            "Health",
            "Rural Development",
            "Agriculture"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "What is the size of budget as mentioned in Bihar's Budget for year 2025-26",
        "answer": "3.17 lakh crore",
        "choices": [
            "3.17 lakh crore",
            "1.37 lakh crore",
            "7.31 lakh crore",
            "1.73 lakh crore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Center of excellence for jaggery is proposed in which district of Bihar",
        "answer": "Samastipur",
        "choices": [
            "Samastipur",
            "Darbhanga",
            "Muzaffarpur",
            "Patna"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Center of excellence for Paan is proposed in which district of Bihar",
        "answer": "Vaishali (Bindupur)",
        "choices": [
            "Vaishali (Bindupur)",
            "Gaya (Tanukumpa)",
            "Samastipur",
            "Muzaffarpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Center of excellence for Nutritious Cereals is proposed in which district of Bihar",
        "answer": "Gaya (Tanukumpa)",
        "choices": [
            "Gaya (Tanukumpa)",
            "Vaishali (Bindupur)",
            "Samastipur",
            "Muzaffarpur"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Bihar Budget 2025-26, what is the projected Gross State Domestic Product (GSDP) at current prices?",
        "answer": "10.97 lakh crore",
        "choices": [
            "10.97 lakh crore",
            "9.50 lakh crore",
            "10.00 lakh crore",
            "11.55 lakh crore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Which among the following deficit is not presented by the state according to Bihar FRBM Act, 2022?",
        "answer": "Effective Revenue Deficit",
        "choices": [
            "Effective Revenue Deficit",
            "Revenue Deficit",
            "Fiscal Deficit",
            "Primary Deficit"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Bihar Budget 2025-26, how much is the expected Fiscal Deficit?",
        "answer": "2.98% of GSDP",
        "choices": [
            "2.98% of GSDP",
            "0.8% of GSDP",
            "8.29% of GSDP",
            "9.28% of GSDP"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Bihar Budget 2025-26, how much is the expected state Revenue Surplus?",
        "answer": "0.8% of GSDP",
        "choices": [
            "0.8% of GSDP",
            "1.8% of GSDP",
            "2.98% of GSDP",
            "9.8% of GSDP"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "According to the Bihar Budget 2025-26, how much was the interest payment in 2023-24?",
        "answer": "9.11% of total revenue receipt",
        "choices": [
            "9.11% of total revenue receipt",
            "11.9% of total revenue receipt",
            "10.9% of total revenue receipt",
            "1.9% of total revenue receipt"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "How much is the initial seed fund proposed for the Bihar Green Development Fund in Bihar Budget 2025-26?",
        "answer": "25 crore",
        "choices": [
            "25 crore",
            "20 crore",
            "30 crore",
            "15 crore"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "What is the share of Green budget in the General Budget of Bihar 2025-26?",
        "answer": "4.92 percent",
        "choices": [
            "4.92 percent",
            "3.50 percent",
            "1.42 percent",
            "2.41 percent"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "What is the theme for the Bihar Green Development Fund?",
        "answer": "Hari Bihar, Samriddh Bihar",
        "choices": [
            "Hari Bihar, Samriddh Bihar",
            "Hamara Bihar, Harit Bihar",
            "Harit Vikas, Nishchit Vikas",
            "Apna Bihar, Harit Bihar"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "What is the primary objective of the Tarkari Sudha outlets launched by the Bihar government?",
        "answer": "To provide fresh vegetables directly from farmers at fair prices",
        "choices": [
            "To provide fresh vegetables directly from farmers at fair prices",
            "To promote organic farming",
            "To export vegetables intentionally",
            "To set up vegetable processing factories"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Which of the following is the full form of VEGFED?",
        "answer": "Bihar State Vegetables and Fruits Development Corporation Ltd.",
        "choices": [
            "Bihar State Vegetables and Fruits Development Corporation Ltd.",
            "Vegetables and Fertilizer Development Corporation",
            "Vegetable Federation of India",
            "Vegetable Farmers Empowerment Directorate"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "VEGFED functions primarily under which department of the Government of Bihar?",
        "answer": "Department of Horticulture",
        "choices": [
            "Department of Horticulture",
            "Department of Agriculture",
            "Department of Animal and Fisheries Resources",
            "Department of Cooperation"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "The Tarkari Sudha outlets launched in Bihar are managed and operated by:",
        "answer": "VEGFED",
        "choices": [
            "VEGFED",
            "COMFED",
            "NABARD",
            "Bihar State Agricultural Marketing Board"
        ]
    },
    {
        "sheet": "BiharEconomy",
        "question": "Which model has been used for setting up Tarkari Sudha outlets under VEGFED?",
        "answer": "Sudha Dairy retail booth model",
        "choices": [
            "Sudha Dairy retail booth model",
            "AMUL model",
            "Mother Dairy model",
            "Farmer Producer Company model"
        ]
    }
]